Hey everyone and welcome to the security
operations 101 course presented by TCM
security academy. If you want to become
a sock analyst or a security analyst or
if you're already an analyst and want to
fill in some knowledge or methodology
and practical skill gaps, well, you've
come to the right place. And before we
dive in, let's cover some standard
housekeeping tasks and set the stage for
what we're going to be learning. And the
first thing I'll mention is that we're
actually limited to 12-hour uploads on
YouTube and SOCK 101 is a long course.
Uh it's about 35 hours at the time of
recording and we're always adding new
lessons and challenges and just making
changes over time, right? Um and so
doing some mental math here, we'll be
able to carve through about a third of
the way through the course during our
time together here, but just know that
it's sort of far from the full SOC 111
curriculum. And if we take a look at the
core syllabus, uh, you know, we'll be
able to cover up to sort of our lab
setup and, uh, the security operations
fundamentals and understanding where our
role fits in in the sort of grander
scheme of things. Uh, we're going to
deep dive into fishing analysis, right?
And talking about all the different
tools and methodologies that we have
available to us to identify suspicious
or fishing emails. And then we're really
going to get into network security as
well, right? And learning how we can
both collect and analyze and sort of
make meaningful connections and
correlations from network traffic. And
we're probably going to cap it off
around the endpoint security module here
and sort of just getting into talking
about how we can hunt malware at the
endpoint level. Uh but just know there
is so much more to this course that
unfortunately we cannot really fit in in
12 hours. Uh of course we're going to be
talking about the SIM or the security
information and event management system
all the way into threat intelligence and
even digital forensics and incident
response. So a very jam-packed
curriculum here. And so if you find that
you've enjoyed this sort of mini version
here, feel free to join us over at TCM
Academy for the full
course. I just want to take a moment to
talk about our sponsor for this video,
Flare Academy. Cyber threats are
evolving fast. And staying ahead is not
just an advantage, it's a necessity. And
that's where Flare Academy comes in.
Flare Academy is an educational hub
designed to democratize cyber security
knowledge. Backed by the Flair research
team and leading threat intelligence
experts, they provide accessible
training, collaborative discussions, and
cutting edge resources. With the support
of Flair's industry-leading research
team, members gain access to hands-on
insights and training while connecting
with peers and experts to tackle the
toughest and newest challenges together.
This is through practical sessions
designed to solve real world cyber
security challenges. The opportunity to
engage with industry leaders,
researchers, and fellow professionals to
grow your skills, community meetups to
share insights and experiences in both
virtual and in-person events, and
exclusive research and tools such as
access to cutting edge reports, tooling,
and intelligence from Flair's experts
tailored specifically for the community.
With Flare, you can learn and grow
through in-depth training sessions on
credential management, reconnaissance
techniques, OSENT, and much more.
Delivered by industry leaders like Jason
Hadex, and backed by Flair's research
team. You'll get exclusive access to
expertly crafted solutions, playbooks,
and session materials designed to
address real world cyber security
challenges. You'll be able to
participate in expert-led discussions
and Q&A channels and stay ahead of
emerging threats with exclusive reports,
feeds, and insights from Flair's
comprehensive cyber crime intelligence.
And verified members gain access to
premium resources and private insights
while contributing to a community that
thrives on shared knowledge. And so, if
you're ready to level up, join Flare
Academy today through the link in the
description. And so, first, I want to
quickly introduce myself. And so, my
name is Andrew Prince. I'm a security
nerd, a a sort of blue teamer by day,
and I've worked in sock environments for
a number of years. Uh, and I've even
dabbled into a bit of offensive security
as well. I work as an instructor for TCM
where I've trained thousands of analysts
across many large organizations and
industries, uh, including managed
security providers, healthcare,
manufacturing, uh, even academia and
department of defense and much more. Uh,
and to sort of balance out the
practitioner side, I also work in DFIR
consulting and security research. I have
some of my background listed here,
right? some education, previous roles,
uh some credentials and affiliations,
and some shiny collectible badges over
in the lower right along with some links
where you can reach myself and TCM
security. And so, just to preface, I
truly believe that anyone is capable of
breaking into this field. And most of
the industry professionals that I work
with and or look up to the most did not
come from a securityoriented background,
right? And I can attest to that for
myself as well. I used to work in
graphic and web design before carving my
way into the industry and uh taking more
of a traditional path of help desk to
system administration to networking and
then finally security operations and
engineering. So it took me a bit to find
sort of my calling there. But if working
on the sort of blue team and
sockoriented work is something that you
want to do or a path that you want to
start going down as you gain experience.
Well, I want to help you as much as I
can, right? Um and that's really why I
created this course to share my
knowledge and experience and basically
just my lessons learned, right? all of
the things that I wish I knew as I was
becoming a security professional. You
know, uh these are all the things that I
wish someone had sat me down and showed
me during my first sock analyst job. And
so I'm lucky to have this course as a
platform or an outlet to share my
stories and struggles from the field uh
or different insights and present all of
this along with endless hours of
research and compilation putting all of
this together into an engaging and
practical format for you to learn from.
And so all of that to say, I really hope
you enjoy the course and find value from
the passion that was put into it. Before
we cover the course objectives, well,
let's first talk about why would you
want to take this course in the first
place. You're here, right? So, you're
obviously interested in the topic, but
specifically, there are a number of
important tangible takeaways that I want
you to get out of this course. The first
one here is well, something that we
truly stand for at TCM, which is
practicality. And so, this course, save
for the foundation section, is going to
have a practical focus. First, I'm going
to dive into real tools and realistic
scenarios and walk you through hands-on
labs that you can follow along with and
complete yourself and treat as projects
and discussion points during job
interviews. Additionally, there is
absolutely a shortage of skilled sock
analysts and blue teamers in the
industry, especially right now.
Organizations are looking for talent
with hands-on experience and practical
skills. And it's true that many skills
and tools can and will be taught on the
job, but having exposure to the domains
covered in this course is going to give
you such a strong leg up and an ability
to speak intelligently with hiring
managers and future
colleagues, which ties into job
readiness, right? And so having tangible
skills and experience within these
domains is going to build up such a
strong holistic view of blue team
operations and fill any knowledge gaps
that you had previously and honestly
just set you on the right path.
And even if you're already in the
industry, even as a sock analyst, well,
I trust that we'll be able to fill in
some gaps here and level up your blue
team skill set, right? There might be
tools or methodologies that you don't
typically see or interact with in your
day-to-day operations. And so, once
again, giving you that holistic view and
making you as strong of an analyst as
you can
be. All right, and here we go. These are
the course objectives and all of the
topics and methodologies that I want to
cover throughout this course. And so
first of all, we want to understand the
foundational principles and practices of
a security operation center, right? And
this is really important. You know, we
need to know what makes up a sock or
even what does a sock analyst actually
do? What different tools or metrics do
they use and
follow? We want to learn techniques for
analyzing and identifying fishing
attacks, right? So, how can we safely
and accurately analyze potential
malicious emails? and also how can we
proactively protect our organizations
from fishing as
well. We want to develop skills in
monitoring network traffic for security
threats and anomalies, right? So, how
can we analyze network traffic and
gather artifacts or how can we create
detection and prevention rules to block
malicious
traffic? We're going to learn how to
monitor and analyze endpoint security
events as well, right? So, how can we
identify suspicious happenings in
processes on a system? Or how can we
work with our endpoint detection tools
to triage
alerts? We're going to learn how to use
a SIM for security event correlation and
analysis and incident management, right?
And so, this is a big one here, but
we're not just going to stick to the
SIM. So, we're going to learn how can we
analyze logs manually and also with
tools. And so, how can we search through
our SIM to investigate and correlate and
identify security incidents?
And next, we're going to take all of
this and sort of converge to learn how
to leverage threat intelligence to
enhance our security operations and
incident response, right? And so, what
indicators or models or frameworks can
we use to understand attacks better? And
how can we write and consume detection
rules to enhance our detection
capabilities? We're going to develop an
understanding of digital forensic
processes and common tools and
methodologies when it comes to
forensics, right? So, how can we acquire
and analyze forensic data and artifacts
and make conclusions?
And lastly here, we're going to
understand the process and procedures
and best practices for incident
response. And so technically everything
we're doing up to this point involves
incident response in some way, right?
We're going to talk about the core
concepts of a sock analyst to monitor,
detect, analyze, and respond. And the
response effort, well, is always going
to trickle up to any domain that we
cover here. And so we're going to learn
how organizations respond to incidents.
And what role do us as analysts play in
incident response or IR as well? And you
can see how the objectives that we just
covered here start to map nicely with
the domains and the outline of this
course. And I've kind of structured
everything in a way that builds off of
each other and flows nicely. And if
you've taken a TCM course before, well,
you'll notice that we're following a
very similar structure and format here.
And so the bulk of this course is going
to be delivered through these byite-size
video lessons. And there's going to be a
major practical focus here as well. And
so you'll be able to follow along and
set up your own lab machines to
configure security tools and install
appliances or applications and perform a
lot of hands-on analysis. And the course
will also be full of resources and links
and bookmarks for you to get your hands
on additional practice or paths or
research options to investigate anything
we cover here in more detail. And within
the public repository for this course,
there will be a bookmarks file that's
full of this kind of thing for you to
add to your own browser for reference.
And so with all of this, I'm super
excited to jump in and I really look
forward to going through all of this
with
you. Okay. And so before we get into the
lab setup, I want to quickly talk about
prerequisites and the available course
resources. And so on the prerequisite
side, there aren't too many to be
honest. This is a beginner aimed course,
but I do have to mention that in my
opinion, cyber security itself isn't
truly an entry-level field. Or to put
that another way, not always a truly
beginner-friendly field. And what I mean
by that is there's some knowledge that
is often assumed when it comes to basic
IT concepts or networking fundamentals.
And while it's not impossible to get by
without having this, well, having this
foundational understanding of these
topics will certainly make the learning
process smoother and less confusing
during certain sections. And so in terms
of some of the areas or concepts that
would be beneficial for you to be
familiar with well we have things like
networking fundamentals like I mentioned
right and so understanding the TCP IP or
the OSI model you know you don't have to
be an expert here and know it at a PhD
level and I will say I do break down the
protocols here during the network
section but knowing how different
systems interact with each other over
the network and being able to understand
things like what a subnet is an internal
versus external IP address network
address translation and how routers are
used in the network to well route
traffic through different
networks. And again, I do cover this
actually during the network security
module. And I cover the main protocols
that you're going to want to know as
well. But you know, knowing common
protocols like SSH or FTP or the
differences between HTTP and HTTPS, you
know, that kind of stuff. And then on
the endpoint side, well, it would be
beneficial to know how to navigate
Windows and Linux a little bit, you
know, and so you don't have to be an
expert in the terminal or in the command
line or PowerShell, but even just
knowing what they are, you know, basic
commands like cd and ls or cat, that
kind of thing, because we're going to be
jumping into the command line and the
terminal a lot throughout the course.
And there's no real way to throw in an
operating systems 101 section in the
course. It's already pretty bloated as
it is, but again, I'm always doing my
best to explain what commands I'm
running or what arguments or parameters
I'm using and why I'm using them. And
so, lastly, on the infosc side
specifically, there's going to be some
assumed knowledge on, you know, the
foundational security concepts like the
CIA triad or different security controls
and concepts like encryption or hashing.
Again, just knowing about these things
and why they're used is, you know, more
than good enough for
me. And while I know I do speak a bit
fast sometimes, I do try to cover
everything as verbose as possible,
sometimes to my own detriment, but just
know that I do this to make sure that
you're able to follow along, right? And
so I try not to just copy and paste
commands and run them unless they're
super redundant or not super important.
And I try to write out exactly what I'm
running and break down commands by their
arguments to give you more of that
contextual
knowledge. And so now we should also
talk about the system requirements.
And so to get the most out of this
course, I want you to be able to follow
along with the labs as much as
possible. And to do that, well, there
will be times where we need to run two
virtual machines simultaneously. And
we'll talk more about that in the lab
install section. And so we're going to
need to install a Windows and a Linux
VM. And I'll admit, I'm really not a
hardware guy. I don't really do
hardware. I more so do software. But
after basing it on my own lab setup and
looking at requirements for similar
demands, you're ideally going to want to
be running something like a 64-bit Intel
i5 or an i7, you know, like a modern
host machine with at least 8 GB of RAM
and a multi-core processor is
recommended to efficiently run multiple
VMs. And worst case scenario, you know,
if you just don't have the system
resources to run two VMs simultaneously,
or if it's just running too slow for
you, you know, feel free to just sit
back during some sections and just
follow along on a single VM. You know,
you can always up the resources for a
single VM if you're just using one at a
time, but there are always going to be
workarounds.
On the disk space and storage side,
well, you're going to want to have
around 80 to 100 GB of free storage
space on the hard drive to host the
different VMs and install tools and work
with the course files. And SSDs or
solidstate drives are recommended.
You're going to get a lot better
performance out of them, but we won't
likely get anywhere near filling up the
drives. It's more so just a theoretical
limit. And we'll be setting up dynamic
hard discs as well, and so it's only
going to fill up as much as we use them.
And again, these are just the
recommended specs.
And lastly, I just want to point you to
the public course repository which I'll
have linked down below. And I'm going to
cover this in more detail along with its
contents during the lab setup. But I
just wanted to mention that this
repository also contains some resources
that might be useful to you as you go
throughout the course and also takeaways
for you after you finish the course. And
so if you go under resources here and go
under bookmarks for example, well,
you'll see this sock_bookmarks.html HTML
file. And this is a bookmarks file that
you can download by clicking on it and
then clicking on the download icon
here. And once it's been downloaded, you
can then import it into the web browser
of your choice. And so I'll link some
documentation below on how to actually
import a bookmarks file for a number of
different
browsers. And when you do that, you're
going to have access to a number of
different curated resources and links.
and a lot of which we cover in the
course and some just for your additional
reference or learning. And it's all just
meant to be a nice takeaway for you to
reference in the field or just for you
to have as you continue on your journey.
And so I just wanted to shout out the
course repository here. And it might be
a good idea to occasionally check up on
this in case additional resources are
added in the future. Now obviously
because we want to be doing a lot of
hands-on and practical work during this
course, well, we're going to need to set
up a lab environment. And we're going to
do this using the concept of virtual
machines. And if you've never worked
with a virtual machine or a VM before or
set up any kind of lab environment like
this, well, don't worry cuz we're going
to walk through it together. But
basically, we can think of virtual
machines as a separate computer or a
system that's running on top or inside
of our host system.
And the reason why we want to use
virtual machines is so that we can
deploy things like a separate isolated
Windows instance to install our security
tools on and generate artifacts and data
all without having to configure anything
or mess with anything on our host like
our normal operating system that we use
for day-to-day work. And the other thing
is we're going to be creating some
different lab scenarios where we're
looking at artifacts that we generate
from one system onto another in real
time. And so we're going to need to
simulate aworked environment to do that.
And at most we're going to have two
separate machines or systems
running. And so with that, we're going
to need both a Windows virtual machine
to run all of our Windows commands on
and install tools and, you know, learn
to investigate Windows hosts, but also
we're going to need a Unix based or a
Linux- based operating system. Because
of course, when we think about being a
sock analyst, well, we're not just going
to be investigating and working with
Windows endpoints. Right. Many servers
run Linux and so it's just as important
for us to get a good handle on both
operating systems. And so we're going to
install a Windows 10 machine as well as
an Ubuntu machine. And to run our
virtual machines, well, we need to
install what is known as a hypervisor.
And the hypervisor is the thing that
actually creates and manages our virtual
machines and allows multiple operating
systems to, you know, share a single set
of hardware. and it provides that layer
of abstraction between the physical
hardware of our machine and our
VMs. And so the hypervisor I'm going to
be using and the one I recommend for the
course is Oracle's Virtual Box. And
that's because it's free, it's ready to
go, and it's highly featured. And so we
can use it to create snapshots. And the
installation is also really
simple. And so what we're going to want
to do on our host machine is just open
up our internet browser.
And I'm just going to do a search for
Virtual Box
download. And we should come across this
download page here. In reality, we can
just go to
virtualbox.org and then just click on
download Virtual Box. And so I will
include this actual link down below as
well as some guides if you're trying to
install Virtual Box on Mac or Linux
because you can see there's different
host packages here for whatever
operating system you're running. And so
in my case, I'm obviously on Windows.
And so I'm going to click on the Windows
host option. And that's going to start
downloading here. And once we have it
downloaded, well, we can locate the
installer file. And it should be in our
downloads folder. And so I'm just going
to open up Explorer here, go under
downloads, and we can see the installer
file. And so I'm just going to double
click on it to
run. Hit yes to this UAC prompt here.
And if you're running into this error
message here, well, we can see that we
need to have Microsoft Visual C++ 2019
installed. And so we can just search for
this
package. And so I'm going to click on
this Microsoft link here. And again,
I'll have this link down
below. And here we can find the latest
version that we need to download. And so
I'm just going to click on x64
here. And then in my downloads folder,
I'm just going to run this installer
file.
All right. So, that's been installed and
we should be good to go
now. And so, I'm just going to double
click on the Virtual Box installer
now. And we're ready to start
installing. And so, I'm pretty much just
going to roll with all the default
settings here. So, I'm just going to hit
next. We're going to get a warning about
our network interface here. It's just
going to temporarily reset and
disconnect our connection. Just keep all
the defaults selected here and then
click on
install. All right, looks like that's
finished. And so I'm just going to click
on finish here to start up Virtual
Box. And there we go. So if you're
seeing this window here, well, you're
good to go. This is the Oracle VM
Virtual Box Manager and we've
successfully installed it on our host.
And now we can use it to build out our
virtual machines that we use throughout
the course. And so let's go ahead and do
just that in the next
lesson. All right. So now that we have
our hypervisor installed, let's go ahead
and install our first operating system
that we need for the course, and that's
going to be a Windows operating system.
And so what we need to do here, I'm just
going to exit out of Virtual Box for
now. Then head back to Edge or whatever
better browser you're using. And what we
need to do is find the Windows
evaluation copy. And so we can do a
quick Google search here for the Windows
evaluation center. And I can click on
this Windows 10 Enterprise link
here. And what we could do is find the
Windows 10 Enterprise image, right? We
can download the ISO here. And we could
give Microsoft all of our information
and register. And then we'll get a link
to the ISO file which we could use to
install the VM into our hypervisor.
However, I've included a link below that
will take you right to the download
page. And so we can essentially skip
this form. And so just navigate to that
URL. And you'll see here we can select
the version that we want to download or
the language. And so I'm just going to
go under English here and make sure to
click on 64-bit
edition. And in doing that, that's going
to kick off the download for our ISO
file. And just to note here that we're
downloading a, you know, an operating
system. And so essentially, this is
going to be a pretty big file and it's
around 5 GB. And so depending on the
speed of your connection, this could
take a little bit to run. And so I'm
just going to fast forward here to when
my download's
finished. All right. And there we go.
The Windows 10 ISO file just about
finished. Yeah, there we go. And so I
now have Virtual Box installed and my
Windows ISO file has been downloaded.
And so let's get a bit of organization
going here. And feel free to do this
however you like, but I'm just going to
head to my documents folder here. And
I'm going to create a folder called
virtual
machines. And within my virtual machines
folder, I'm just going to create another
subfolder here called sock
101. And this is basically where I'm
going to store all of the virtual
machine information for the course.
And so I'm just going to open up another
explorer window here under the downloads
folder and then locate the actual ISO
file and just drag it into this sock 101
folder. All right, there we go. And so
now let's open up Virtual
Box and then click on the new button
here within this main toolbar
section. And from here we can start to
fill in all the information about the
Windows virtual machine we're creating.
And so for the name, I'm just going to
call it sock 101- Windows
10. And for the machine folder, well,
I'm just going to override the default
here. And so I'm going to click on other
and then locate the sock 101 folder
under virtual machines that I just
created under
documents. So I'm just going to select
that folder. And for the ISO image,
well, as expected, this is where we're
going to locate the actual ISO file that
we just downloaded. So again for me
that's going to be under documents
virtual machines sock 101 and this ISO
file right
here and when we do that it should
automatically recognize things like the
addition and type in version and so that
all looks good to me and so next I'm
going to make sure that I check skip
unattended installation here and then
I'm just going to click on next. Now,
for a RAM or memory size here, it's
technically possible to keep it at the
default here of 2 gigs, but I can
anticipate that you're going to run into
some limitations. And so, if you have
the capacity, it's best to bump it up a
bit. And I have quite a bit of RAM on my
physical host, and I'm actually running
a VM inside of this. And so, there's a
bit of VMion going on, but on my
physical host, I have 32 gigs. And so,
again, it all depends on what your max
capacity is. And we're eventually going
to be running two VMs at once. And so if
you can bump it up to around 6 or 8 gigs
each, well that would be great, but it
shouldn't be the end of the world and we
can always bump it up later if
needed. And so next we can add a virtual
hard disk to our machine. And
specifically, we can create a virtual
hard disk and we can keep our disc here
dynamically allocated rather than
setting aside the total amount of disc
space needed immediately. And so to do
that, just make sure you have
pre-allocate full size unchecked. And
for the storage amount, well, you can
leave it at the default of 50 GB here if
you need to. And again, if needed, we
can always adjust these values later
on. And so I'm just going to hit next
here. And we will get a machine summary
here. And this all looks good. So I'm
going to hit finish. And there we go. So
our machine's been created. And so our
new Windows VM here is staged and ready
to go. and to kick off the Windows
installation, but we can just hit start
here to start up our
machine. This might just take a
second. All right, and so here we go.
So, if you saw that Windows loading
screen and if you're now looking at the
setup window here, well, then you've
correctly set this all up. And a lot of
the install process here is going to be
pretty self-explanatory, but we can walk
through it together. And so we can first
select things like the language and the
time and the keyboard input. And all
that looks good. So I'm going to hit
next. And then just click on install
now. And this could take a moment to
initialize. And we're going to be
presented with the Windows license here.
And so feel free to read through this if
you want to take a nap.
And we can just hit accept and then
next. From here we can select the custom
installation. And now we need to
allocate the drive space. And remember
this is all virtualized. And so what I'm
going to do here is just click on new.
And it's going to automatically fill the
size of our drive. And so I'm just going
to hit
apply. And here it mentions that it's
going to create some additional
partitions which is fine. So I'm going
to hit okay. We should see another
partition there. There we go. And just
hit next.
And so now it's finally installing the
operating system. And again, this could
take a little while to complete. And so
I'll just cut ahead to when mine's
finished. All right. Now we should see
this screen here. And it's going to
mention that it needs to
restart. And once we load back in here,
we should see the main Windows
installer.
And so this is where it's going to ask
us a bunch of setup questions and
annoying little prompts until we can
finally get to our desktop. And so I'm
just going to run through this
quickly. We can select our keyboard
layout. This looks
fine. We do not need to add a secondary
keyboard
layout. It's going to do some networking
shenanigans or I guess magic they call
it.
Now again, this is going to be a lab
machine, right? And so we can kind of
skip all of the standard employee or the
intended user setup features that
Windows always asks for. And one of
these is to sign in with a Microsoft
account. And I think not. So let's click
on domain join
instead. And from here, we can set up a
local account. And so for the username
here, I'm just going to call it TCM.
And for the password, I'm going to use
the super strong password of
password. And then we just need to fill
in some security questions. So my first
pet was named
one, my childhood nickname was
two,
and and the city where I was born was
three.
And so now we can turn off all of this
dystopian you know spying and tracking
and privacy enrichment features that
Microsoft is offering. And with that we
can just click on
accept. We can ignore Cortana here. So
just click not
now. And in a moment after this little
message here we should be ready to go.
All right. And if you see this Windows
desktop here with this nice blue bright
wallpaper, well then we're good. We're
good to go. We're set up. And now there
are a few more housekeeping things that
we should do and we have to do before we
continue. And the first being, well,
let's get a bit of a quality of life
improvement up in here. And so we're not
stuck using this tiny croppedin box for
our desktop. And so to do this and use
an actual usable resolution, what we can
do here is go under devices and click on
insert guest edition CD image. And this
is going to load in an actual CD drive
into our VM. And so what we can do after
clicking on that is go under our
explorer window
here and then click on this PC and we
should see this CD drive for Virtual Box
guest editions. So I'm going to double
click on that to open it up. And from
here, I can just double click to run
this VBox Windows Edition- AMD
64. So, I'll just run this, hit
yes, and just run through the very basic
installer here. Just leave everything
default. Should take a
second. All right, sounds good. And
we're just going to reboot now after
doing that.
And when we return here, the VM tools is
going to start up as a service and we
should be able to do some more
interesting things, more interactive
things and more, you know, visually
pleasing uh, you know, integrations
within our VM
here. So, I'm just going to sign in.
And so now what I can do here is go
under the view tab and click on full
screen mode and just hit switch. And
there we go. That looks much
better. Awesome. And the other thing
that we can do now is so now our toolbar
is going to be at the bottom here. And
I'm going to go under the devices tab
and go under shared clipboard. And then
I'm going to change this from disabled
to birectional.
And so this is going to allow us to
essentially share the same clipboard
between our host machine and our Windows
VM. And so that's going to be really
useful when we want to copy and paste
commands, you know, from our host into
our VM or copy and paste output from our
VM into our host. And so just to prove
that it works, I'm going to open up the
Notepad application
here. And I know you can't see this
right now. That's off screen, but I'm
just copying the phrase hello world into
my clipboard. And if I paste it, well,
there we
go. And for example, if I just copy the
word hi here, and again, you can't see
it, but I can paste this back into my
host machine. And so our VM now is a lot
more
usable. And lastly, before we move on to
customizing this install, well, let's
take a snapshot of our base image. And
this is really important in case you
need to revert anything on your system
or if anything goes wrong throughout the
course. Well, you can always then just
revert to your base image and not have
to go through the entire install process
again, right? And you can be confident
that your VM is set up and in a state
that's ready to go. And so to do this,
I'm going to go down to our options here
and click on
machine. And then I'm just going to
click on take
snapshot. And I'm just going to title
this
base-install so I can reference it
later. Hit okay. And now our VM is going
to freeze up for a second just as it's
taking the actual snapshot, which is all
good. And so that's all finished. And
with that, we now have our base image
and we're ready for the next
steps. Okay, so in a previous lesson, we
installed our base Windows image that
you can see here. However, to get ready
for the course, we're going to need to
do a couple of quality of life
configurations and also get our course
files onto the machine. And so, let's
start up our Windows 10 VM again if you
don't already have it running. And once
we're loaded in and we're on this lovely
desktop screen here, well, what we want
to do first is some things that we would
honestly never want to do if this was a
real production system in the
enterprise. But in the case for our lab
environment and being able to interact
with our Ubuntu VM and set up some
really cool attack and defense
scenarios, well, we're going to turn off
Windows Defender, our sort of built-in
endpoint
antivirus. And again, this is because
we're going to be creating some very
basic malware later on in the course so
that we can see what kind of artifacts
it leaves on our system. And if we don't
do this step, then Defender is going to
get in the way and be really annoying
and basically just yell at us a ton,
which is nice. I really appreciate it.
But for the case of trying to showcase
some safe examples of malware, it's not
really ideal for a use case. And to
demonstrate that, well, I can just open
up a PowerShell window here. And you
don't have to follow along. Don't worry.
I'm just kind of demonstrating here. And
within PowerShell, well, I can just run
the invoke mimikats commandlet. And
don't worry if you don't know what
mimiats is. We're going to talk about it
later on in the course. Just know that
it's bad. And even if I try to run it, I
don't even have Mimiats installed on my
machine, but it's already yelling at me
that this script contains malicious
content, even though the script doesn't
even exist. It's already been blocked by
again Windows
antivirus. Another way to demonstrate
this, I'm just going to open up my
browser here, and I'm going to do a
search for the EIC test file.
And this is basically a test file
developed specifically to test out
things like the response of antivirus
programs. And it's completely harmless,
but Windows Defender should kick in and
pick it up immediately and say, you
know, hey, this might be malware as soon
as we try to download it. And so what
I'm going to do is scroll
down to the
EIC.txt file and I'm going to try to
download it. Smart screen is probably
going to yell at us and so I'll click on
more information and just click on
continue. And this is it. This is the
malware that uh Defender is already
piping up against. And so I'm just going
to rightclick and save as and just try
to save it to my downloads
folder. And immediately we got an alert
that Microsoft Defender found threats
and this file should not exist anymore.
Yeah, there we
go. And so to disable Windows Defender,
well, first what I'm going to do here is
go under the Start menu and type in
Windows Security.
and I'm going to click on the Windows
security application and go under virus
and threat
protection. From here, I'm going to go
under virus and threat protection
settings and click on manage settings.
I'm going to scroll down to tamper
protection and just check it off to turn
it
off. We're getting a warning here that
our device may be vulnerable. That's
okay. And what we want to do now is open
up a PowerShell window as administrator.
And so to do that, I'm going to go under
the start menu. I'm going to do a search
for
PowerShell. And when we see the
PowerShell application, we can either
rightclick and click run as
administrator or go down here and just
click on run as administrator. We just
hit yes to this UAC prompt. And we're
now in PowerShell as an
administrator. And from here, we just
need to run a couple of commands, which
fortunately now we can copy and paste.
And I'll have them listed down below.
The first one here is going to disable
the real-time monitoring features of
Defender. And this next one here is
going to disable the scanning of network
files. You can see we're already getting
notifications that Defender has been
turned
off. And then a couple more commands
here. And lastly, we're going to add a
key to our registry to actually turn off
Windows Defender. And so this is a long
command, so you don't have to type this
out. Again, you can just copy and paste.
And to paste into PowerShell, you can
just rightclick if you have something on
your
clipboard. So I'm just going to run
that. We can see it completed
successfully. And now if I search
Windows security again in the start
menu, go to virus and threat protection.
And you can see we have no antivirus
provider. So now what I can do is open
up PowerShell again. Again, you don't
have to follow along here. I'm just kind
of demonstrating that we can now run
invoke
mimicats. And this is not going to do
anything. So, we're going to get a
different error, but it's not going to
be the same error that it was, you know,
disabled or blocked by our antivirus.
And so, that is a plus. And if I return
to this EIC file, click on continue, and
just rightclick save as, we should be
able to save it now and open the file
with no issue.
So good. That's great. And so next, with
that out of the way, we can go ahead and
actually get our course files onto the
system. We didn't need to disable
Defender to get our course files on the
system. I'll just make that clear. But
it's for stuff that we're going to be
doing later on in the course. And so to
do this, we're going to need to install
Git, which is the version control system
that we're going to be using to clone
the course repository from GitHub. And
this is all kind of in an effort to make
sure that we're starting with the latest
files in case anything changes over
time. And so what I'm going to do here
in my browser is go to
git-cm.com. We're now on the web page
for the Git version control manager. And
under the latest source release here,
you can see in my case
2.45.2. I'm just going to click on
download for
Windows. And then under standalone
installer, I'm just going to click on
the 64-bit for Windows setup.
Once that's downloaded, I can just open
up the installer
file. Hit
yes. And I'm just going to leave
everything as the default option here.
So, I'm just going to run through this
installer. Everything looks good to
me. If you wanted to, you know, you can
read these options and make sure, you
know, you're not signing away your life
or anything like that. And it's now
going to install
All right, so Git's been installed. I'm
going to uncheck view release notes.
Don't really
care. And now what we can do is run the
git command in our command line and
actually clone
repositories. And so to do that, I'm
just going to type in cmd to open up the
command
prompt. And from here, you can see I'm
in my
cuser/tcm directory. I'm going to go
into my documents folder. So, I'm going
to CD over into
documents. And now I'm going to clone
the course
repository. And I will have the link to
this repository down below if you want
to check out the individual files. But
we're going to be cloning the entire
thing. And so what we can do here is
just run git
clone and then paste in the link to the
git
file and just hit enter. And that's just
going to take a second to
download. And there we go. And so now
with this newly downloaded
folder, well, we can unzip the course
files onto our desktop. And so to do
that, I'm going to open up an explorer
window just with this little folder
explorer icon here. And go into the
documents
folder. And we can see this sock 101
folder here. Well, this is the git
repository that we just cloned. And can
see all of the different files and
folders within
this. And so I'm going to open up the
course file directory here. And you can
see we have a number of zip files
relating to each domain or section in
the course. And so all we need to do now
is just extract each of these folders so
we get access to the contents inside.
And so all we need to do is just select
the first file here, right click on it,
and then I can click on extract all. And
what I can do is change the location of
the extracted files. And so I'll click
on browse, and then I'll just send it
over to the desktop. So I'll click on
desktop and then select folder.
I'm just going to uncheck this to show
extracted files when complete. And then
I'll just click on
extract. And all we need to do now is
just repeat that same process for the
remaining files. So I'll right click on
this one, extract all, send it to the
desktop, extract, and
repeat. All right. And so with that
done, if you wanted to, you can just
organize them the way you want to. Or
you can create a folder here on the
desktop. And I can just call this
something like sock 101 course
files. And I can just move that up to
the top here. And just highlight and
drag in everything into this folder just
so it's more
organized. And within this containing
folder, well, you can in fact see we
have all of our course files and
directories. Nice.
And to make our lives easier, you don't
have to do this step, but I will just
show it just in case. I want to add
PowerShell and the command line as
shortcuts on my desktop just cuz we're
going to be accessing them a lot. And so
to do that, I'm just going to go down to
the start menu here and type in
PowerShell. I'm going to right click on
the application and click on open file
location.
And from here under Windows PowerShell,
I'm going to rightclick, go under send
to, and then select desktop to create
the shortcut. There we go. So, we have
PowerShell. And now for the command
prompt, I'm just going to type in cmd.
And once again, same thing. Open the
file location, right click on it, go to
send to desktop.
Nice. And with that, well, we're now
good to go with our Windows VM. We're
going to install a number of different
things and tools as we go throughout the
course, but for now, we have our base
image and our base installation ready to
go. All right. And so now back on our
host, we can go ahead and install our
Linux machine. And the flavor or the
distribution of Linux that we're going
to be using is called Ubuntu Linux. And
so I'm just going to open up my browser
here and do a search for Ubuntu
download. And we should see this get
Ubuntu link here. And I'll have it
linked down below.
And from here we can go under the
desktop version because we want to have
that graphical user interface or that
desktop environment and then click on
download Ubuntu
desktop. And from here what we can do is
download the long-term support version
or the LTS version here. And for
reference in my case the release number
here is
24.04. And if you need to find older
versions for example if you're not
seeing the 24.04 04 link here. Well, you
can go down to check out our alternative
downloads
link. And from here, just go down to
past
releases and click on all past
releases. And from here, you can go
through this repository here of all the
different past versions. However, we
don't need to do that. So, I'm going to
go back. And from this download page
here, I'm just going to click on the
green download
button. And within a second, it should
start downloading.
And so again, this is a 6 GB file. And
so just be patient with the download and
let it transfer over. And once it's
complete, I'll see you again for the
next
steps. And now that we have our Ubuntu
ISO file downloaded, well, we can head
back to Virtual Box and create our new
VM. But first, what I'm going to do is
some more organization here. So I'm
going to go under my documents, virtual
machines, and the SOC 101 folder. And
I'm going to open up a second window
here to my downloads folder and just
drag over that Ubuntu ISO file into this
sock 101
folder. All right. And so from here, I'm
just going to open up Virtual
Box. And from the main page here, click
on the new
button. For the name, I'm just going to
call it sock 101- Ubuntu.
For the folder again I'm going to update
this do point to documents virtual
machines sock
101 for the ISO image of course that's
going to be our Ubuntu ISO file and we
should be good to go and so again I'm
going to check off skip unattended
installation here and hit next and so
again same kind of deal here like with
Windows and so allocate as much memory
as you can here to reasonably run both
VMs at the same time alongside ongside
your host. And to be honest, you can
kind of strategize here and sort of
overresource your Linux VM first since
we're not going to be working with our
Windows VM as much during the first
section or two. But then once we start
working with Windows more, you can then
reallocate your RAM. And so I'm going to
set my RAM to around 8 gigs here. And
for the processors, going to bump it up
to
two. For the storage space, you can
leave it at default, but I would
recommend we kind of match our Windows,
you know, storage here.
And again, make sure you have
pre-allocate full size unchecked. And we
can just hit next. Review everything.
Make sure it looks good. And I'll hit
finish. All right. And so now we have
our two virtual machines ready to go.
And now we just need to run through the
installation process for our Ubuntu VM.
And so I'm going to click on the green
start icon here. And it's going to start
booting everything
up. All right. And when this starts up
here, we can just leave it as is. You
can see it's counting down. Or we can
click into the actual machine here,
click on capture, and then we can select
the different options. And so I'm going
to keep it at the, you know, first
selection here at try or install Ubuntu
and hit
enter. And if you see this loading
screen here, well then you're good to go
so
far. And from here, we can just run
through the installation process. And so
we can choose our language. Hit
next. We can turn on some accessibility
settings if you need
to. We can set the keyboard layout, the
internet
connection. It's going to say there's an
update. You can either update now or we
can do it
later. And from here, we're going to
keep it on install Ubuntu. And then hit
next.
And we'll keep it on interactive
installation and leave it again on
default selection
here. For the recommended proprietary
software here, we can just ignore this
for
now. And for the installation screen,
well, we can leave it again on erase
disc and install Ubuntu. And don't
worry, it's not your host disc that's
going to be erased. It is the virtual
hard disk that we just created.
And so I'll just hit next. We can set up
our account. And so I'm just going to
call my account TCM. Of course, for the
computer name here, I mean, you can set
this to whatever you like. I'm just
going to call it sock
101. Again, for the username, just call
it TCM. Password. The very strong
password of password. Once
again, actually for the computer name,
I'll just change this to sock 101-
Ubuntu just in case when we're looking
at it in the logs, we can actually, you
know, differentiate it and then hit
next. We can select our time
zone and review all of our selections,
which looks good to me. So, I'm just
going to hit
install. And so, now it's installing the
actual operating system. And so, like
with everything here, this could take a
little bit. And so, we just need to wait
for it to
finish. All right. And so, that install
finally finished. We can just hit
restart.
Now, it's going to ask us to remove the
installation medium. And so, essentially
just eject the ISO file, but Virtual Box
should have done this automatically for
us. So, we can just hit enter
here. And we're now going to be taken
hopefully to the
desktop. And there we go. And so we can
see the login screen here for the user
TCM. Just going to type in my
password. And there we go. And so if
you're seeing this message here, well,
you successfully installed Ubuntu Linux.
Now, like we did with Windows, let's get
our Ubuntu machine looking better by
installing the guest editions image so
we can increase the screen resolution
and allow for things like the shared
clipboard. And so to do this, we can
open up the terminal window. And I'm
just going to right click anywhere on
the screen and click on open in
terminal. And this is going to open up
the terminal window, which is a lot like
the command line in Windows.
And so from here we can just run the
clear command to clear out that warning
message. And the first command we want
to run here is pseudoapp
update. And this command and argument
like the name suggests is going to
update all of the system package well on
our system. And so I'm just going to hit
enter there. And it's going to ask us
for a password because we're invoking
this with pseudo. And so we're running
it with elevated permissions.
And so if you run into this yellow
warning here about the unit file like I
did, well, we just need to run this
command here. So systemct ctl damon
reload. And we want to prepend it with
pseudo once again. So pseudo
systemctl
damon-reload. So there we go. And so now
what I can do is just hit the up arrow
twice to run our pseudo apt update
command once
again. And there we go. It looks like
everything is running just as
expected. And from here, we need to
install a couple of required packages
before we can actually install the guest
edition CD. And so the command we're
going to run here is pseudo apt or a
install. And then the packages we need
to install are the following. Bzip 2,
tar, gcc, make, pearl, and lastly, git.
And I'll have all these commands listed
down below. We just can't really copy
and paste them yet because we don't have
our, you know, shared clipboard ready to
go. And so I'm just going to hit
run. And when we run this, it's going to
ask us if we want to continue. And so
I'm just going to press shift Y here to
put in a capital Y and hit
enter. And those packages have now been
installed.
The next command I'm going to run is
pseudoapp
install linux- headers-g
generic. And this is going to install
the generic kernel headers, which again
is kind of high level, but it's
something we're going to need to
actually install the guest editions
image. And now what we can do is run the
same command again, but I'm just going
to modify the end here after the last
dash here. and basically just run a
subshell with the dollar sign and then
within parenthesis here I'm just going
to run the uname command with the tac r
option to essentially just sub in here
our own kernel version and you might see
this message here that we already have
you know the newest version and that's
all good and so now what we can do I'm
just going to minimize our terminal here
I'm going to go under
devices and click on insert guest
edition CD
image when we do that we should see this
little CD icon appear
I can just click on that and we can see
we have a actual directory structure
mapping to this CD. And so what I'm
going to do is open up our terminal
again. Again, that's just going to be on
the left, you know, side navigation here
under this little terminal icon. And I'm
going to CD or change directory over to
the / media
directory. Okay. And if I run an
ls, we can see the directory for my user
TCM. So I'm going to hop into there with
cdtcm and then run an ls and we can now
see the virtual box image. And so again
I'm going to change directory here into
that actual directory structure. And so
I'm just going to start typing it with
vb here for vbox. And then I'm going to
hit the tab key and it's going to
automatically fill in the name of the
directory. So I'll just hit enter. And
if I run an ls we can see a number of
different
files. And specifically this is the one
that we want to run. This vbox linux
additions.run. run file. And so to run
this file, I'm just going to run pseudo
with a dot slash here and put in the
name of the file. And that's going to be
vbox. I'm just going to start typing in
Linux and just hit tab. It's going to
autocomplete there. And then I can just
hit
enter. And that's going to start
installing everything it needs
to. And you can see it actually kind of
shrunk our resolution here. So, I
promise I didn't just troll you. This is
part of the process. And so, what we
need to do is just restart our VM now.
And so, I'm just going to run pseudo
reboot and then just give it the now
argument to make sure it reboots right
at this very
moment. And now that we're back in, what
I can do now is go under the view option
here and click on once again full screen
mode. Just hit switch. There we go.
That's looking much better now. I'm just
going to sign in here. Make sure
everything is going well. Make sure
everything's
good. Nice. There we go. And so again,
our toolbar here is now going to be on
the bottom. And what I can do is click
on devices, go under shared clipboard,
and once again, make sure that's
birectional because it's going to really
save a lot of time and a lot of typos uh
when it comes to, you know, copy and
pasting commands or outputs back and
forth.
And just to demonstrate this, I'm going
to rightclick, click on open in
terminal. And again on my clipboard, I
have hello world from my host. Going to
paste that in. Looks good. And to double
check it's working, I'm just going to
copy this. And I know you can't see
it, but that pasted in no problem on my
host. All right. And so with that, we
now have our Ubuntu VM ready to go. And
our lab is starting to come together.
And so I will see you in the next
lesson. All right, now it's time to
actually configure our Ubuntu machine.
And we just have a couple of things to
do. And so first, let's make sure we
have git installed so we can clone the
actual course repository. And we did
install it earlier. I just want to make
sure that it is actually installed in
case you didn't run, you know, one of
the commands earlier or something. Let
me just zoom in for you.
I'm just going to type in which git and
this is going to locate the actual file
itself or the binary. And fortunately we
do have it. But if you don't, you can
just run pseudo apt install
git. Type in a
password. And you can see in my case I
already have it
installed. All
right. And so now I'm just going to head
into the documents folder. So I'm going
to give it the tilda here to go to my
home directory. and then with a slash
type in the documents
folder. And from here, I'm going to
clone in the course repository. And
again, I will have this command linked
down below with the URL and everything,
but it's just going to be a get clone
command here. And then pasting in the
actual URL of the git
file. So, if I hit enter, we're going to
clone this into its own
directory. I run an ls, you can see we
have the sock 101 directory ready to
go. If I just run an ls inside of it,
well, we are good to go. And so what I'm
going to do now is open up a file
browser. And that's just going to be
this folder icon
here. And I'm going to head to my
documents folder under the sock 101
folder that we just cloned. And I'm
going to go into course files here. And
within this directory, what we can see a
zip folder containing all of the course
files for each domain in the course. And
what we need to do now is just extract
each of these folders. And you can
either extract them all at once, which
I'm going to do, or you can extract each
of them one at a time as you make it
through each section in the
course. However, the process is going to
be the same no matter what. It's just a
little repetitive, and I'm sorry about
that, but it really makes the course
more modular, so I can update each
section as time goes on.
And so what I'm going to do is just
select and highlight everything here.
And I'm going to right click on one of
the files and click on
extract. Excellent. So there we go. And
so we have every zip file here, which we
don't actually need anymore along with
the corresponding extracted folders. And
with them all highlighted, I'm just
going to drag them all to the
desktop. I can close out of this folder
here. Excellent. And there we go. And so
that's starting to look a lot
better. All right. And what I also like
to do is move this side navigation down
to the bottom like kind of like a more
standard Windows desktop environment.
Again, totally optional, but if you want
to do it, we just need to right click
anywhere on the desktop and click on
desktop icon
settings. And from this window here,
just need to scroll down to position on
screen under the dock and change this
from left oh to bottom. And there we go.
And we can also start to clean up the
different items on our taskbar as well
or our you know doc bar. And so the
first thing we can do is right click on
the actual CD icon here for the guest
editions and just click on
eject from this little help window here.
We can unpin this again by
rightclicking. Same kind of deal with
the app center here as well. And what I
will do is pin the terminal icon to the
dash because we're going to be using it
quite a
bit. And that looks good to me. And so
with all of that out of the way, there
is an install script located in the
course repository that we need to run to
install any necessary packages or
dependencies before we start jumping in.
And part of the reason why we have this
repository is in case I need to update
the list of packages that is included in
this install script, right? If I need to
include any additional packages later
on. And so if that's the case, well,
it's easy because the process doesn't
change for you. I just need to update
the script on my end. And so I'm going
to open up the terminal here.
and I'm going to head to the documents
folder. So, I'm just going to CD back
into my documents folder
here and I'm going to go into that sock
101 directory within my documents
folder. And then I'm going to go into
resources and then into the install
directory. And if I run an ls, you can
see we have this install.sh
script. And so to make it executable, we
can run the change mode command or
chmod. Give it the plus x to add that
executable bit and then provide the name
of
install.sh. And now if I run an ls,
well, it should be green. There we go.
And so now I'm just going to run the
file with dot
/install.sh. And it's just going to
update our packages and just install a
couple of things. So it shouldn't take
long at all. And just like that, the
installation has been completed and we
are good to
go. And so lastly, this is completely
optional once again, but I'm going to be
super slick here and just update the
desktop wallpaper. And so to get there,
I just rightclicked anywhere on the
desktop and clicked on change
background. And from here, I'm going to
go down to background and click on add
picture. I'm going to locate under
documents the sock 101 folder. Go under
resources under the wallpapers directory
and click on wallpaper.png.
png. And I'm just going to click on that
there. And now we're looking a lot
better in my
opinion. However, this did kind of mess
up my ordering here. So, I'm just going
to fix
this. All right. And so now we're good
to go. We just need to do a quick
networking setup and then we're ready to
jump into the course.
Now lastly, we just need to make a
couple of networking configurations
between our two VMs that will allow them
to talk to each other but not to our
physical host. And this is important to
ensure that you know both our VMs are
physically separated from our host but
logically connected to each other. And
to do this in Virtual Box, we just need
to create a network and then apply it to
the network adapters for our
VMs. And it kind of sounds complicated,
but it's really easy. And so under tools
here, I'm just going to click on the
little hamburger icon here and go down
to
network. All right. And from here, I'm
going to click on the NAT networks
tab. And then I'm just going to click on
create. And now with our sampleN or
network address translation network
created, well, I can right click on it
and go to
properties. And from here, what we want
to do well is first name it. So I'm just
going to call it TCM.
And next we need to set the IPv4 prefix.
And so this is basically going to be the
network range that our network is going
to utilize. And you can leave it at
10.0.2.0 here if you want. It doesn't
really matter. And best practice is to
keep the actual range here separate from
what your physical host is using. Or in
other words, make it look different.
Right? So if my host machine is using
192.168, you know, well, I can make my
NAT network here 10.0.2. And so they
just kind of look visually
different. But anyways, in my case, what
I'm going to do is just change this to
192. And feel free to follow along.
Again, it doesn't really matter. It's
just that anytime I reference my own IP
range during the course, well, yours
might be different if you set something
different here. And that's fine.
Completely fine. Just keep that in
mind. So
192.168.1.0. And again, I'm just going
to make it a/24 network. Going to keep
DHCP enabled. And that's basically it.
So, I'm just going to click on
apply. Now that that's ready and
created, we just need to tell our two
VMs here to use this network. And so,
I'll start with the Windows machine. I'm
just going to right click on the actual
VM name here and go to
settings and then go down to the network
tab. And the first thing I want to do
here is click through all of these
different tabs here, listing out the
different network adapter cards. And I
just want to make sure that none of them
are checked aside from adapter one here.
And under adapter 1, I'm going to make
sure it's enabled, obviously. And under
attach, I'm going to change this to NAT
network. And under name here, I'm going
to make sure it's set to TCM or whatever
you just named it. And that's all good.
I'm going to click on
okay. And I'm going to do the same thing
here for my Ubuntu
machine. Go under network again. Make
sure none of the other adapters are
selected. and under attach to net
network and make sure it's
TCM. And there we go. And so if you
want, we can verify connectivity here.
So we just need to spin up both machines
at the same time. And so we can just
click on
start. All right. And with my two VMs
running, you can see I just have them on
different windows here. I'm going to
start off with my Ubuntu machine and
open up the terminal so I can get my IP
address.
And with the terminal open, I'm just
going to run the if config
command. And so if I just hit
enter, you can see I'm getting my IP
address here under
ENP03 under inet. You can see my IP
address is
192.168.13. Over on Windows now, I'm
going to open up the command
prompt. And this time I'm going to type
in IP
config. And you can see that my IP
address is 1
192.168.1.12. And so on Windows we
have.12 and on Ubuntu here we have.13.
And so that's a good sign. It looks like
they might be on the same network. And
so what I can do now from my Windows
host is try to ping the IP address of my
Ubuntu host. And if I get a response,
well, it means they can in fact
communicate. And so that's just going to
be ping and then the IP address. And
remember, your IP addresses here might
be different, and that's completely
fine. Just make sure you're using the
right one. Don't just use mine if yours
is different. In that case, you're not
going to get the result that you want.
And so I'm going to type in
192.168.1. And my Ubuntu host ends in
13. And so if I run
this, you can see we are in fact getting
replies from our host, which is a great
sign. And just a note here, I'm pinging
my Linux host from my Windows machine.
If you try to do it the other way around
and ping your Windows machine, well, the
pings are going to fail because by
default, Windows machines block pings or
ICMP traffic. You can resolve this by
going into the Windows firewall and
allowing IPv4 ICMP packets. But don't
worry, we don't need to do that. If
you're getting pings back from your
Linux or Ubuntu machine, then you're
good. And the two systems can talk to
each other. And so there we go. So we've
finally set up our VMs. We've configured
them, customized them, and now we have
the networking set up, too. And so,
thank you for following along for this
lab setup. I know it was quite a bit,
but now we get to jump into the fun. And
so I will see you in the next
lesson. Before we get into the main
practical sections of this course, let's
first understand what a sock is, the
components that make up a sock, as well
as some important terminology that we
should be familiar with. Now, I have a
confession here, and it's that this
section of the course is going to be a
bit of a death by PowerPoint section.
And I'm really sorry in advance, but
trust me, every other section of this
course is going to be hands-on and
practical. It's just that it's really
hard to present some of this stuff in a
less theoretical way. But I promise you
that this is the only section that is
going to be very slideheavy like this.
And trust me that this is going to lay a
necessary foundation that we're going to
build upon to grasp some of the hands-on
topics. So within this section, we aim
to gain a holistic understanding of
security operations within organizations
that you might find yourself in. So when
we talk about the domain objectives for
this section, we want to understand the
core functions within a sock as well as
the role that it plays within
organizations. So we want to answer
questions like why do we have a sock and
what is the business justification for
maintaining a sock from a resource or
financial aspect. We also want to
explore the daily tasks and
responsibilities of a sock analyst. We
want to understand what the day-to-day
looks like in an average sock. We also
want to familiarize ourselves with
different sock models, roles and
organizational structures. You know so
how is the team actually structured and
how do various roles and
responsibilities disseminate amongst the
team. We also want to learn several
metrics that are used to evaluate the
effectiveness of our security
operations. Right? So what does success
look like for a sock team and how can
areas of improvement be identified. We
want to understand various tools that
are used within the sock for monitoring,
detection, analysis and response. And
lastly, we want to identify and
understand common cyber security threats
faced by organizations because of course
as our technology landscape grows, so
does our attack surface. And we need to
be able as sock analysts to quickly
identify common threats.
So the first question we should probably
ask is what is a sock? Well, a sock is
short for a security operations center
and you're going to see many different
definitions of socks out there. You
know, some sources might define a sock
as the heartbeat of an organization
security posture. And some sources might
describe it as the frontline defense
against cyber attacks. And all of these
are essentially true. And part of this
reason, and something that's continually
going to come up throughout the course,
is that socks can vary greatly between
organizations based on their size or
industry or budget or maturity level.
But regardless of the terminology used,
the core essence of a sock remains the
same. A security operation center is a
centralized unit within an organization
that deals with security issues,
incidents, and
events. And this definition casts a wide
net. And that's kind of purposeful
because socks serve many different areas
of the business which we're going to
cover shortly. But the primary objective
of a sock is to minimize the impact of
cyber attacks and protect sensitive data
and to ensure the confidentiality,
integrity and availability of the
organization's assets. And so of course
a sock is going to be staffed with a
team and that team is going to consist
of security analysts and engineers and
incident responders and basically a
number of people that collaborate
together in order to monitor, detect,
analyze and respond to cyber security
incidents in real time. So let's cover
all these different stages in more
detail. So the first step in any
security operations is monitoring and
that involves continually observing the
organization's networks and systems and
digital assets for any signs of
suspicious activity. And so we use
things like our monitoring tools and
technologies like our SIMs, our security
information and event management systems
or our IDS or intrusion detection
systems. And we use these tools to
provide real-time visibility into things
like our network traffic or log data.
For example, suppose a sock team has
deployed an endpoint detection and
response solution like Crowdstrike
Falcon to all of the company's servers
and workstations and we use it to track
things like file access or suspicious
processes or login attempts. And so once
potential security incidents are
identified through our monitoring, sock
analysts employ various detection
techniques to confirm the actual
presence of threats. So this might
involve things like correlating multiple
security events together and searching
through our SIM to analyze patterns of
behavior based on the logs or statistics
or even threat intelligence feeds to
identify known indicators of compromise
or IOC's.
So to continue our example, suppose an
alert is triggered within our EDR
software, signifying that an employee,
Bob Jones, is attempting to access
sensitive files outside of their normal
working hours and location. So in that
case, we're actually analyzing Bob
Jones's behavior on his system, and
we're noticing, hey, this is an anomaly.
You know, Bob Jones typically operates
between 9:00 to 5, and in this case,
it's 3:00 a.m. his time. Why is he
trying to access files at this time? And
so we're going to get an alert on that.
and we're going to detect the event. And
so here we move on to the analysis
section. This is where analysts conduct
in-depth investigations to understand
the nature and scope of the incident. So
this will involve things like examining
the affected system or analyzing malware
samples or tracing an attacker's
tactics, techniques, and procedures or
TTPs to determine the extent of the
compromise. So in the case of our EDR
alert, an analyst would need to
investigate the alert to get more
information. They might have to review
Bob Jones's access history, right? His
recent login, the IP addresses of these
login to see if there's anything
anomalous. We might need to look at
other data points that we have available
to us to determine if that access
attempt is
malicious. And next, we have response,
right? So based on our findings, sock
analysts need to formulate and execute a
response plan to contain the threat or
mitigate its impact and restore normal
operations. So this might involve things
like isolating the affected system or
deploying patches or updates or
coordinating with other internal teams
like stakeholders or even law
enforcement or regulatory bodies as
needed. So to wrap up our EDR alert
example, maybe after thorough
investigation, we as an analyst find
that Bob Jones's access attempt is in
fact malicious, in which case we need to
respond and mitigate the threat and
contain the threat and do things like
revoke Bob Jones's access. we would need
to reset his credentials and maybe look
through our sim to see if we can
correlate other events and try to figure
out the root cause. We might need to
inform relevant stakeholders and conduct
a deeper investigation. And lastly, you
can see here on the right how this all
sort of works together and feeds into
each other within this life cycle. So,
as we're able to improve our monitoring,
we can then detect more incidents. And
as we analyze these incidents, we're
able to have more effective response.
And through everything we've learned
through our response and all of the
indicators that we've collected, we can
then feed that back into our monitoring
to enhance our detection capabilities.
So you can see how this all sort of
feeds into each other and they all build
upon each other.
So when we say that a sock is
centralized, you might be picturing in
your head something like the image on
the screen here where we have a giant
bustling room filled with rows and desks
and a bunch of analysts sitting
shoulder-to-shoulder and hundreds of
monitors at the front all displaying
intricate graphs and charts. And you
know, an image like this has long been
the common depiction of a sock in many
people's minds. However, as the modern
sock has evolved, especially in the wake
of things like the rise of remote work
and the digital transformation of
businesses, well, this sentiment is no
longer as common. Instead, the concept
of a centralized sock has kind of
undergone a transformation. So, rather
than a physical room housing a large
team of analysts, today's sock is
increasingly virtualized and distributed
in many cases. And you know with the
advancement of cloud technologies and
things like virtual private networks and
collaboration platforms well now sock
teams are able to operate from almost
anywhere in the world without the need
for a centralized physical location.
However, the sock still logically refers
to that centralized team within the
organization. And we can also take a
step back in time and understand how the
concept of a sock has evolved over time.
And maybe in doing so we can better
understand how the priorities and the
functions within a soach have shifted to
meet the changing landscape of threats
and challenges. But at a high level
we've essentially seen changes from a
primary focus on just availability
monitoring to more reactive monitoring.
And from there we've moved on to
proactive monitoring and now to
proactive automation. And so the initial
concept of a sock well started well
before the 2000s and traces back to the
early days of network security primarily
with government and defense
organizations. In fact, we can go all
the way back to 1975 with the United
States National Security Operations
Center. And this picture is so cool
because it laid the groundwork for what
would eventually become the modern sock
because back then every security
solution and control and tool was
customuilt to detect very specific
threats. and most commonly back then
were dealing with availability issues
and malicious code running within a
network. But during the late '9s and
early 2000s, cyber threats kind of
evolved and organizations began to
recognize the importance of fortifying
their digital perimeter. And the
emphasis shifted from initial
availability monitoring towards
perimeter defense with companies
spending investments in technologies
like firewalls and antivirus software
and intrusion detection systems. But the
focus was still largely reactive and
sock teams were more so responding to
incidents as they occurred. But of
course, the landscape of cyber threats
continued to evolve. And around 2007, we
saw the rise of advanced persistent
threats or a kind of introduced a new
breed of attacks that haven't previously
been seen before that operated in this
low and slow type of environment and
evaded traditional security methods. And
these types of attacks meant that an
adversary could be in your network for
months or even years without any
detection. And they could quietly
excfiltrate data or start laying the
groundwork for more large or devastating
breaches. And so this prompted a
transition from reactive to proactive
monitoring within sock environments. And
this is sometimes referred to as the age
of the SIM or the security information
and event management systems, which
we'll get into much more detail later
on. This shift in mindset laid the
groundwork for what is today the modern
sock which adopted more of a proactive
stance towards cyber security. So rather
than just reacting to incidents, sock
teams began to actively monitor for
signs of potential threats and using
things like threat hunting techniques to
proactively hunt for evil. And you know
there are several other generations of
sock history that we didn't get into,
but I don't think it's that important.
You know, the main takeaway here is that
there was a shift between reactive
perimeter defense to proactive threat
detection and response. And so, what
actually makes up a sock? You know, it's
not just a magical entity or concept
that CISOs love to brag about and
vendors love to sell products to. There
are actual tangible things that make up
the team and its
capabilities. So, every sock is equipped
with personnel, with protocols, and
technical resources that all work
together to cover the functions that
we've talked about earlier.
And you know, we mentioned personnel and
protocols and technical resources, but
let's break that down a bit because they
are essentially the definitive pillars
that make up a sock. And another way
that we can think of this is through
people, processes, and
technology. So, of course, we have
people. These are the personnel within
the sock that form that human element or
that backbone of operations. And often
this human element is crucial in
ensuring how effective a sock can be.
This personnel includes people like
analysts and incident responders and
engineers and threat hunters who all
work together to actually analyze,
respond to and resolve security
incidents or do things like build out
detection capabilities or manage the
team. We also have processes. So teams
also need to build out descriptive
processes that streamline their
operations and ensure consistency,
efficiency, and agility to manage and
respond to incidents. So you might have
specific incident response playbooks or
detection and response processes that
the team can follow during the life
cycle of an incident or event. For
example, when an alert is triggered,
well, what predefined processes or
procedures are in place to dictate how
the sock responds? You know, what
escalation paths are there? What
investigation steps or mitigation
measures can be taken? Of course, that's
not an exhaustive list, but just
understand that processes drive the way
in which people within the sock conduct
their operations. Lastly, we have
technology. And technology provides the
tools and infrastructure necessary for
the people within the sock to do their
jobs and follow processes. And of
course, this is a non-exhaustive list
again, but concepts that fall into the
technology category can include things
like our SIM platform, our IDS or IPS
systems, our EDR solutions, our soar
systems, vulnerability management tools,
or even our threat intelligence
platforms. And of course, we're going to
cover these tools and more in much more
detail in the following lessons. and
we'll also get to directly configure and
interact with several of these tools to
gain that hands-on experience with them
in the following domains. Now, I also
want to quickly touch on the concept of
the CIA triad and how security
operations centers use this model as a
fundamental principle that basically
guide every single practice decision and
control that they make. And more
specifically, the sock supports the
business by upholding these principles
of the CIA triad. So, we have
confidentiality, we have integrity and
availability. We're going to cover each
of these in more detail in a future
lesson, but at a high level, the sock
aims to ensure the confidentiality,
integrity, and availability of all
assets within the organization. And we
can think about how all of these
concepts kind of intersect during an
incident, right? So, for example, in the
case of a critical server failing, maybe
we had a hardware disc failure in one of
the servers and we did not have
redundancy in place. Well, in this case,
we'd be facing an availability issue
because we are losing access to the data
stored on that server. So in this case
the sock would rely on the people you
know the experts that can leverage their
expertise of skilled analysts and other
IT personnel who understand the
intricacies of the system and these
people would then enact pre-established
recovery redundancy or failover
processes to mitigate the impact of the
availability issue and lastly they would
utilize technology solutions like
automated backup software or redundancy
failover solutions that can restore and
bring up the affected server. And lastly
here, let's take a look at some of the
key functions of a sock. Right? So, we
talked about what makes up the sock and
the value that they add to
organizations, but what specific
objectives do they actually serve on a
day-to-day basis? Now, this won't be an
exhaustive list, but it's going to
highlight some of the highle functions
that a typical sock will perform within
an
organization. And we can generally break
down the key functions of a sock into
two distinct categories. We have
reactive functions and proactive
functions. So on the reactive side,
these are functions that the sock
performs in response to cyber security
incidents as they occur. So we have
things like the primary role of the sock
monitoring and detection. So this is
where the sock team is going to monitor
network and system logs or endpoint
devices, security alerts and other
sources of data to identify potential
security incidents and threats in real
time. So we're going to use tools that
we have available to us like our SIM
platform, our IDS systems, our threat
intelligence feeds or even manual log
analysis. And next we have incident
response. So when a security incident is
detected, the sock is going to initiate
an incident response or an IR process to
investigate, contain, and mitigate the
threat. So this is going to involve
actually analyzing the incident and
gathering evidence and coordinating with
relevant stakeholders to minimize the
impact and restore normal business
operations. And depending on the size of
the sock, you might have forensic
analysis functions as well. You know,
this could be something that's conducted
inhouse or maybe coordinated with a
third party that specifically does
forensic examinations. But overall, this
is going to include conducting detailed
forensic analysis to determine the cause
and extent of any security breaches.
This is also going to include preserving
and collecting digital evidence for any
potential legal or regulatory purposes.
And depending on the size and severity
of the incident, the team may have to
collaborate with law enforcement
agencies or external forensic experts as
necessary. And lastly, here we have
malware analysis. And again, depending
on the size of your sock, this is
something that could be conducted
in-house or coordinated with a third
party. And this could involve running
malware samples in controlled
environments like sandboxes or VMs to
understand their actions and potential
impact on your systems or networks. It
could also involve things like reverse
engineering and deoffiscating malware to
study its behavior. But the goal here is
ultimately to collect indicators of
compromise and attempt to attribute the
malware to a specific threat actor or
group to enhance your threat detection
within the organization and inform more
proactive defense measures. And speaking
of which, we have proactive functions as
well. And these are the functions that
the sock performs to prevent cyber
security incidents before they occur or
to mitigate potential vulnerabilities.
So we have threat intelligence and this
is where the sock team actively gathers
and analyzes threat intelligence data
either from internal or external sources
so they can stay informed about emerging
threats or indicators of compromise
vulnerabilities as well as other attack
techniques. And of course the goal here
is to feed that intelligence into our
detection tools themselves so we can
then enhance our detection capabilities
and find incidents sooner. Which kind of
leads us into threat hunting. So this is
where the sock team is going to
proactively search for signs of
malicious activity or intrusions that
might have evaded traditional security
controls or detection mechanisms. So by
performing specific hunts and analyzing
logs and doing detailed searches, we
attempt to identify indicators of
compromise and potential threats that
might be lurking within our environment
that we haven't detected yet. And next
we have vulnerability management. And
some might argue that this could be
under reactive or maybe a blend between
reactive and proactive. And I wouldn't
disagree because while it does involve
reactively responding to vulnerabilities
that are identified, it does so in a
more proactive way to mitigate them and
remediate them before they're exploited.
But essentially, vulnerability
management is when the team works
closely with other departments like the
IT team or the development team to
identify and address vulnerabilities
within the organization's assets. So
this is going to involve performing
vulnerability scans and assessments and
identifying actual vulnerabilities and
implementing things like patch
management schedules and ensuring that
the organization can remediate
identified vulnerabilities in a timely
manner. And lastly here we have security
awareness training. So the sock
personnel themselves often play a role
in promoting cyber security awareness
within the organization. So they might
do things like educate employees on best
practices or write up security policies
and procedures and make sure that
employees read them or even provide
training to enhance the overall security
awareness and help prevent security
incidents in the future. They might even
go as far as to simulate fishing attacks
and gauge how effective the organization
is in responding to them or falling
victim to them. But ultimately the end
goal here is to mitigate human error
that often leads to incidents.
Let's dive into a bit of a refresher on
some of the important information
security concepts and terminology that's
going to come up time and time again
throughout this course. And the goal
here is not to just throw a bunch of
terms at you for memorization, but to
gently introduce some of the
foundational concepts of what it means
to work in a sock, but also some of
these concepts might actually get thrown
at you in interviews. So, it is best to
have a solid grasp on them. But if
you've been pretty familiar with
everything so far, or if you have a
background in security, well, you're
going to breeze right through this
section. And if not, don't worry because
we're going to hopefully fill in those
gaps for you here. So, let's start out
with something we've briefly mentioned
in the previous lesson, the CIA triad.
And this triad is a foundational concept
in cyber security that represents the
three core principles of
confidentiality, integrity, and
availability. And essentially any
security control or process or tool that
you implement within your organization
is aimed to protect one of these
principles. So let's cover them a bit.
Let's talk about confidentiality. And
this is going to ensure that information
is accessible only to those who are
authorized to access it. And we can
implement many security controls that
focus on protecting the confidentiality
of data. And most often you'll see it
associated with encryption. So, if
you're not familiar, that's going to be
converting the data into a form that can
only be read or processed after it's
been decrypted using an appropriate key.
Therefore, if someone who is not
authorized or does not possess that key
gains access to the encrypted data,
well, they won't be able to read it. And
honestly, we use encryption all over
throughout our environments and even
within the sock. For example, we're
going to need to encrypt data stored at
rest. Things like hard drives or backups
or like log archives from our SIM or
even data in processing in transit. For
example, right now you're watching this
video. You're accessing it through an
HTTPS protocol, which is the web
protocol that integrates TLS or
transport layer security that introduces
encryption within the connection. But
there are other controls related to
confidentiality as well. We can think
about access controls like access
control mechanisms like authentication
and authorization processes. Basically,
anything that can restrict access of
information based on a user's identity,
roles or any other attributes. We can
also tackle this from a process side,
right? So we have data classification
for example. So we can classify data
stored within the organization or within
its systems based on its sensitivity
level. For example, data might be
categorized as public for internal use
only or strictly confidential. You know
this classification helps us determine
the appropriate level of protection and
access controls that we need for each
type of data. Next we have integrity.
And integrity ensures that the data
remains accurate, complete and also
unaltered during its storage,
transmission or even its processing. So
this is where we protect data from
unauthorized modifications or deletions
or insertions whether it's accidental or
malicious. And this comes into play a
lot actually during digital forensics
where we need to document a proper chain
of custody of evidence and be able to
prove and present that the evidence that
we submit has not been tampered with.
And often we do that through hashing
algorithms and things like write
blockers to prevent modifications. We're
going to get deeper into that of course
during the digital forensics section.
But we can also implement things like
audit trails that keep detailed records
of data access and allow us to track
changes and allow us to identify any
unauthorized changes. And lastly, we
have availability. And this ensures that
information and resources are actually
accessible and usable when we need it.
And commonly you'll encounter controls
such as things that prevent disruptions
or denial of service attacks because of
course these compromise the availability
of systems. But realistically, so many
different things could be a disruption
to availability. We can think about a
server failing or an internal DNS or a
proxy going down which prevents
employees from accessing a certain
website that they need or maybe
accidentally implementing an
oversensitive endpoint rule that's going
to block access to an important business
application. Next, we have the AAA
framework which is also known as the
authentication authorization and
accounting framework. This is a model
that is used to securely control access
to resources and services and provides a
more structured approach for managing
user interactions on a system. And like
with many of the controls we talked
about, the ultimate goal of the AAA
framework here is to ensure that only
authenticated and authorized individuals
can access specific resources. So we
have authentication. And of course, this
is the process of verifying an identity
of a user or a system entity attempting
to access a resource. Basically, it
ensures that they are who they say they
are. And we have different
authentication methods, right? We have
things like passwords or keybased
authentication using public key
infrastructure or even things like
biometrics, right? fingerprints or
facial recognition. And we can provide
multiple sources of authentication at
once to create more security or also
known as multiffactor authentication.
Next, we have authorization. And this
determines what actions or permissions
or what resources a user is allowed to
access after they've authenticated
themselves. And typically, this relies
on defining an enforced access policy
based on specific user identities,
roles, or other attributes within the
company. So we're looking at things like
access control lists or rulebased access
control. And lastly here we have
accounting which is also known as
auditing or tracking and it essentially
it involves logging and monitoring user
activities within the system. So it
records details like who accessed what
service and when for how long and often
accounting is really crucial for meeting
compliance standards, but it's also just
as important for security event
monitoring as well. And we can use
things like native audit logs as well as
monitoring tools like our SIM to record
user activities and implement
accounting. So next, let's make some
important distinctions that often come
up when talking about security
operations. And sometimes the terms that
we're going to cover here are used
interchangeably, which is a common
misnomer because they're related, but
they have distinct meanings. So we have
a threat, a risk, and a vulnerability.
And let's talk about how they differ
from each other. So to put it simply, a
vulnerability refers to any weakness or
a flaw in a system, a network, an
application, any kind of asset that
could potentially be exploited by a
threat actor to compromise anything
within that CIA triad, right? So we can
think of things like software
vulnerabilities, right? Coding bugs or
coding errors or design flaws, uh maybe
configuration weaknesses like improperly
configured systems, default passwords or
unpatched software. But there's also
human factors as well, right? So human
errors or negligence or even just a lack
of awareness can lead to security
vulnerabilities like someone falling
victim to a social engineering attack. A
threat on the other hand refers to any
event or even an actor themselves with
the potential to exploit vulnerabilities
within any of the organization's assets.
So threats don't have to just be a
malicious individual maybe like wearing
a hoodie in a dark room and launching
attacks like malware or ransomware,
right? This this can come from things
from inside the company, things like
technology failures or natural disasters
or even the organization's own
employees, which we would call an
insider threat. And while a
vulnerability exposes the organization
to threats, the threat actually takes
advantage of a vulnerability, which
leads us into risk. And risk is the
potential for loss or harm or damage
resulting from the exploitation of
vulnerabilities by threats. It really
does, as you can see in the diagram,
represent the intersection of
vulnerabilities and threats and the
assets or resources that they target
because a risk is realized when a threat
exploits or harms a vulnerability. And
often times, organizations and security
teams will perform risk assessments that
evaluate the likelihood and impact of
potential security incidents. And we
consider things like the threat
likelihood, how probable is it for a
threat to exploit a specific
vulnerability as well as the impact
severity, right? So what is the
magnitude or the consequence from this
resulting action? As well as the asset
value. So what kind of data is at risk?
What kind of systems and infrastructure?
How critical is it? And we're going to
talk more about risk in a bit. But let's
move on to some more tangible concepts
that as a sock analyst you'll be dealing
with on a day-to-day basis. So let's
start simple. Let's talk about a log.
And we can think of logs as a
chronological record of events, actions,
or any transaction that occurs within a
system. At a high level, a log is going
to provide us as analysts and auditors
with detailed accounts of any activities
or changes or interactions as they
relate to a system or the
interconnection of systems. There are
countless log sources out there and many
that we're going to cover. So, this
isn't an exhaustive list by any means,
but we can start thinking about things
like system logs or application logs or
maybe network logs that you know
document network traffic or connections.
So, let's take a look at an example log
from a web servers log file. The
following log you're seeing here has
been extracted from an Apache web
servers access log file. So we can
actually break this down section by
section. Right? We have the IP address
here at the start. This is the public IP
address of the system that made the
request to the web server. We also have
a timestamp here. Right? We get the date
and the time of the
request. Next, this string is going to
be the request line. So we can actually
break this down further into the HTTP
method or the get request. We can see
the requested URL that /admin.php. PHP
as well as the protocol version, the
1.1. And next, we get the status code.
So in this case, it's a 200, meaning
that everything was okay. But if we were
to get something like a 404 not found,
or maybe like a 301 redirect, this would
give us more information in terms of how
the web server handled this request. And
lastly, here we have this weird string.
This is a user agent string and it can
actually tell us many things about the
request or the source of the request
including the browser that the
requesttor used as well as the operating
system used for the request. So we can
actually take this IP address that we
discovered and perform a lookup to
identify where the request came from
geographically and what service provider
the IP address belongs to. This of
course can be useful information during
an incident response investigation and
it can help us trace the origin of any
suspicious activity. And like with the
IP address, we can take that user agent
string and actually parse it using tools
to determine a lot of information that
we talked about. So we can extract some
valuable information about the user who
made this request such as the browser
they used, the name and its version, the
operating system they're running on, as
well as the device type. Is it a
desktop, mobile, tablet, and many other
additional details. So let's talk about
a security event. So a security event is
any occurrence that has the potential to
impact the security of an organization's
informationational assets or
infrastructure. And security events can
be defined as a wide range of
activities, right? So we can think of
things like failed login attempts or
high volumes of network traffic or a
user attempting to run an unauthorized
program on their workstation. These may
not always turn into an incident, but
they should still be investigated
nonetheless, right? All incidents are
events, but not all events become
incidents, which brings us to a security
incident. So an incident is a confirmed
or suspected breach of any kind of
violation of our security policies or
procedures or controls that we have in
place. And ultimately this poses a
threat to our confidentiality, integrity
or availability of our organization's
assets. So again, all security incidents
are events because they involve some
sort of observable occurrence. However,
not all security events escalate to
security incidents. And next we have an
alert. And an alert is a notification or
a warning generated by a security
monitoring system or our tools that
indicate a detection of a potential
security incident. And alerts are
typically triggered based on predefined
rules or thresholds or even patterns
that we set up to indicate potential
malicious activity. Security alerts will
often include important metadata, things
like the event details or the alert
context. Alerts are also typically
categorized based on their nature and
severity, right? Are they a high or
critical alert and require immediate
attention or are they more low priority
and still require attention but do not
pose an immediate threat to the
organization? For example, let's take a
look at a snort alert that was logged to
our SIM. Snort, which we'll cover later
on in the course, is a powerful open-
source network intrusion detection
system. And when we look at the alert
here, we can see like with our log
example from earlier, some information
that we can extract, right? So, we have
the date or the timestamp. This is the
date that the alert was triggered. We
have the priority in this case one which
may indicate a high alert severity. We
have the protocol which is UDP. The
class or the classification gives us
some more context and detail into what
the alert entails. And we have the
source IP address from which the
suspicious network traffic originated
from as well as the port and the
destination port and IP as well. We also
get some more information with the SID
or the signature ID which is a unique
identifier for this rule that we can
then look up to get more information.
We then have the description here which
provides a of course description of the
alert indicating in this case that store
detected an inbound connection related
to the zero access Trojan. So next let's
talk about security controls themselves
and what types of controls we can decide
to implement within our
organization. When we start to implement
security controls that complement and
support each other, we aim to achieve
the concept of defense in depth. And
this is a strategy that involves
deploying multiple layers of security
controls and access controls within our
organization to protect against a wide
range of security threats and
vulnerabilities. And this is a strategy
that involves deploying multiple layers
of security to protect against a wide
range of threats. So rather than relying
on a single point of failure or a single
security measure, defense and depth will
emphasize redundancy and diversity and
depth within our security defenses to
create a more overlapping protection
layer. And we can think of the Swiss
cheese analogy in which we stack
multiple layers of Swiss cheese slices
on top of each other. And if you think
about a Swiss cheese slice, it's going
to have individual holes or weaknesses
that threats can exploit. But when we
start to stack layers on top of each
other, over time we end up patching all
of these holes holistically. And when it
comes to controls themselves, typically
you'll see them separated into three
distinct categories. However, we're
going to see shortly that this can get
confusing and kind of arbitrary. So
first let's talk about administrative
controls and these relate to the
policies and procedures and guidelines
that we implement within an organization
to manage and mitigate security risks.
So for example, we might have incident
response plans or security policies. We
might provide things like security
awareness training. We might implement
access control policies and we also have
technical controls and these are also
referred to as logical controls as well.
And as the name suggests, these controls
rely on technology to enforce security
policies and also do things like detect
and prevent unauthorized access. So we
can think of things like firewalls, our
endpoint detection and response
platforms, intrusion detection systems,
or even things like introducing
encryption, access controls, antivirus
software, the list goes on and on. And
lastly, here we have physical controls.
These are tangible measures that we can
implement to protect physical assets or
our facility and resources from
unauthorized access or even theft or
damage. These controls encompass
security measures designed to secure the
physical environment in which the IT and
security systems and infrastructure
operates. So we can think of things like
surveillance cameras and biometrics or
perimeter fencing access control
systems, right? Or even hiring security
guards. These are all examples of
physical controls. Now we can also talk
about security control functions and
these relate to an actual controls well
function or goal or objective. And so to
start we have preventive controls and
these are security measures deployed to
proactively prevent security threats and
incidents from occurring. So for example
we can implement things like firewalls
or access control lists or EDR tools or
intrusion prevention systems. And we
also have detective controls. So these
are measures implemented to identify and
detect attempted security incidents. And
these focus of course on monitoring and
analyzing. So obviously in this case we
have our IDS systems or our SIM
different log monitoring and analysis
tools and things like audit trails as
well. And next we have corrective
controls and these are security measures
implemented to remediate and mitigate
the impact of security incidents after
they've been detected. So these controls
focus on restoring systems or data or
operations to a secure state and prevent
similar incidents from occurring in the
future. So we can think of things like
having secure backups or incident
response plans or having a patch
management system in place which brings
us to deterrent controls and these are
used to well deter threats from
exploiting vulnerabilities. So we can
think of things like placing warning
signs or physical barriers or tamper
seals to prevent tampering. And lastly,
we have compensating controls. And these
are alternative security measures that
we can implement to mitigate risks when
a primary security control is either
impractical or ineffective or just plain
unavailable. And these controls serve as
substitutes or even enhancements to
primary controls that achieve the same
or similar level of security. And often
when we're evaluating compensating
controls, we need to have a process to
accept and document carefully for
auditing and compliance purposes. So we
can think about using network
segmentation as a means to secure
sensitive and legacy endpoints from the
rest of the network. Right? If we have a
very old system that we cannot patch, we
physically cannot patch it. Well, we
need to have compensating controls in
place. Maybe we airgap the system
because it can't feasibly be updated.
You might have noticed that certain
controls can fit into multiple
categories. For example, we have
surveillance cameras, right? Is it a
physical control? Well, I mean, yes, it
relates to physical equipment, but when
we think about functionality,
surveillance cameras can fit as a
detective control, right? because we're
able to use them to monitor and detect
for attempted security violations. But
they can also be classified as a
deterrent control as the mere presence
of having them can discourage physical
intrusion attempts. So it's entirely
possible that a single security control
can fulfill multiple functions. So let's
quickly talk about risk again. So SOCK
teams employ a range of strategies to
manage risks effectively and these
strategies encompass various approaches.
So we have things like transference or
risk acceptance or avoidance and
mitigation. Each strategy that we're
going to talk about offers distinct
advantages and is applied based on the
organization's risk appetite or resource
availability as well as business
objectives. So first we have risk
transference and this involves actually
shifting a financial burden or
responsibility of managing a risk to
another party typically through some
sort of contractual agreement or policy.
So instead of directly dealing with the
risk, an organization can just transfer
it to a third party that is better
equipped to handle or absorb it. So a
common example that you'll see is
purchasing cyber security insurance. By
paying a premium, we can transfer some
of the financial risk of the potential
security breach over to an insurance
company. We can also think of things
like moving services to the cloud,
right? When we move things to the cloud,
cloud service providers actually
abstract a lot of the physical and some
logical controls away from us. So by
paying a premium to shift things to the
cloud, we gain a lot in security as well
as many other things that cloud
providers offer. We also have risk
acceptance and in this case it involves
acknowledging and continuously deciding
to tolerate or live with a certain level
of risk without actually taking any
actions to mitigate or transfer it. So
this strategy is appropriate when the
cost or the effort required to reduce a
risk kind of outweighs the potential
impact of the risk itself. So for
example, in some cases, organizations
might choose to accept certain
operational risks. They might accept a
minor service disruption during routine
maintenance rather than implementing
some costly redundancy measure to
eliminate downtime altogether. Right?
That's not the best example, but it's
often this balance of resources and time
and cost as well as the impact. We also
have risk avoidance. So this involves
taking deliberate actions to eliminate
or avoid specific risks altogether. So
with this strategy, we aim to completely
remove the possibility of encountering a
specific risk, thereby preventing any
potential negative consequences. For
example, an organization might decide
that the risk of data breaches
associated with storing sensitive
customer data is too high. You know,
maybe for a simple e-commerce site, an
organization doesn't need to be storing
financial data for longer than necessary
just to complete a transaction. So they
put controls in place to only keep that
data ephemerally. And lastly, here we
have risk mitigation. And this involves
implementing proactive measures to
reduce the likelihood or impact of any
identified risk. So for example, we can
implement things like a strong patch
management system or plan to mitigate
the threat or the risk of thread actors
exploiting vulnerabilities or maybe a
strong redundancy plan to mitigate data
loss and system failure which would of
course impact availability. Okay, we're
almost done. Let's quickly talk about
security policies along with a
non-exhaustive list of some common
policies that you might see. So security
policies are documents that outline an
organization's guidance, principles, and
procedures for protecting its assets. So
these policies typically serve as some
sort of framework that establish and
enforce security standards or define
acceptable behavior as well as ensure
compliance with legal and regulatory
requirements. So we use security
policies to provide that clear direction
to employees and contractors and
stakeholders within the company on what
their responsibilities are for
safeguarding the company's assets. So
for example, we have acceptable use
policies and these define acceptable
behaviors and practices regarding the
use of an organization's IT systems. So
basically what is and what isn't allowed
within the organization. And
additionally, sometimes you might see
this through a separate policy called
bring your own device policies. But
there are policies that can address the
use of personal devices as well and
establish rules and security measures
for accessing the company resources from
personal devices. Next, we have the
password policy, which you're likely
familiar with as these establish the
requirements and best practices for
creating, managing, and securing your
passwords within the organization. So,
it includes things like guidelines for
the complexity and length and expiration
or even reuse of passwords. Next, we
have data classification policies and
these categorize information assets
based on their sensitivity, their
criticality or confidentiality
requirements. So it will define
classification levels like public or
internal or confidential restricted and
specify specific security controls and
protections that are required for each
of these classification levels. We also
have change management policies. So
these outline the procedures and
protocols for implementing, reviewing
and approving any changes to IT systems
or applications. It defines the roles
and responsibilities and establishes a
change control process to mandate
documentation as well as testing
requirements to minimize any disruptions
or errors or any vulnerabilities that
might be introduced because of these
changes. So for example, in an ideal
world, we should have a process to
document a record of every asset's
initial state along with every record of
change like an upgrade or an
installation or replacement because of
course change can bring in new risks to
the organization and the grand purpose
of any change management process is to
minimize that risk. And lastly here we
have a disaster recovery policy and
these establish the strategies and
overall objectives and procedures for
recovering any IT system or data or
operations and infrastructure in the
event of a disruptive incident or
disaster. And so it's going to outline
the roles and responsibilities of key
personnel. It's going to identify
critical systems and resources and
define things like recovery time
objectives and recovery point objectives
to adhere to. And through all this, a
disaster recovery policy is going to
help the organization ensure business
continuity, minimize downtime, and also
mitigate the impact of unforeseen events
on organizational
operations. So, we've covered a lot so
far, but the one thing we haven't talked
in detail about yet is the actual
organizational structure of a sock. You
know, what different types of roles
exist? What does the hierarchy look
like? And although security analysts
themselves are the backbone of the sock,
there are a lot more potential avenues
and roles that we can explore that all
work together to provide that strong
security operations coverage. So first,
you'll typically see three different
models or arrangements of a sock. There
might be many more that you come across,
but in general, we can break it down to
the following. First, we have an
internal sock. And this is going to be a
sock that is owned and fully operated by
the organization that it serves. So,
it's going to be staffed with the own
company's security analysts or engineers
or incident responders, and the sock is
going to be fully integrated within the
organization's existing IT
infrastructure, and it's going to
operate as that typical central hub that
we come to think of. Internal socks are
great because it offers the most
visibility that you're ever going to get
and the most control over security
operations within your company, but it
does obviously come with a large upfront
cost to invest in those resources and
skilled personnel and technology
infrastructure and building up the
actual sock along with ongoing training
as well. So, as an opposite or
alternative, we have the managed sock or
the MOC. Sometimes it's also known as
security operations center as a service
or sock as but typically this is going
to be a sock type entity that's
outsourced to a third party that
specializes in cyber security services.
So if you end up working in a managed
sock, chances are that you're going to
be overseeing a large number of clients
and a large number of different systems.
And managed socks typically deliver that
range of 24/7 monitoring and threat
detection and incident response and
overseeing the SIM sometimes for a large
number of clients like we mentioned. And
sometimes different organizations will
prefer to have a different amount of
managed sock involvement, right? So
maybe a certain customer will have some
in-house capabilities and would just
prefer to offload the burden of the
initial alert triage to the managed
sock. Other times, your team will be
expected to provide assistance and lead
response activities for a customer that
doesn't have that type of thing in
house. But unlike an internal sock, one
of the challenges that organizations and
sock analysts themselves will face
working in a managed sock is that it's
going to be hard to maintain visibility
and control over the network because
after all it's managed by the client.
And this leads us to the hybrid sock or
the third model here which is going to
combine the elements of both internal
and managed socks to sort of leverage a
mix of in-house resources as well as
bringing in external expertise as
needed. So this will allow companies to
retain that control over their core
security functions while also allowing
for more extended or specialized
capabilities like incident response,
forensic analysis, malware analysis, and
leveraging third parties for that. Now
for the more exciting part, we get to
talk about the actual roles and titles
that make up a sock. And listen, before
we dive in, we need to acknowledge that
there's kind of a caveat here. Job
titles and roles specifically in our
industry are often dynamic and might not
always align seamlessly to match what
your specific requirements are. And also
these roles can vary very significantly
between organizations based on again
their structure, their size, their
maturity and budget. And I'll also
mention that we're going to be talking
about a tiered model of sock analysts
here. And it's important to recognize
that a lot of organizations kind of
ditch that traditional tiered model and
opt for a more collaborative approach.
And there's definitely an argument to be
made there that a non-tiered setup can
kind of promote a more crossunctional
team. But I'm not going to get into the
debate here. So to keep everything broad
and sort of to the book, we're going to
essentially cover everything we can. So
let's first start with of course sock
analysts and these are the frontline
defenders in a sock. They're responsible
for monitoring and detecting and
analyzing and responding to security
incidents and threats. So, first we have
a typical tier one sock analyst. And
these are typically entry-level
positions that are tasked with the
initial triage and investigation of
alerts and incidents. So, they're the
ones that are doing that routine
monitoring of the systems and analyzing
log events and alerts and escalating
confirmed incidents to higher tiers as
needed. Essentially, their goal is to
categorize and prioritize alerts and
escalate incidents to the tier 2
analysts as needed. Which leads us to
the tier 2 analysts. And in many
organizations, you might see the role of
a tier 2 analyst be described as an
incident responder, especially in a sock
team that does not have a dedicated
incident response team. So these are
going to be more senior analysts, and
they're going to be the ones tasked with
investigating and remediating escalated
incidents. And lastly, here in our
tiered model, we have the tier three,
which is typically the highest tier that
you're going to see. And I will speak
generally here and say that a tier three
analyst is often referred to as a more
proactive role in organizations. and
they're sometimes actually treated as
threat hunters. So these are going to be
the most senior level analysts and
they're able to assist the tier 2s with
any complex incidents or anything that
gets escalated to them. But they will
have a primary focus on proactively
searching for suspicious behavior or
ingesting threat intelligence and
performing threat hunting activities and
assessments to detect advanced threats
and areas of improvement to better their
detection engineering efforts. And I've
seen different cases of how this is
structured. So you might have a setup
where a tier three analyst is doing
typical instant response and triage
during the majority of the week and
maybe they have specific days or
specific parts of the week where they
specifically focus on threat hunting.
Again, this is all dependent on the
organization and the management of the
sock. And lastly here we have a sock
team lead. And this isn't always the
case. If your team is large enough, you
might have a dedicated sock team lead
who is the one who's responsible for
overseeing the day-to-day operations of
all the analysts and managing things
like workload and providing guidance and
mentorship. But sometimes the
responsibility of this lead is served by
a tier 2 or three analyst. So in
addition to the sock analyst, we
sometimes have specialized roles that
address specific cyber security
challenges and enhance the overall socks
capabilities. If your organization is
large enough and they invest enough in
the sock, you might see one or several
of these roles that you might want to
actually work towards as you progress
your career. So the first one being an
incident responder. So this would be
where you have a dedicated team that is
responsible for responding to and
containing security incidents. So
they're going to be the ones that are
actually leading the incident response
efforts and assessing the severity and
the scope and executing incident
response plans and dealing with you know
the collaboration between stakeholders
and management and IT and legal and all
the other departments that are involved
in an incident. So next we have threat
hunters. And these again are going to be
that proactive role that searches for
signs of advanced threats and tries to
find hidden security risks within the
organization that isn't being detected.
So they might be the ones that are
developing custom alert and detection
rules. They might be ingesting threat
intelligence and using that to conduct
threat hunts where they try to find
known indicators of compromise within
their environment. And this kind of
leads us to threat intelligence
analysts, which are the ones who are
going to be gathering and analyzing and
disseminating the actionable
intelligence on emerging cyber threats
or adversary tactics, techniques, and
procedures or TTPs related to their
organization's threat model. And they'll
do this by collecting and analyzing
threat data from various sources. So the
organization might subscribe to
proprietary feeds and actually pay for
that threat intelligence related to
their organization. or they might use
things like open source intelligence or
OSENT or things like collaborations with
information sharing communities. So
typically they're going to be the ones
producing intelligence reports. They're
going to be reporting on indicators of
compromise and developing actionable
insights that can help things like the
threat hunters or the tier 3 analysts
and support things like making the
organization more efficient with
detecting
threats. Next, we have a very important
role, the security engineer, sometimes
referred to as a security architect. And
these are going to be the people who
design, implement, and maintain the
different security controls,
technologies, and the overall
architecture that the sock is built
upon. So, they're going to be the ones
getting that hands-on deployment and
design and configuration to actively
tune security infrastructure like
firewalls or IDs and IPS systems. They
might also be the ones conducting
security assessments or audits and maybe
reviews to identify weaknesses and
recommend remediation measures to
enhance the security posture amongst the
organization. Which kind of leads us
into vulnerability management. And if
you're in this type of role, you're
typically going to be the one who's
overseeing the identification, the
assessment, prioritization, and also the
remediation of security vulnerabilities
within the organization's environment.
So, they might be the ones conducting
vulnerability assessments or scans or
coordinating penetration tests to
identify weaknesses in systems or
applications or any kind of
infrastructure within the org. They're
going to be the ones going through the
reports and prioritizing vulnerabilities
based on their risk factors, how
exploitable they are, the potential
impact and you know relevance to the
company. And with this analysis, they'll
be collaborating with the IT teams and
development teams to sort of implement
patching strategies and remediation
plans. Next year, we have forensic
analysts. And these folks specialize in
digital forensics and incident response
or what we refer to as defer. So they're
going to be the ones collecting and
preserving and analyzing digital
evidence to come up with timelines and
reconstruct events and trace an
attacker's activities to support legal
and sometimes regulatory investigations.
So sometimes this type of function is
left to third party companies that come
in during or after an incident or
sometimes companies engage forensic
analysts on retainers for this purpose.
So again, these are the ones that are
going to be doing the data acquisition
to acquire evidence or performing memory
dumps or documenting their findings,
preparing forensic reports, and
maintaining chain of custody. They might
need to testify as the expert witness in
legal proceedings depending on how
severe the incident is. And lastly, here
we have a malware analyst. And again,
this is one of those specialized roles,
which you may or may not see in your
day-to-day, but they're going to be the
ones that are specialized in analyzing
and reverse engineering malware to
understand its functionality, behavior,
and impact on the systems. Personally,
I've never seen a dedicated malware
analyst at any of the sock roles I've
been in. You're primarily going to be
looking at like larger companies or
companies that do a lot of research and
development. We can think of things like
EDR or anti virus companies where having
this function would actively benefit the
end product of the business. So lastly,
let's talk about management type roles.
And obviously management roles are going
to provide that strategic leadership and
direction and overall oversight for all
of the sock
operations. So first we have the sock
manager. And the sock manager is going
to be the one who oversees the
day-to-day operations within the
security operations center. So they're
going to be the ones managing the
personnel, the resources, the budget,
different activities and priorities
within the sock to ensure that the
monitoring, detection, and response
efforts are going as well as they
possibly can. And sometimes you might
have another role like a director of
security. Not all the time, but this is
typically going to be a senior
leadership role that's responsible for
defining and executing the
organization's overall cyber security
initiatives.
So they're going to be the ones
providing strategic direction and
governance and general oversight for all
aspects of security within the company
and this includes sock operations. So
they might be the ones implementing the
standards and policies and controls that
protect the organization and support the
business objectives. They might be the
ones collaborating with executive
leadership or board members or external
stakeholders to assess risk and
prioritize investments. Which leads us
into the sea level here with the CISO or
the chief information security officer.
And this is going to be the highest
ranking executive that's responsible for
the organization's overall security
program and all of these security
initiatives. So many of the things we
just mentioned for the director often
apply to the CISO. So again, they're
going to be on that senior management
level and on the board to advocate for
investments within the cyber security
capabilities within the
organization. As we dive deeper into
this course, we're going to be getting
hands-on with incident and event
management operations. Because of this,
we should understand what goes into
incident and event management and make
some key distinctions that an analyst
must make every day when dealing with
handling alerts. So, when we think about
event management, we're thinking about
the process of monitoring, analyzing,
and prioritizing security events
generated by our various systems. The
goal of event management is to
continually collect an accurate record
of all the happenings going on across
our environment, which gives us a strong
visibility into our infrastructure. So
as an analyst, we can turn this
visibility into actionable insights and
allow the sock to identify potential
security incidents or anomalies or
threats in real time so we can then take
the appropriate actions to mitigate
those risks. So a crucial first step in
being able to manage events is to
collect events obviously and we do that
by first taking an asset inventory of
all the systems and devices within our
network to identify where the gaps are
and determine what we need to collect.
So, these sources of these events
include things like firewalls and
intrusion detection systems or antivirus
software, log files, network devices,
user endpoints and hosts, and you know,
the list goes on. These events might
include system alerts or network traffic
logs or authentication logs and
application logs. We're going to get
more into this in the SIM section, but
typically we'll deploy something like an
agent or a forwarder to these devices
that can then collect and transmit logs.
In the cases where we're dealing with
like networking equipment or a router or
something where we can't actually deploy
an agent, we're going to use some other
protocol specific means like SIS log or
something to then collect that
information. So the collected events are
then normalized to a common format or a
schema that can facilitate consistent
analysis as well as correlation across
different data sources and technologies.
So when we think about normalization,
that's going to involve like
standardizing the event attributes or
the timestamps or even the data formats
themselves to ensure that they are
consistent across the board. So for
example, imagine if we have two
different log sources, maybe like a
firewall as well as a reverse proxy
server that we're collecting logs from.
And these two different devices have
different naming conventions when they
log a source IP address. For example,
maybe the firewall logs it as IP source
and maybe the proxy server says source
IP address. These are not accurate
examples, but just so you can start
thinking about it. So normalization is
going to be the process of parsing the
schema of these logs and ensuring
consistency when the logs are
aggregated. So when an analyst is
searching for a source IP address,
they're effectively querying a single
data point rather than multiple. And so
when events meet a predefined rule
criteria or different thresholds,
they're converted into actionable alerts
and are then forwarded to the sock for
further investigation and response. As
we talked about previously, alerts are
categorized in different ways. based on
their severity, their urgency, and
relevance to the organization itself.
And this magical SIM solution that we've
been talking about is the centralized
platform that aggregates, normalizes,
correlates, and analyzes these events.
And there are a number of different SIM
platforms and vendors out there that
provide SIM capability. And you can see
some of the ones listed below. On the
right hand side we have a screenshot of
the Splunk cloud instance but we also
have different options like log RHM or
IBM's Q radar elastic security grey log
or solar winds. So when we talk about
incident management on the other hand
well this is the process of detecting
and responding to and resolving security
incidents in a timely and effective
manner so that we can minimize their
impact. Like with event management,
we're going to get deeper into this
later on but at a high level the
incident management life cycle attempts
to follow some sort of a defined
process. So we have incident
identification. This is when security
incidents are identified through our
event management process or through our
different detection mechanisms or alerts
or user reports or external
notifications. So there are many
different ways and there are many
different types of incidents too, right?
We might have unauthorized access or
malware infections or data breaches or
denial of service attacks. You know the
list goes on. We then have incident
classification and this is where
incidents are classified based on their
severity, impact and the nature of the
threat. And some common classification
categories that you might see are like
critical, high, medium, or even low
severity alerts. And these are going to
help prioritize the incident response
efforts and allocate resources
accordingly. Next, we have incident
investigation. So this is where the
actual sock analysts are going to
conduct their thorough investigations
and gather evidence and analyze the root
cause and determine the scope and extent
of the incident. So they might be
looking at logs and doing some
correlation and searches or they might
be actually gathering forensic evidence
on an infected workstation. Next we have
the incident containment. So once the
nature and the scope of the incident are
understood, this is when the sock
analyst is going to implement the
containment measures to prevent further
escalation or minimize the spread of
damage. So this might involve isolating
the affected systems or blocking the
network traffic or disabling compromised
user accounts. Next here we have
incident eradication which is kind of
similar here. This is where after the
containment measures are in place, the
sock analyst is going to work on
eradicating the root cause of the
incident and restore the affected system
to a secure known good state. So this
might involve actually removing the
malware or patching vulnerabilities or
most likely just restoring data from
backups. And lastly here we have
incident recovery. So once the incident
is resolved, the sock analyst is going
to focus on restoring normal business
operations and miticate any residual
impact. This might include things like
post incident reviews and meeting with
stakeholders to determine what was the
root cause or updating security policies
and procedures or providing user
awareness training to prevent similar
incidents in the future. So let's talk
about detection outcomes. So there's
some terminology that's commonly used in
the context of security event analysis
as well as incident response to describe
the accuracy and reliability of our
detection and alerting mechanisms. And
as a sock analyst, you're going to be
constantly classifying alerts you
receive as true or false positives. And
the sock itself is going to be actively
tuning its detection capabilities to
mitigate any potential for false
negatives or missed incidents. So the
first one we have here is the false
positive. And this is going to be when a
security tool or system incorrectly
identifies a normal or benign activity
as a security threat or an incident. So,
for example, we could think of an
antivirus program mistakenly flagging a
legitimate word processing software as
malware leading to a false positive
alert. Or maybe a rule is tuned too
sensitively and when a user mistypes
their password a couple times, the
system alerts on a brute force attempt.
Next, we have a true positive. So, a
true positive occurs when a security
tool or system correctly identifies a
genuine security threat or an incident.
So for example, we could think of a
network intrusion detection system or an
IDS accurately detects an alert sock
analyst on a malicious attempt to
exploit a vulnerability on a web server
for example. Next we have a false
negative and this occurs when a security
tool or a system fails to detect a
genuine security threat or incident. And
these are very scary. So for example,
imagine there's a threat actor that
evaded a web application firewall and
gain access to a web server through
remote code execution and then maybe the
attacker is able to exfiltrate data or
privilege escalate or move laterally
without being detected by any network or
system rules. Obviously this is very
scary. And lastly here we have a true
negative. So this occurs when a security
tool or a system correctly determines
that no security threat or incident is
present and as a result no alert is
generated. So, for example, we could
think of a firewall correctly
identifying and allowing legitimate
traffic to pass through it without
triggering any false alarms or false
positives. Now that we have a better
idea of what aspects make up a sock,
let's quickly look at some of the
metrics and benchmarks that are
typically used to evaluate the
effectiveness and performance of the
people, processes, and technology within
the sock. This is an important point to
cover because as an analyst, you will be
the first line of defense and one of the
most crucial contributors that actively
impacts these metrics on the day-to-day
basis. And the reason why metrics are so
important to businesses, particularly
sock managers and CISOs, is their role
in providing quantifiable insights into
the socks operational efficiency,
effectiveness, and also alignment with
the organization's goals. So by
collecting these metrics, it enables
these stakeholders to assess the sock's
performance, identify any areas of
improvement, and make datadriven
decisions that optimize the security
posture of the organization. And while
there are a number of different metrics
and strategies for measuring
performance, you're likely going to
encounter some of the following in your
roles as they're quite common in the
field. I will say though, there are some
arguments to be made in terms of
weighing and prioritizing certain
metrics over others based on
organizational priorities and risk
appetite. This is not an exhaustive list
but rather a starting point for
evaluating sock effectiveness and
performance. So the first one we have
here is the meanantime to detect and
this is the average time it takes for
the sock to detect an incident from the
moment it occurs. And so a lower
meanantime to detect indicates a faster
detection and response capability.
Similarly we have the meanantime to
resolution. So this is the average time
it takes for the sock to resolve an
incident from the moment it's detected.
So of course a lower meanantime to
resolution indicates a more efficient
incident response process and more
timely mitigation of incidents. And you
know consider a scenario where the sock
identifies an incident where an employee
fell victim to a fishing campaign. And
so after triage and investigation and
containment activities as well as
recovery objectives, the incident is
fully declared resolved within 4 hours.
In this case, the MTR or the meanantime
to resolution would be 4 hours. And next
we have the meanantime to attend and
analyze. That one's kind of a mouthful.
Um this is the average time it takes for
the sock or the analyst to pick up and
work on an alert from the moment it's
triggered. And so a lower MTA indicates
a prompter response and reduce latency
in incident handling. So as another
example, suppose like a data loss
prevention alert came up indicating that
there's a potential data exfiltration
going on within the organization. So
let's say an analyst logs in and picks
up the alert within 5 minutes and then
conducts their initial analysis and
begins fully investigating the incident
within 15 minutes. In this case, the
MTNA for this alert would be 15 minutes.
So next we have the incident detection
rate and this is the rate at which the
sock detects security incidents within a
specific time period. So a higher
detection rate indicates better
visibility and effectiveness of
monitoring the detection capabilities
which enables the organization to
proactively identify threats and
initiate responses. So let's say in a
given month the sock detects 90 security
incidents out of a total of 100.
Therefore the incident detection rate
for that month would be 90%. And you
might be thinking that of course
sometimes this can be a hard metric to
track accurately and if you have
eventually identified an incident that
wasn't initially detected or we had a
false negative scenario that's usually a
bad day for the sock as the incident has
had much more time to propagate. And
next we have false positive rates or
FPRs and this is the percentage of
alerts or incidents that are incorrectly
identified as true positives. And so a
lower false positive rate indicates more
accurate alerting which would result in
reduced analyst workload and minimize
things like alert fatigue or wasted
resources and time spent on false
alarms. So let's say the sock receives
200 alerts in one week out of which
maybe 20 alerts are later deemed to be
false positives upon investigation.
Therefore the false positive rate for
the week would be 10%. Next we have
false negative rates or FNRs. And this
is the percentage of true incidents that
initially go undetected or missed by the
sock. In which case, a lower false
negative rate indicates fewer missed
detections and fewer gaps in our
detection capabilities. And again, you
can imagine this is a hard rate to
detect unless in
retrospect. So in addition to these
specific sock metrics, there are also
more general terminology and frameworks
that relate to performance measurement
and management within the sock. So we
have KPIs or key performance indicators
and these are more quantifiable metrics
used to evaluate the effectiveness and
performance of specific processes,
activities or functions within the sock.
So you know all the metrics that we
described on the lefth hand side here
can all relate and be applied to various
KPIs within the sock. We also have key
risk indicators or KIS and again these
are quantifiable metrics that we can use
to assess and monitor the potential
risks and threats to our organization's
security posture. And so a key risk
indicator is typically a measurement
that management would use to indicate
how risky an activity is. And
organizations use these metrics
proactively to provide an early signal
in increasing risk exposures in various
areas of the enterprise. So there's
typically going to be some sort of
threshold or trigger based on the
likelihood and impact of the risk that
categorize and define risk factors so
they can be documented and risk analysis
can be performed more efficiently. And
lastly here we have service level
agreements. And we've touched on this a
bit before. These are agreements between
the sock and its stakeholders. So if
we're thinking in the example of an
internal sock, this would be between the
sock and the socks management or the uh
organization as a whole. Or if we're
thinking of more of a managed service
provider, this would be an agreement
between the sock and the customers of
the sock. And these agreements define
the level of service performance
expectations and response times most
critically for security operations and
incident response activities. And so
they help ensure accountability,
transparency, and alignment with
business objectives. So for example, an
SLA may indicate that the sock must
acknowledge and begin investigating a
critical security alert within 15
minutes of its generation. And so you
can sort of see how metrics like the
meantime to resolution are typically
mapped closely with SLAs's to identify
gaps in areas for
improvement. When thinking about the
main pillars that make up a sock, we've
identified people, processes, and
technology. In this lesson, let's focus
specifically on technology and discuss
the types of tools that socks use to
actually conduct operations at a
hands-on level. And while we're going to
cover multiple specific tools throughout
the course, the highle emphasis that I'm
always going to put within this course
is that we want to understand the
methodologies and processes. Right? So,
it's crucial to recognize that tools are
just tools. You know, they evolve, they
come and go, and while they have
similarities between each other, they
also have differences. So our goal isn't
to become experts in any single tool
immediately, but rather to grasp what
they do, why they're used, and other
methodologies around using them
effectively within security operations.
And you can see that there are quite a
number of different types of tools that
socks use. You may or may not use some
of these in the field or all of these.
It's entirely dependent on your role and
the size of the company and the actual
capabilities of your sock. But for the
sake of being thorough, let's quickly go
through each of these at a high level.
So first we have the security
information and event management system
or the SIMS. And a security information
and event management system is one of
the most important components in modern
cyber security infrastructure. So much
so that it's often referred to as the
heartbeat or the nerve of the sock. SIMs
serve as a centralized platform for
collecting, correlating, analyzing, and
managing security event data in real
time. So at its core, a SIM system
aggregates logs generated throughout all
of our technology within the
organization. And then we can employ
advanced analytics and correlation
techniques to identify patterns or
trends or anomalies within the collected
data. And by correlating events from
various sources using a SIM, we can
differentiate normal activity from
potentially malicious behavior, which
can help us on the security side detect
and respond to incidents as they occur.
And with a SIM, we can integrate
functions like log management, right? So
collecting and storing and normalizing
log data from all these different
sources, but also real-time monitoring.
So we can analyze the incoming data
streams and in real time identify
security incidents as they occur and get
alerted on them. Which brings us of
course to alerting and notification. So
we can actually generate alerts within
our SIM. We can set up rules and
thresholds to fire off notifications for
suspicious activities or policy
violations which allow us to rapidly
respond. Which of course brings us to
incident response. And we also typically
have dashboards and reports and
visualization capabilities. So we can
actually generate reports to share
amongst the team or with senior
management. We can do things like set up
visualizations and statistics to support
ongoing monitoring and compliance
efforts. And lastly, we can do things
like threat intelligence integration. So
we can actually incorporate external
threat feeds to enhance our detection
capabilities. So let's quickly talk
about the security orchestration
automation and response platform or the
soar platform. And this is more of a
holistic solution and kind of like a sim
on steroids that can combine the power
in orchestration and automation with
intelligent rapid response. And not all
socks are going to have a source
solution built out, but it can save a
lot of analyst and administrator time by
automating repetitive response tasks.
You know, we're never going to entirely
automate instant response, but source
solutions can certainly alleviate some
of the manual work. And we can do that
through orchestration, right? So with
this orchestration capability, we can
seamlessly collaborate and integrate
between different security technologies
like our SIM, our threat intelligence,
and different security controls like our
firewalls and ACL's, identity and access
management systems. So we can automate
some tasks that usually require manual
work, which of course leads us to
automation, and we can free up security
analyst time to focus on more complex
and high priority tasks. Sore platforms
can even do things like automated
artifact collection. For example, if a
reported fishing email comes through the
platform, it can automatically conduct
an initial analysis and extract specific
artifacts and indicators like domain
names or emails or IP addresses. And
through using automated playbooks or
runbooks, source can help streamline
incident response processes and ensure
that we have a consistent and effective
response every time. And we can also
integrate things like threat
intelligence and then generate reports
and metrics from our SOAR platforms as
well. So next we have incident
management tools. And this is kind of
like a catch-all kind of term because in
general incident management tools are
solutions we have that are designed for
the detection analysis but more so the
resolution of security incidents within
the organization's infrastructure. So
they provide this centralized platform
for us as a team to coordinate our
efforts, collaborate, document progress
and also manage incidents effectively.
So we can start using things like
ticketing management systems that allow
us as analysts to create, assign and
track incidents throughout the entire
incident life cycle. And these tickets
can serve as a central repository for
all the information related to each
incident. And we can also link incidents
together as needed. We also have alert
management. So through these tools, we
can integrate with our security
monitoring systems like our SIMs or any
of our you know detection and prevention
solutions to ingest security alerts
generated from all these sources. So we
can automate things with like workflow
automation. So when we get an alert
generated, we can automatically create a
ticket for that alert and make sure
nothing gets missed. And obviously here
we have the whole collaboration aspect
where we can effectively communicate and
collaborate amongst our team which is
often very essential during incident
response. You can see some examples
here. Some of these are more general
just IT ticket managing systems like
Atlassians Jura or Service Now
Freshworks. We also have some specific
ones like on page. Next we have network
security monitoring or NSM and this
specifically focuses on the detection
and mitigation of network related
threats and vulnerabilities. So these
tools provide us with the capacity to
monitor network traffic, analyze network
behavior and of course identify
potential incidents in real time based
on different rule matching and anomaly
detection and behavior detection. So we
can do things like packet capture and
analysis. So this allows us to actually
capture and analyze network traffic in
real time or retrospectively. And these
packet captures can give us a detailed
insight into the network communications
and things like protocols as well as
source and destination IPs, the actual
content within payloads and many more
capabilities. We can also do things like
perform network traffic analysis and use
techniques like statistical analysis,
machine learning and behavioral
profiling to identify potential security
threats. There's also some overlap here
with our intrusion detection systems or
our IDS systems. And some network
security monitoring tools actually have
built-in IDS functionality which allows
us to detect and respond to known and
unknown security incidents in real time.
So we can utilize things like
signaturebased detection, anomaly based
detection, and protocol analysis to
identify an alert on suspicious network
behavior. And of course, what would any
of this log collection be if we cannot
integrate it into a central repository,
which of course we can do through
integrations with our SIM platform. And
this integration enables the correlation
of network security events with other
security data like log data or endpoint
telemetry and threat intelligence feeds.
So we can start correlating and get a
central security monitoring and incident
response solution. And you can see some
common examples here. And we're actually
going to get hands-on with some of these
which I'm very excited for like Snort
and Siraata and Wireshark. And there's
also things like Zeke and Nagios. So
we've talked about IDS and IPS systems
quite a bit actually. So let's get into
what they actually are. So intrusion
detection systems and intrusion
prevention systems are designed to
monitor network traffic, detect
potential security events and take
action to mitigate and prevent
unauthorized access and malicious
activities. So what is the difference?
Right? So an IDS system or a detection
system is going to passively monitor the
network traffic and analyze it for signs
of malicious activity. And so they're
specifically designed to detect security
incidents and generate alerts based on
their predefined criteria like known
attack signatures or anomalous behavior
or different policy violations that we
set up. An IPS system on the other hand
is used to prevent attacks and it
actually builds upon the capabilities of
an IDS by actively blocking or
preventing detected threats in real
time. So in addition to detecting
security incidents, IPS systems have the
ability to take automated actions and
mitigate or stop malicious activities
before they can cause harm to the
network. And of course, both of these
tools are going to have detailed logging
information that we can then forward to
a SIM or a centralized management tool
for more event correlation. And again,
we have some similar players here. We
have Snort or Siraata or Zeke. This
brings us to endpoint detection and
response or EDR. And these tools
specifically focus on the protection of
endpoint devices such as laptops or
desktops, servers, and even mobile
devices. EDR tools are typically
deployed with an agent that sits on the
endpoint, which provides our
organization with that sort of single
pane of glass capacity to detect,
investigate, and actually respond to
security events as they occur at the
endpoint level. So, of course, we have
real-time endpoint monitoring. So, an
EDR tool or an agent is going to be
continuously monitoring the endpoint
device for any suspicious activities and
behaviors. And behaviors is the main
thing here. We can look at things like
suspicious processes that are starting
up or parent child relationships or
unauthorized access attempts or known
malicious downloads. By collecting all
this telemetry, we can actually provide
some real-time visibility into our
endpoints. And this brings us into user
entity behavior analysis or UEBA. And so
our EDR tool is going to leverage
behavioral analysis and behavioral
capabilities to detect things like
insider threats or compromised accounts
by monitoring user and entity behavior
on all the endpoint devices. So they can
look at things like login patterns and
user activity, file access behavior, you
know, when is a user typically accessing
a file or logging into their system and
a number of other behavioral indicators
to identify potentially anomalous or
suspicious activities. We also have more
general threat detection and prevention.
So we can introduce things like
signaturebased detection, machine
learning and huristics to identify and
prevent even unknown security threats.
So of course an EDR tool is going to be
almost crucial for us in incident
response and incident investigation if
we're dealing with an endpoint which we
often are. And through that these tools
are going to facilitate rapid response
and remediation actions to mitigate
these threats and contain incidents. We
can do things like quarantine and
isolate and roll back files for example.
We can kill processes and patch
management all remotely to respond to
incidents as they're occurring. And of
course, all of the logs that we
generate, all of the alerts from our EDR
tools can and should be forwarded to our
centralized logging capability or our
SIM. And you can see some examples here.
Of course, CrowdStrike Falcon, we have
Sophos, Carbon Black, Sentinel 1. There
are many EDR tools out there. And next
up, we have firewalls. And firewalls are
a fundamental component of network
security designed to monitor and control
incoming and outgoing network traffic
based on predefined security rules. And
in the traditional sense, they kind of
act as this barrier between a trusted
internal network and an untrusted
external network such as the internet.
We also have different types of
firewalls depending on specific use
cases and feature complexity. So we have
the most common network firewall that
you're probably familiar with. These are
also known as just traditional or
stateful firewalls and they operate at
that network layer or layer 3 of the OSI
model. They examine packets of data as
they pass through the firewall and make
decisions based on factors like the
source and destination IPs, the port
numbers and protocols. We also have the
concept of next generation firewalls or
NGFWs and these are more advanced
firewall solutions that integrate
additional security features beyond the
traditional network firewalls
capabilities. They combine stateful
packet inspection with more advanced
security technologies like deep packet
inspection where they can actually open
up individual packets and inspect them
at that level or things like application
awareness because again they work on
that layer 7 or application protocol.
And lastly here we have the web
application firewall or the WFT and
these are specialized firewalls designed
to protect web applications from a
variety of web-based attacks like SQL
injection, cross-sight scripting and
other application layer vulnerabilities.
And again, unlike traditional firewalls,
these also operate on layer 7 because
they're dealing with the application
layer. And you can see some common
examples here of firewall technologies
like Palo Alto, Sonic Wall, PFSense,
Juniper, F5, and more. Next, we have
threat intelligence platforms. And these
are designed to aggregate, analyze, and
operationalize threat intelligence data
to enhance our defenses and improve
threat detection and response
capabilities. So these platforms can
aggregate threat intelligence data from
a wide variety of sources like open
source feeds, commercial providers,
government agencies, or even specific
industry groups. And they can then
enrich our raw threat data by
correlating and contextualizing it with
this additional information like threat
actor profiles, malware characteristics,
attack techniques, or even indicators of
compromise. And IoC's or indicators of
compromise might be things like hashes
of known malware executables or known
malicious domains or IP addresses or
different tools that adversaries are
using or even like host and network
artifacts on systems or even the tactics
and techniques themselves that
adversaries use during an attack. And we
can also think about things like
normalization and standardization where
this threat intelligence data is
consistent and operable across many
different sources and formats. And they
use specific schemas and protocols,
things like sticks and taxi, which we're
going to cover later on, which make it
easier for security analysts to ingest
and consume and analyze this threat
intelligence data. And of course, we can
integrate all of this within our SIM. So
we can actually get that data enrichment
right from a single pane of glass. And
we have a couple different examples
here. We have OpenCTI, we have the MISP
threat sharing platform, we have Maltego
or Maltiggo, however you want to
pronounce it, as well as Recorded
Future. Getting close to the end here,
we have forensic analysis tools. And
these are specialized pieces of software
that are designed to collect, analyze,
and interpret digital evidence from
computer systems or networks or storage
devices for the purposes of forensic
investigations. And through these tools,
we can do things like data acquisition
and imaging where we're actually
creating forensic images or bit-by-bit
copies of storage media so we can
preserve the integrity of the original
evidence. We can use tools that can
perform file system analysis and
actually extract metadata or file
attributes, timestamps. We also have a
suite of tools that can do memory
forensics. So, we can actually capture
memory dumps from compromised systems.
We can analyze that volatile memory or
RAM for evidence of malicious
activities, things like fileless
malware, any modules or DLS that were
loaded or even open network connections.
We have tools for registry forensics
where we can actually uncover evidence
of user activity and system
configuration changes to find things
like malware persistence mechanisms or
even network traffic forensics where we
can look at things like network traffic
logs or packet captures which again
there's some overlap here with some of
these tools and we're going to be
covering some of these tools in the
digital forensics section like autopsy
and volatility. We also have the Eric
Zimmerman tool suite and things like
cape and INC case as well. And lastly
here we have malware analysis tools and
these are specialized pieces of software
that are designed to analyze and dissect
malware to understand its behavior
functionality as well as the impact on
systems and networks. And it's also
useful sometimes to know what types of
threats and how advanced threat actors
are who are targeting our organization.
So we can do things like dynamic
analysis where we can actually execute
and detonate malware samples in a
controlled environment like a virtual
machine or a sandbox so we can then
monitor the behavior in real time. You
know you can think about investigating a
potential fishing email that contains a
word document attachment. You want to
perform some dynamic sandbox analysis to
determine if there are any malicious
macros embedded inside that execute when
it's opened. So we can observe and log
the activities like file system
modifications, registry changes, network
communications or processes that are
being spawned. Basically any system
interaction that helps us understand the
malware behavior. There's also the
concept of static analysis where we can
actually provide tools with a sample of
malware for it to without actually
executing it but focus on examining the
file attributes and code structure
embedded resources and metadata. There's
also signature and pattern matching
capabilities where we can look at known
signatures or patterns or heruristics
stored in malware databases and threat
intelligence feeds so we can identify
known threats and variants. And another
way to say this is that we can integrate
with our threat intelligence platforms
to correlate analysis results with
existing threat intelligence data and
feeds. And to wrap this up, you can see
some examples here. We have a screenshot
of any run which is an interactive
malware analysis suite. We also have
other tools like hybrid analysis, Joe
sandbox as well as gedra for actual
reverse engineering
purposes. Okay, we are finally at the
home stretch of this section. So, thank
you for sticking this out. Throughout
the course, we're going to be covering a
number of detection and response efforts
for a number of different types of
attacks and subsequent incidents. And
because of this, it's going to be very
important for us to have a good
understanding of what the most common
attacks and threats are that Sock teams
typically face. So, you can see a number
of different attacks laid out on the
screen here that we're going to cover.
And these various attacks can target
different vulnerabilities or weaknesses,
but ultimately they all have similar
objectives or goals in mind to
compromise a system or excfiltrate
sensitive data. So, let's start out with
social engineering. And we've talked
about it quite a bit before. Social
engineering is an attack that exploits
the human side of cyber security rather
than any kind of technical
vulnerability. And a common goal here is
to gain some sort of unauthorized access
to a system or exfiltrate some sort of
data or gain some sort of user
credential that can then be spoofed or
impersonated. So for example, we can
think of an attacker posing as a trusted
IT technician and maybe they call up an
employee claiming that there's a problem
with their computer or their account and
they request their login credentials so
they can fix it. and the employee
thinking that it's a legitimate IT
technician might actually give their
credentials over the phone leading to an
account compromise. And we've talked
about fishing a lot too. And fishing
involves sending some sort of deceptive
email or a message to someone and
appearing to be from some sort of
legitimate source like a bank or a
trusted organization. And these emails
will typically contain an attachment or
some sort of malicious link that when
clicked that can lead to a malicious
website to trick a user into putting in
their credentials or downloading some
sort of malware. And we're going to
cover fishing and analyzing fishing
emails in the next section of this
course. But at a high level, we have
different types of fishing, right? We
have spear fishing, which is a targeted
form of fishing where an attacker is
going to tailor their message
specifically to an individual or an
organization. So often this requires a
lot of research beforehand so an
attacker can personalize their email
with convincing details or gain some
credibility to make them more likely to
succeed. We also have whaling, which is
a type of spear fishing, which
specifically targets high-profile
individuals within an organization. So,
we can think of people like senior
executives or some sort of senior
management because these types of people
typically have more access or more
exposure to sensitive information that
can be stolen. We also have fishing or
voice fetching, which was in our
example. This is where an attacker calls
someone over the phone and attempts to
trick them into providing sensitive
information, performing certain actions,
or giving up their account credentials.
Similarly, we have SMS fishing or
smishing, which is the same kind of
thing, but an attack conducted through
text messages or SMS messages. So, you
may have gotten a suspicious text before
from a number you didn't recognize that
asks you to click on a link or visit a
web page. Most likely, this was a
smishing attack. And lastly, here we
have quishing, which is a weird word,
but essentially refers to QR code
fishing. And this is a similar type of
attack where an attacker is going to try
to deceive someone into scanning a
malicious QR code that is then going to
lead them to some sort of fishing
website. So, let's talk about malware or
any malicious software that's designed
to harm or exploit an organization or an
individual because there's several
different types of malware that we can
cover here. And the first one here being
a worm. And a worm is a malicious
program designed to replicate itself and
spread across networks or on the
internet and often without requiring any
user interaction. So they may do this by
exploiting some sort of vulnerability so
they can infect and propagate throughout
a network and infect more people. We
have a couple notable examples of worms.
So first we have stuckset which was a
highly sophisticated worm discovered
around 2010 but was in development from
much earlier and it was specifically
crafted to target SCADA systems used in
industrial environments and particularly
to attack Iran's nuclear program. And it
did this by exploiting multiple zeroday
vulnerabilities and chaining those
together to infect and propagate. We
also have blaster which is the one
pictured here on the right. This is a
hex output of what the actual worm
looked like. And it was an older worm
back in around 2003 that exploited a
vulnerability in Microsoft Windows. And
while technically a ransomware, if you
remember Wukry from 2017, it used
wormlike capabilities to propagate
across the network. Specifically, it
exploited a vulnerability in Windows
Server message block or the SMB protocol
to infect unpatched Windows systems. So,
let's quickly talk about spyware and
adwear, which are similar but share some
distinctions. And these are types of
malware that either covertly monitor
user activity or display unwanted
advertisements respectively. So with
spyware, it's specifically designed to
again secretly monitor and collect
information from a user's computer
without their knowledge or consent. And
it can do this by things like installing
a key logger or tracking keystrokes or
capturing screens or the webcam. It can
look at browsing habits of the user or
gather some sort of other personal
information and send that to somewhere
else. AdWare on the other hand is often
bundled with other software like free
applications or browser extensions you
find. And again, it's typically
installed without the user's explicit
consent. But the primary purpose of
adwear is to generate revenue by
delivering targeted advertisements to
the user. So you might install adwear
unexpectedly and start to see a bunch of
ads on your desktop or within the
homepage of your browser or your search
bar. So next we have Trojans, which is
actually named after the famous Trojan
horse from Greek mythology. And they're
a type of malware that, as the name
suggests, disguises itself as a
legitimate program to deceive users into
executing it. So unlike worms, which can
actually self-replicate and spread on
their own, Trojans will typically rely
on social engineering tactics to trick
users into installing or executing them.
They're typically distributed through
various channels. So things like fishing
email attachments or on malicious
websites or within a software download,
often masquerading as some sort of
legitimate or innocent looking file like
a game or some sort of extension or a
productivity application. And most
commonly Trojans are going to be in the
form of remote access Trojans or RATS.
And these are a type of Trojan that
gives an attacker remote control over a
system. And they will typically create a
back door on the infected system so the
attacker can return and regain that
access as desired. And this may lead
into some sort of botnet recruitment
where a Trojan can be used to recruit
infected systems into a botnet which is
a network of compromised devices that
use a central command and control
server. And we'll touch on botnetss in a
second. But lastly, Trojans can be used
to actually deliver ransomware. And
speaking of ransomware, well, ransomware
is a very scary type of malware that's
designed to encrypt files on a victim's
computer or within a network. and it
renders these files inaccessible by
demanding a ransom payment in exchange
for the decryption key. And typically a
ransomware attack is going to follow a
specific sequence of steps. So first
obviously there's going to be an
infection and this could be through a
malicious email attachment like a
fishing email like we said or through a
compromised website. Maybe someone
accidentally downloads something. It
could even be like a Trojan. Maybe
someone thinks they're downloading a
music app. But in reality it's going to
be ransomware. And once the ransomware
gains access to the system, it's going
to start quickly encrypting files using
that strong encryption algorithm and
using public key infrastructure so that
they can't be decrypted without that
specific key. And after encrypting
files, you're typically going to see
some sort of ransom note like we have on
the right here that informs the victim
that their files have been encrypted and
provides instructions on how to actually
pay the ransom back, which is typically
going to be done through some sort of
cryptocurrency because cryptocurrency is
a lot more difficult to trace. And
lastly, we're going to have decryption
if you're lucky because this is a cyber
criminal we're talking about. So even if
the ransom is paid by an organization,
there's no guarantee that they're going
to actually get the decryption key back
to recover their files, which is why
having strong backups and recent backups
is the most important and most useful
way to get around ransomware. So we
mentioned botnets before, and a botnet
is a network of compromised devices or
computers that are infected with
malware, and they're typically referred
to as zombies because they're
essentially being controlled remotely by
a single entity. And botnets are often
used in various malicious purposes like
launching and staging denial of service
attacks or DDoSes, distributed denial of
service attacks or spreading malware or
sending spam emails or even things like
mining cryptocurrencies without a user's
knowledge. We also have fileless malware
which is also known as memory based
malware. And this is a type of malware
that operates primarily within memory
and it's able to execute and operate
without leaving traces of its presence
on the victim's file system. So unlike
traditional malware that relies on files
and executables to infect systems,
fileless malware can leverage legitimate
systems or something we refer to as
living off the land to carry out
malicious activities which makes it a
lot more difficult to detect and log. So
often fileless malware is going to use
techniques like Windows PowerShell
scripts or Windows management
instrumentation or WI or even inject
malicious commands within memory to
carry out its objectives. Now, this is a
big one. Identity and account
compromise. And they're kind of two
separate things, but identity and
account compromise or also known as
identity theft or account takeover
occurs when an unauthorized individual
gains access to someone's personal
information or their user credentials or
their online accounts without their
permission. And this can include various
types of sensitive data like we
mentioned like usernames, passwords,
even things like social security numbers
or credit card numbers. And once an
attacker gains access to an individual's
account or identity, they can carry out
various types of malicious activities
like impersonating them or even fraud
and making unauthorized purchases using
their stolen credit card information. If
an attacker can impersonate a victim,
they can start sending spam emails or
fishing emails from that compromised
user to make them appear more
legitimate. And often this type of
attack can be done through fishing or
brute forcing credentials or things like
credential stuffing where an attacker
gains a user's credentials through a
breach and then subsequently tries that
password or credentials on different
services for that user to try to gain
access as well. Next we have insider
threats and these refer to the risk that
an organization faces by individuals
from within that organization or someone
who has authorized access to sensitive
information. So these may be current or
former employees. It could be
contractors or partners or any trusted
entity that has legitimate access
privileges. And insider threats can
often manifest in various forms. So we
may have a malicious insider and that's
someone who intentionally misuses their
privileges to steal data or commit fraud
or uh sabotage the company in some way.
But we also have careless insiders. And
this is someone who inadvertently
compromises their security through
things like their negligence or
carelessness or just their general lack
of awareness. And lastly, we have a
compromise insider which could be the
result of something like identity or
account compromise. And this is where
someone's credentials or access
privileges get compromised by an
attacker either through fishing or
social engineering and then the attacker
is then exploiting that account to gain
unauthorized access and steal sensitive
information. And as you can imagine,
insider threats can have serious
consequences for organizations and lead
to things like data breaches or IP theft
or financial loss, reputational damage,
and even legal liabilities. The other
thing, too, is that insider threats can
be very challenging to detect and
mitigate because insiders often have
legitimate access to these services and
can often blend in with normal user
behavior. We also have advanced
persistent threats or APS and these are
sophisticated cyber groups that are
highly orchestrated and highly skilled
and often wellunded such as nation state
actors or organized crime groups. And
unlike typical cyber attacks which are
more opportunistic and may be
short-lived, APS are characterized by
several things like their
sophistication. So they might employ
advanced techniques and tools and
develop their own custom malware or
leverage zeroday exploits. And as the
name suggests, they're often persistent.
And these groups are able to maintain
long-term access. We're talking like
months or years. And they're often very
targeted, right? So, not every
organization is going to have an AP in
their threat model. We're mainly
thinking of specific organizations or
industries or government entities or
even countries. And lastly, they
typically have strategic objectives. So,
they're trying to do things like
espionage or steal intellectual property
or sabotage or cause some sort of
disruption to critical infrastructure.
And many vendors actually categorize APS
based on their industry and geography.
For example, Crowdstrike uses a naming
convention called Falcon Intelligence to
identify AP groups, which you can check
out at this link here. And you can
actually search based on your industry
and your business size as well as your
country. But if we just start looking at
some of the groups here, you can see we
have different known groups as well as
their names depending on their country,
right? So with Iran, we have banished
kitten or static kitten. With Russia,
it's primarily bears, right? We have
fancy bear or cozy bear. We can also
view these groups in a different naming
convention with mandant. So mandant as
you can see uses this apt format with
different numbers to attribute different
groups. So for example a39 is attributed
to Iran and a31 is attributed to China.
And we can actually view these groups on
the miter attack framework which we're
going to look at later in more depth.
But just as a quick aside you can see we
have this groups tab here where we have
all the different names and their IDs.
And if we just do a search for fancy
bear, you can see we have that under
AP28, which is the Mandant naming
convention as well as the crowd strike
naming convention with fancy bear here.
And if we click to a specific group name
and scroll down to techniques used, we
can actually see what types of common
techniques and tactics does this group
use. So we can see here with fancy bear
or apt28, they typically use a
PowerShell command lit to grant the
application impersonation role to a
compromised account.
So we also have denial of service
attacks which are aimed to disrupt or
degrade the availability of systems and
often this could be done by overwhelming
them with a flood of traffic or resource
requests. And denial of service attacks
don't always have to be intentional. For
example, some sort of system failure or
accidental misconfiguration or just
general network congestion or spikes in
legitimate traffic can also cause
service interruptions. Now we also have
distributed denial of service attacks
which we mentioned earlier where they
have multiple compromised systems or
devices to target a single system. By
using multiple devices and compromised
zombies, an attacker can amplify their
attack making it much harder to defend
against. However, there are a lot of
service providers out there that offer
things like DOS protection where they're
going to leverage scalable and elastic
cloud infrastructure to spin up extra
resources in the event of a DOS so that
the organization can ride out the storm
so to speak. But this can be costly
obviously. It's more of an insurance
type of thing. So, we have data breaches
which are going to occur when sensitive
or confidential information is accessed
or disclosed or stolen without
authorization. And data breaches are
often the outcome of some of the threats
that we mentioned earlier like cyber
attacks or insider threats. But they can
also be disclosed accidentally through
human error or misconfigurations or just
inadequate security controls such as
like a non-secured S3 bucket in the
cloud. Just as an example or an
anecdote, I once led the incident
response efforts on an information
disclosure incident where that the
customer reports that were generated
from one of our organizations systems
were accidentally being hosted on
publicly accessible links. The only
reason that this was identified is
because these links were being crawled
and indexed by search engines which was
quite a serious concern and required a
lot of recovery efforts and contacting
multiple search engines and website
archives to ensure that all of this data
was wiped. So obviously with data
breaches we can think of a lot of
reputational damage that can occur or
regulatory trouble. And so nearing the
end here we have zero days which are
software vulnerabilities that are
unknown to the software vendor or
developer and have not been patched or
fixed to date. And these are called zero
days because they are typically
exploited by actors before the vendor
has a chance to release a patch leaving
vendors with zero days to fix the
vulnerability and users or organizations
with zero days to protect themselves.
And zero days themselves can often exist
in various types of software. So
operating systems or web browsers,
applications, databases or even firmware
themselves. Historically we can think of
things like heartbleleed or shell shock
or log forj. Typically due to the nature
of zero days, organizations are left to
rely on risk mitigation and avoidance
strategies through implementing things
like compensating controls until an
official patch from the vendor is
released. And lastly here we have supply
chain attacks. These are a type of
threat or attack that targets the
software supply chain to compromise the
security downstream to organizations or
users. So instead of directly attacking
a target organization systems or
networks, attackers are going to exploit
vulnerabilities or weaknesses in the
software or services provided by third
parties, vendors or partners. And
because of this, the threat is going to
propagate down, which makes it hard to
detect, right? Because this is a type of
malware that's from trusted entities. It
might actually be digitally signed as
well by trusted entities. So hopefully
this gives you a good understanding of
the common threats organizations face
and gives you a good primer that
prepares you for the next section of
this
course. Welcome to the fishing analysis
section of this course. And this is a
topic that I really wanted to do justice
and give it the true focus that it
deserves. Because although we talk about
how every sock is different and every
organization has different priorities or
threat models or attack surfaces, one
constant is that no matter any of these
variables, chances are that fishing is
going to be one of the consistent
threats that your company faces. And
this is due to its, you know, ubiquity
and its low barrier for entry for
attackers and quite honestly its success
rate. It is often a good return on
investment for attackers to employ
fishing techniques. And I also thought
it would be a good idea to cover this
first in the course because although
many of the analysis and response
concepts that we're going to cover here
are going to be built upon later on in
the course, analyzing fishing emails is
a great practical skill to have in any
security analyst role and one that we
can readily dive into here. So let's
quickly cover our objectives for this
domain. First, we want to understand the
fundamentals of fishing and its
prevalence. We will soon learn why
fishing is such a big deal in pretty
much any organization that we find
ourselves in. Next, we want to learn a
strong methodology for analyzing fishing
emails. You know, if we want to analyze
effectively and efficiently, well, we
need to have a strong process that we
can rely on. We also want to develop, of
course, some hands-on skills,
specifically in analyzing the email
content or the email headers. And we
want to be able to trace the original
senders of emails. You know, we're going
to take a look at many real life fishing
email examples and how to extract
malicious artifacts or indicators of
compromise and also understand the true
nature of these emails. And next, we
want to gain an understanding in
identifying and analyzing malicious URLs
and attachments. So, we're going to look
at some manual and automated means to
again extract those IoC's and make
determinations and judgments. And we
want to explore both proactive and also
reactive defense strategies against
fishing attacks. So, we're going to take
a look at how organizations can prevent
or most likely mitigate fishing at the
source or through technical means. And
lastly here, of course, we need to learn
to document and communicate our fishing
analysis findings correctly and
proficiently. You know, there's no point
in building all of this methodology and
gaining these hands-on skills if we
can't communicate it or have another
analyst follow our steps. So, we're
going to cover how to properly write
reports and what we need to include when
we close out fishing tickets. So, first
here, what exactly is fishing? You know,
we covered it briefly before, but at a
high level, why is it something that we
should be concerned about? And what role
do sock analysts play in the day-to-day
for defending against fishing attacks?
Well, fishing, as we've covered before,
can be described as an attempt to steal
information from victims through the use
of social engineering techniques and
various communication channels like
email or SMS or even over the phone or
on the web. And often this is done with
a malicious individual impersonating a
legitimate organization or a legitimate
entity to trick recipients into
revealing that sensitive information.
Things like their passwords or their
credit card numbers or other sensitive
files that the attacker finds useful.
And another common goal of fishing
attempts is to have the recipient either
download a file or visit an infected
site so that malware can then be
downloaded and installed onto the victim
device. And fishing attacks are so
prevalent in organizations because they
exploit what we would typically refer to
as the weakest link in the security
chain, the humans. These recipients or
end users are often the first line of
defense against fishing attempts because
they're the ones who are actively
receiving them. And it's very easy for
attackers to cast a wide net by sending
fishing emails to entire companies or
departments and hoping that just one of
those individuals will take the bait.
And once a fishing email is successful,
of course, it can lead to severe
consequences. things like unauthorized
access or account compromise, stealing
sensitive data or financial or
reputational loss. And of course, this
isn't to say that end users are the
problem or anything. It just means that
that's where we need to focus the most
on proactive defense measures. And we'll
get to that later on in this section.
You know, while we have many technical
controls that we can implement to
mitigate fishing attacks from getting to
our users at the source, well, not
everything is foolproof at the end of
the day. Remember, we think of this
concept of defense in depth. Us as sock
analysts need to be quick and efficient
at spotting and analyzing and of course
responding to fishing emails because we
are the frontline defenders against
these threats. So how does fishing
actually work? And you know fishing or
rather social engineering itself
exploits several human principles to
achieve its objectives. So, we can list
some of these out, right? We have
authority. And so, fishing emails will
often impersonate a figure of authority
such as a company executive or a manager
or even the IT staff and by claiming to
represent a trusted and authoritative
source. Well, attackers might be able to
compel victims into complying with odd
or malicious requests without question.
So, for example, a common fishing
scenario with organizations is an email
supposedly from the CEO requesting
employees to buy gift cards for some
seemingly legitimate purpose. Because
the email is often spoofed as the CEO,
this impersonation of a top
authoritative figure in the company
might actually persuade employees to
make these purchases and send the
details to the attacker. Another common
example is someone seemingly from the IT
department claiming to be conducting
some sort of audit or security audit and
requesting employees to provide their
login credentials to verify their
accounts. The next one we have here is
trust. And fishing emails often rely on
elements of building up trust such as
using authentic looking logos from
trusted organizations or official
sounding language or even making
references to reputable companies or you
know internal company policies. And by
crafting this illusion of trust,
attackers aim to lead individuals into
that false sense of security, which in
turn increases the likelihood of
compliance with their requests. So for
example, an attacker might send out an
email appearing to be from a well-known
bank. Maybe the attacker actually went
as far as to conduct research into the
area and identified that a particular
bank is very common among these
employees. And so a legitimate looking
email from this bank requesting some
sort of account verification might have
a good chance at deceiving recipients
into logging into some sort of
credential harvesting page or providing
their sensitive information. So next we
have intimidation. And fishing attacks
can use intimidation tactics to instill
a sense of fear and attempt to coersse
individuals into some sort of immediate
action. So we can think of things like
threats of legal consequences or account
suspensions or financial penalties.
These can all sort of intimidate
recipients into complying with the
attacker's demands. So, for instance,
maybe an attacker sends out an email
warning of an impending legal action
unless an employee sends over
information or pays a fake invoice. You
know, depending on the wording of this
email, an attacker might be able to
induce a sense of fear or panic and
prompt individuals to act impulsively
through intimidation. We also have
social proof or this concept of
consensus. And fishing emails might
leverage the concept of social proof by
referencing other individuals or even
organizations that have supposedly
benefited from taking similar action.
And by implying that there's already
this widespread sense of acceptance or
endorsement, well, an attacker might be
able to trick individuals into
validating the legitimacy of their
request and reduce any chance for
skepticism. So, for example, an attacker
could send out an email claiming that,
well, thousands of satisfied customers
have already verified their accounts and
now you can, too. or emails like
hundreds of investors have already
gotten rich by signing up to our
investing platform, that kind of thing.
Which brings us to urgency. And so
fishing emails often, as the name
suggest, can create a sense of urgency
by emphasizing a time-sensitive issue or
impending deadline. And often this can
take the form of some sort of urgent
request for account verification or a
mandatory password reset or a financial
transaction that needs to occur. And due
to the time-sensitive nature of these
requests, well, they can pressure
recipients into acting quickly without
fully evaluating the legitimacy of the
claim. So, for example, an attacker
could send out an email warning that
there was unauthorized access on their
account and they urge for an immediate
password change as their account is now
at risk. As another example, a common
tactic is emails that mention a user
must update their password immediately
or their account will be locked out
indefinitely. We also have the concept
of scarcity, which is related but not
the exact same as urgency. So unlike
urgency which again urges negative
consequences for account lockouts or
security issues, scarcity is often done
by suggesting that an opportunity or
resource is limited or time-sensitive.
And so attackers aim to provoke a fear
of missing out or FOMO and prompt
recipients to act quickly. So for
instance, an attacker might send out an
email offering an exclusive access or
limited time discounts or promotions.
And due to the human nature of not
wanting to miss out on these
opportunities, these types of emails
might tempt individuals to click on a
malicious link or provide information
without thinking it through. And lastly,
here we have familiarity. And this
refers to a sense of recognition or
acquaintance with someone or something.
And in the context of fishing, attackers
can exploit familiarity by creating an
illusion of pre-existing connections or
interactions to lower a recipient's
guard. And so this tactic aims to make
the fishing attempt appear more credible
and less suspicious by leveraging
elements that the recipient finds
familiar or recognizable. So for
instance, imagine an email that's
masquerading as communication from a
familiar friend or a colleague or some
sort of reputable organization. By
playing on the feelings of familiarity,
an attacker might be able to evoke a
sense of trust and acquaintance, making
individuals more susceptible to
manipulation. And lastly, here as
another example, maybe an attacker is
able to compromise an actual victim's
email account. And so they might use
that newfound access to stage more
sophisticated attacks using the concepts
of familiarity. And so maybe once they
gain access to someone's inbox, they
start replying to ongoing threads or
emailing known users based on the user's
contacts. And so when these future
victims receive an email coming from a
legitimate contact, well, they'll very
likely trust the content of the fishing
email and be less inclined to question
its authenticity or
legitimacy. And so lastly here, I've
stressed a couple times now how
prevalent fishing attacks are. So let's
take a look at some real world examples
of actual fishing attacks in the wild
and how they compromise organizations
through that weak link and the
devastating impact that they've had. And
quite honestly, when I was compiling a
good list of stories to cover here,
well, there were actually so many
options to choose from, which really
speaks to how some of these attacks
occur. But I think this is a decent list
of notable attacks to start with. So,
first we have the Colonial Pipeline
attack back in May of 2021. And Colonial
Pipeline is a major fuel pipeline
operator in the United States. And in
back in May of 2021, they fell victim to
a sophisticated fishing attack
attributed to the Russian-based Dark
Side hacking group, which is known to
target its victims using ransomware and
extortion. And in this case, the
attackers used fishing emails to deliver
ransomware onto the Colonial Pipelines
network. And as it typically does, the
ransomware quickly spread and ended up
infecting critical systems that actually
disrupted the pipelines's operations.
And so as a result, Colonial Pipeline
was forced to shut down its pipeline,
which caused a number of fuel shortages
and panic buying across the United
States. So much so that nearly half of
the US East Coast oil supply was shut
down for a week. As for the ransom, the
attackers demanded a payment of 4.4
million in Bitcoin to restore the access
to the Colonial Pipeline systems. And
quite honestly, this incident really
highlighted how something as simple as
fishing can lead to such devastating
economic and societal real world
consequences. And the second one here
has to do with Levitas Capital back in
2020. And Levitas Capital was a New
York-based hedge fund that became the
target of a fishing attack. And
specifically, it was a whailing attack
that was targeted against its
co-founder. And as it was reported, an
attacker sent out an email containing a
malicious URL for a fake Zoom meeting.
And back in 2020, well, this was
particularly around the time where
remote work and Zoom really started
taking off, which of course attackers
took full advantage of. So this one
malicious link led to the download and
installation of malware and eventually
led to attackers generating over 8.5
million in fraudulent invoices. And as
you can expect, this kind of attack led
to both financial but also reputational
consequences. So much so that the fund
ended up losing clients due to its
impact which ultimately led to the
closure of the
business. And so third here we have the
ubiquity networks attack back in 2015.
And ubiquity is quite a large networking
technology company. But back in 2015,
well, they fell victim to once again a
sophisticated fishing attack. In this
case, it was reported that this type of
attack was a CEO fraud or a business
email compromise attack. So, this type
of attack usually begins with an
attacker either fishing an executive and
actually gaining access to their inbox
or emailing employees from a spoofed
lookalike domain that looks like the
target company's real domain. And in the
case of this story, attackers managed to
impersonate executives and trick
employees into wiring funds. And as a
result, well, around 46.7 million in
funds were transferred to other overseas
accounts. And actually, Brian Krebs of
Krebs on Security really covered this
story well back when it was going on.
So, I encourage you to read more at this
link if you're interested. And lastly,
here we have Ukraine's power grid attack
back in 2015. And so in December of
2015, well, Ukraine's power grid was
targeted in a highly coordinated cyber
attack attributed to the AP group
Sandworm, which is associated with
Russian intelligence agencies. And so
this attack actually used spear fishing
emails to deliver malware, which got the
attackers initial access into the power
grid systems. And once inside the
network, the attackers were able to
seize SCADA equipment and remotely
switched off substations and disabled
infrastructure components like power
supplies and modems and other
communicators. And in total, 30
substations were switched off and about
230,000 people were without electricity
for some time. And this incident was
really marked as one of the first known
instances of a cyber attack causing
physical disruptions to critical
infrastructure at this scale. And of
course, it all started from that spear
fishing campaign. So hopefully you found
these stories interesting. I encourage
you to read more about them if you're so
inclined. And hopefully it gave you a
good idea into how important fishing
analysis is and how important it is that
we defend our organizations from fishing
attacks. Let's quickly cover how email
works. And it might seem a bit high
level at this stage, but understanding
how emails are transferred across the
internet will help us with one of the
most important strategies in email
analysis. Determining sender origin and
attribution. And chances are you've sent
and received emails before, either in
your professional or personal life. But
have you ever actually dove in to
understand the components that make up
and deliver email messages? Well, if you
have, then you'll probably breeze
through this intro. But if not, I think
this is worth discussing. And at its
core, sending email operates on a simple
yet robust system called the Simple Mail
Transfer Protocol or SMTP. So, let's
break down the process a little bit.
When you compose an email and hit send,
your email client like Gmail or Outlook
or Thunderbird communicates with an SMTP
server. And typically, you'll find these
mail clients in either a desktop or a
web application format. And this server
acts as the post office for your email
and manages it transfer to the
recipient's inbox. So, in this example,
let's say Bob, who has a Gmail account,
decides to send an email to his friend
Alice, who uses a Yahoo mail account.
Well, he opens his Gmail account and
then composes his message and addresses
it to Alice's Yahoo email address. And
so your email client connects to your
email provider's SMTP server. And this
server authenticates your identity and
usually uses some sort of username and
password to ensure that you have
permission to send emails from this
account. And we'll quickly cover the
protocols in a second, but typically
this is done over port 25, which is the
standard simple mail transfer protocol
port. And so when Bob hits send, his
email client communicates with Gmail's
SMTP server, which verifies his
identity, usually through his Gmail
username and password, and accepts the
email for delivery. And so Gmail's SMTP
server checks the domain part of Alice's
email address, in this case, the
yahoo.com, and queries DNS to find the
IP address of the Yahoo's SMTP server.
And then at this point, it's then
forwarded to the recipient's SMTP
server. And again, this is done by
quering the domain name system or the
DNS to find the recipient's email
server's IP address. And so at this
stage, the Yahoo's SMTP server receives
the email and stores it in Alice's
inbox, ready for her to access it. And
finally here, when the recipient checks
on the email, well, their email client,
again, like Outlook or Gmail, in this
case, Yahoo, connects to the server to
download the email. And so there are
separate protocols like POP 3 and IMAP
that allow for the retrieval of email,
but we'll touch on those in a second.
And so when Alice logs into her email
account, well, her email client connects
to Yahoo server and downloads the email
from Bob into her
inbox. And so next, let's touch on the
components that actually make up email.
Specifically, we have email headers. And
email headers are what essentially make
up an email. And they're lines of text
that provide information on an email's
origin, routing, and how it should be
handled. And you're likely used to
seeing some of these headers in various
email clients that you interact with.
But the majority of email headers are
abstracted from the user. And so when it
comes to investigating potential fishing
emails, well, email headers are one of
the first things that we turn to. For
example, here is an email that I opened
in Mozilla Thunderbird, which is a mail
client similar to Outlook or built-in
mail apps that you might have used
before. And upon doing so, we can
immediately see some of the common email
headers that have been graphically
displayed within the email client. For
example, on the right here, well, we can
see the timestamp of when the email was
delivered. And over here, we can see the
subject line of the email. We can also
see the recipient and the reply to
header. And we're going to get more into
email header analysis in a future lesson
because it's really important to note
that almost all of these headers that we
see here can be spoofed by an attacker.
So, we can't immediately trust what our
email client displays. And now I
mentioned that these were only a small
subset of the actual headers attached to
a typical email. And this is true. Just
as a quick example, we can export the
entire list of email headers to get a
holistic view of what makes up an email
message. And you can see we have a large
number of headers here. And these are
some of the ones we saw in our email
client, right? We have the subject, the
date or that timestamp, as well as some
of the others here like the recipient.
But we have so much more and even custom
headers that we can see here. And there
are many different ways to extract the
email headers like this depending on
your email client. And we're going to
cover some common methods in the email
analysis
section. So next we have the email body.
And the email body serves as the main
content space within an email message.
And it can include various elements like
plain text or HTML or even multimedia
rich content. And this section often
includes not only textual elements but
also hyperlinks and embedded images or
HTML formatting. And so let's return to
our example here in
Thunderbird. And you can see the actual
email body being rendered here. And it
looks to be appearing as intended. We
have some custom styling here for this
blue bigger text here. We have a button
that we can click on as well as a
company logo. But like with a web page,
this is rendered to the client and we
can't actually see the components or the
code that is making up the contents of
this email. And so if we export this
email or even just go to view the
message source, well, we can scroll down
past the email headers here and we're
going to see the actual content or the
HTML markup of this email message. We
can see the content type here is in HTML
and we actually have some valid HTML
markup as well as CSS styling that is
making up the contents of this
email. And so what is an email address?
Well, at its core, email addresses are
unique identifiers assigned to
individuals or organizations and
entities, enabling them to send and
receive email through email services.
And so, an email address such as the one
you see on the screen here,
bob.smith@acample.com, is made up from
multiple parts. So, first we have the
local part or the mailbox. And the local
part often represents the username or
the alias of the email account holder.
And it can contain various characters
like letters or numbers or periods, even
underscores and hyphens. In some cases,
the local part might include additional
information like the department or the
role within an organization. And it
might separate those with periods or
hyphens. And most often, you'll see this
done with different syntax. Right here
we have Bob. So we have first name.ast
name. Some organizations might do first
initial last name. Or you might have
specific mailboxes for finance or
accounting. And so the second part here
is the domain part. And the domain part
of an email address identifies the mail
server that hosts the email account. And
it of course typically consists of two
or more segments separated by periods
such as example.com or
company.co.uk. And specifically, this
last segment here is known as the top
level domain or the TLD. And this
indicates the type or the category of
the domain such as.com or.org or.net or
even country specific tople domains
like.uk. And so we mentioned DNS before.
And so when an email is sent, the
sender's email server will query the
domain name system or the DNS to find
the mail server associated with the
recipient's domain. And so the DNS will
then translate that domain name like
exampample.com into the corresponding IP
address of the mail server using the MX
records. And so we mentioned that there
are a couple of email protocols. And the
email protocols are these sort of
behind-the-scenes rules and standards
that govern how emails are sent,
received, and also managed across the
internet. So these protocols are what
enables that seamless communication
between email clients like Outlook or
Gmail or Yahoo and ensure that messages
reach their intended recipients and
allow recipients to query the mail
server to retrieve those messages. So
the first one we have here is SMTP or
simple mail transfer protocol and this
is the foundation of email
communication. So, it's responsible for
sending outgoing emails from your mail
client to the recipient's mail server.
So, when you hit send on an email, well,
SMTP is the protocol that handles the
transmission of your message across the
internet. And so, it operates on port 25
by default, although encrypted versions
like SMTPS or SMTP secure and SMTP over
TLS operate on ports 465 and 587
respectively. But this is mostly for
context. You don't really need to
memorize these ports, although you
should probably know that SMTP itself is
port 25, which is pretty common. And so,
next here we have POP 3 or Post Office
Protocol version 3. And POP 3 is an
email retrieval protocol used by email
clients to download messages from the
mail server to your device. And it works
by connecting to the server and then
downloading emails to your device and
then deleting them off of the server.
And so POP 3 is ideal for users who
primarily access their emails from a
single device, which to be honest is not
that common anymore. And it operates on
port 110. But again, like SMTP, there
are encrypted versions of this protocol
like POP 3S or POP over SSL that uses
port 995. And lastly, here we have IMAP
or Internet Message Access Protocol. And
IMAP is another email retrieval
protocol, but it offers more advanced
features compared to POP 3. So with
IMAP, emails actually remain stored on
the mail server and your email client is
able to sync with the server to then
grab and display your messages. This
means that you can access your emails
from multiple devices and any actions
you take like deleting or moving emails
are then reflected and synced across all
those devices. And so chances are you're
more accustomed to using IMAP without
even knowing it. An IMAP operates on
port 143, but like with POP 3S, there is
a TLS encrypted version of IMAP called
IMAP secure or IMAP S, which uses port
993. Now, remember when we talked about
how the SMTP protocol works in that the
sender's mail server communicates with
the recipient's mail server to deliver
the message? Well, we use this nice
graphic that I painstakingly put
together. However, this is kind of a big
abstraction of what actually occurs as
the email traverses the internet.
So, more typically, it's going to look
something more like this. Well,
actually, this is also kind of an
exaggeration, but you can see that our
message is going to be making many more
stops along the way. This is because
most likely an email sent from Bob on
Gmail is going to need to travel through
different routing points or mail
transfer agents to reach Alice on Yahoo.
And so, what is a mail transfer agent?
Well, an MTA or a mail transfer agent,
you might also see this called a mail
transport agent, is a software
application or server that's responsible
for routing and transferring email
messages between different mail servers.
And so, when an email is sent, the MTA
on the sender's mail server accepts the
message, looks up the destination
domain, and then determines the
appropriate route to deliver the email
to the recipient's mail server. And so
when an email is sent from one domain to
another, it might have to traverse
through multiple MTAs over the internet
in a relay before reaching its final
destination. And something that we'll
cover later on in the header analysis
lesson, depending on the amount of MTAs
that an email has to traverse in transit
from source to destination, an email
will have multiple received headers
which should be read in ascending order
chronologically. And so next we have a
mail user agent or an MUA. And so an MUA
is the actual software application used
by users to compose and send and receive
and manage email messages. So common
MUAS include desktop applications like
Microsoft Outlook or web-based clients
like Gmail and mobile apps like Apple
Mail. And so MUAS provide a
user-friendly interface for actually
interacting with email and allowing
users to organize their messages or
create drafts and set up filters. And so
when a user sends an email, the MUA
communicates with the user's mail
transfer agent or MTA to transmit the
message to the recipient's mail server.
And so in essence, the MUA serves as the
primary interface between user and email
system. And we also have mail delivery
agents or MDAs. And this is a component
of an email system that's responsible
for accepting incoming email messages
from a mail transfer agent and
delivering them to the recipient's
mailbox. So we can think of it as the
last agent in the relay that holds the
email for the recipient to retrieve. And
so once an MTA has successfully relayed
an email to the recipient's mail server,
well, the MDA takes over and performs
actions like placing the email in the
recipient's inbox or applying filters or
sorting the message to specific folders.
Essentially, the MDA is responsible for
storing and organizing incoming email on
the recipient's mail server. And there
are actually two other functions in the
email exchanger or the MX standard. We
have the male submission agent or the
MSA and the mail retrieval agent or the
MRA, but they typically overlap with
MUAS and MDAS respectively and they're
not actually supported by the IETF
standard. And so we'll just focus on
these three above to understand the
whole
picture. Now, we're going to jump into
the practical lessons on analyzing
emails and we're going to do that
primarily within our Ubuntu VM. And so
there just a couple of utilities that we
need to install first in order to do so
effectively. And the first one is our
actual email client, right? We want to
have an actual email client on our
system so we can open up and interact
with email messages. And typically in
the enterprise, you'll come across
software like Microsoft Outlook or
Outlook on the web. In smaller or more
mediumsiz organizations, you might use
Google Workspace and so you might be
exclusively using Google Mail. However,
in our case, we're going to install
Mozilla Thunderbird, which is a free and
open- source email client that's going
to work perfectly for our
demonstrations. And to do that, it's
quite simple. So, I'm just going to open
up a terminal window
here. And from here, I'm just going to
type in pseudo apt install, and it's
just called
Thunderbird. And with that ready to go,
I'm going to hit enter. Type in my
password. And this should just take a
second to
install. And there we go. It's finished.
I'm just going to minimize my terminal
here. And we should be able to find
Thunderbird now in our list of
applications. And so to do that, click
on the Ubuntu logo here. In my case,
it's in the bottom
right. And you can see the newest app
here is Thunderbird Mail.
And so I'm just going to click on it to
open it
up. And when it starts up for the first
time, it's going to ask us here to set
up our existing email address. And so
here, you can just click on cancel to
sort of exit the setup here. We don't
actually need to set up or configure an
account in order to open up locally
saved email files, which is what we're
going to be doing in the following
lessons. And unfortunately, it's kind of
going to ask us the same thing every
time we open up Thunderbird, but it's
not really a big deal.
However, now that we've installed
Thunderbird, any ML or email files are
automatically associated with the
application. For example, I can just go
under the fishing analysis folder here
and just open up any email file. Right,
we can see we have a number of email
files here and we're kind of jumping
ahead, but that's okay. But we can just
double click on any of these
files and it's going to automatically
open up within Thunderbird, right? And
so you can see now we're looking at the
contents of this email.
And in case that doesn't work
automatically or it doesn't open up,
well, we can right click on an email
file and just click on open with. And
from here, you can make sure to select
the Thunderbird mail
app. Now, one last thing with
Thunderbird. So, let's just open it up
again and just click on
cancel. What we want to do here is just
click on the hamburger icon here in the
top right and go down to settings.
And from the settings page, go down to
the privacy and security
tab and make sure that allow remote
content in messages is
selected. And this is just going to
allow us to open up email messages with
any linked images without automatically
blocking them, which just saves us time
when we're trying to open up multiple
emails. And so we can just close that
out
now. All right. And so now we're going
to install Sublime Text, which is a
really powerful text editor for code and
different types of
markup. And when we do some manual email
file and header analysis, well, we want
to be using an actual code editor
instead of relying on just our terminal.
It just makes our lives so much
easier. And so to do this, I'm just
going to open up
Firefox. And I'm going to do a search
for Sublime Text.
And this first result here at
sublimeext.com just going to click on
it. And I'm going to click here on
install for
Linux. And I'm going to link this below
just in case the commands or the
specific process changes. But we really
just need to copy and paste a couple of
commands here to first install the GPG
key that's associated with the package
and then just install the package. And
so it's just really going to be a copy
and paste job here.
So, I'm going to copy this command, go
back into my
terminal, and just paste it
in. All right, the next command, we're
going to select a channel to use. And
so, instead of dev here, I'm going to
select stable. So, I'm just going to
copy this command
here, head back to my terminal, paste it
in, and then next, we just need to run
pseudoapp get update.
And again, if you see this message here,
we can just run pseudo
systemctl
damin-reload. And just make sure we
update once again, just in
case. All right. And the last command
here is just going to be pseudoapp get
install
sublime-ext. So I will just paste that
in. And we should have sublime text
installed.
And to confirm
this again, we can go down to the
applications menu and you can see we
have Sublime
Text.
Nice. And now we can basically open up
any file within Sublime Text. And so I'm
just going to navigate here to the
desktop folder under 01 fishing analysis
under 01 header analysis and just run an
ls to list out all of those email files.
And to open up any of these files within
Sublime Text, well, I can just run s for
Sublime and then provide the name of the
file. So, sample
1.ML. And so, now we're really jumping
ahead, but you can see how we can sort
of open up files within Sublime Text.
And that's what we're going to be doing
in the next
lesson. And so, let's end it here and
jump into the real lessons.
As a sock analyst, chances are that
you'll frequently encounter a number of
different types of fishing attacks, all
with varying objectives and means to
achieve their goals. But ultimately,
fishing relies on deception. And in
general, we can break down attack types
into several categories. Now, first we
have information gathering attacks. And
in an information gathering attack,
well, you might be wondering what the
entire point of the message was because
it's not really an attack. These types
of emails aren't trying to entice the
victim to click on a link or download a
file, but rather they're really just
checking to see if a destination mailbox
is in use and also if the user on the
other end of that mailbox is prone to
opening email messages. And if they can
manage to get a response from the
victim, they might also be able to
somewhat passively collect data, which
can often be done from an employes email
signature, which can include things like
their name, their job title, their phone
numbers, and other personal or
professional information. And this type
of reconnaissance can be used to stage
and craft a more convincing fish later
on, or to tailor a specific attack to a
specific individual or organization. So,
here's an example of one of these
information gathering attacks. In this
case, I don't see any URLs to click on.
I certainly don't see any attachments
attached to this email, and I don't see
any requests really for sensitive
information. It just seems to be a very
generic greeting and asking if I'm
available. And there are many different
ways that an attacker can gather
information from a seemingly innocent
email. For example, if they attempt to
send an email to a mailbox that doesn't
exist, well, they will typically get an
automated bounceback or an undeliverable
message in response from the email
server. And this can be used to
determine whether the mailbox is in use
or not. And we can actually take a look
at an example of one of these emails
here. You can see here that I attempted
to send an email to a non-existent email
account. And because it couldn't be
delivered, well, I got this email bounce
back in response.
Another way to do this is through the
use of a tracking pixel embedded within
the email's body content. And a tracking
pixel is a tiny transparent image that
gets embedded within the email content.
It's typically like a one by one pixel
image so that it's virtually invisible
to the recipient. And when the recipient
opens the email and their email client
loads the content of the email, it also
loads and requests that tracking pixel
from the sender server. And this action
allows the sender or the attacker in
this case to collect various information
such as the open rate. So the sender can
track when and how many times the email
was opened. And they can also log the IP
address of the recipient. And in some
cases, the sender can determine the
general location of the recipient. And
lastly, they can get device and client
information. So the sender can gather
data on the recipient's device type,
their operating system and email client,
and sometimes even specific operating or
OS settings.
Let's conduct a quick lab setup here to
showcase a tracking pixel in action and
also what data it can uncover. And now
you don't need to follow along with
this, so feel free to just watch. Now,
I've set up a couple of prerequisites
here. Now, first we have this tracking
pixel.png image that I created in
Microsoft Paint just by creating a 1x1
red pixel. Now, of course, in action,
you don't want this to be a red pixel,
but rather a transparent pixel so it
doesn't appear in the email client. And
next, I have this serve.py PIS script
that I put together which uses the
simple HTTP server in Python to set up a
quick and basic HTTP server that I can
use to log the requests. And in this
case, I've added a specific directive so
I can log the user agent. Now, this was
mostly just done to set up an easy
scenario here. In most cases, an
attacker is not going to use a Python
server, but most likely like an EngineX
or an Apache web server to log these
requests. And lastly, here I have this
sample email that we're going to use.
And if we take a look at the contents of
the email, well, we just have some basic
greeting and uh some generic email that
is quite harmless. And now if we preview
this email in our client, well, we're
just saying hello. And that's all there
is. Now, I'm going to start up our
listening server
here. And in a new tab, I'm going to
open up our sample email
again. And obviously, this would have
been done when the attacker was crafting
the initial email. But in this case, I'm
just going to append this image to the
end of our email. And you can see here
we have an image tag. And within the
source of the image tag, I'm adding a
URL to our tracking pixel. And of
course, in this case, it's just using
local host because I'm not hosting this
anywhere on the internet. It's just for
this lab demonstration. And so once I
save this, we're going to open up the
email again. And on the right hand side
here, we should see a request on our
Python server. So I'm just going to
double click the email again to open it
up. And you can see the email has
loaded. But if we minimize this screen,
you can see we actually track the
request here. And it might be really
hard to see, but if we start zooming in,
well, we can see this little red pixel
at the bottom of our screen. This is our
tracking pixel. And again, if we were
smart and used a transparent image,
well, we wouldn't see a red dot here. We
would see nothing at all. So, while this
email seemed completely harmless, well,
we actually track some interesting
information on our server. And so, we
can see the actual IP address of the
user that opened the email. And we can
see here, of course, it's just this
local host address because this is all
being done locally in a lab. But if this
was an actual organization's email
client that opened up, well, we would
see the IP address. If this was a user
opening the email at their home office,
well, we would see the IP address of
their home office. And of course, we
have the request timestamp. And this is
when the recipient opened the email and
the email client itself made the request
to gather this image. And so, if we
close this email and open it again, we
should get another request with another
timestamp. And there we go. There's our
second request. So, not only are we
getting the IP address of the opens, but
we're also getting when and how many
times it was opened. And lastly here, of
course, we are getting the user agent of
the actual email client. And we can see
some very interesting information here.
I'm just going to copy the entire user
agent string and I'm going to parse it
using a tool that we looked at before.
So in this case, I'm going to do a quick
Google search for a user agent parser.
You can see this what is my browser.com
parse a user agent string. Well, let's
go
here. And under here, I'm just going to
paste in the user agent string that we
captured. And if we parse this, well, we
almost didn't even need to because it's
so verbose on its own. But you can see
the client that opened our email was
Thunderbird. And we have the software
version. So we have
1510.1. We can also see the layout
engine and the version of the layout
engine. We can see the operating system.
So we buntu Linux. So we were able to
enumerate all of this information as an
attacker just by introducing a one by
one pixel within our email. So I hope
that was somewhat interesting and
hopefully demonstrated the
reconnaissance technique pretty well. So
we also have credential harvesting
attacks and these are actually a very
common type of fishing attack and likely
one that you most often associate with
fishing emails in general. So these are
fishing attacks designed to trick
individuals into divulging sensitive
data like their username and password.
So their credentials, right? Or even
their credit card numbers or other
personal data. And typically this is
done through a malicious web page or
what we would call a credential capture
website. And the fishing email itself
often contains some sort of call to
action, right? So maybe a button or a
URL to click on. And this link or this
URL usually directs the recipient to a
fake website that attempts to closely
resemble a legitimate one. And honestly,
in the field, the most common one you're
going to see is a Microsoft login page
because so many organizations use
Microsoft products and so many
organizations are moving to their cloud
services. But of course, this is just a
fake website and it's designed to
capture a victim's credentials and send
them over to a server that the attacker
controls. And maybe if the attacker is
really fancy, they'll then redirect the
user to the legitimate Microsoft website
or whatever it's trying to impersonate
as to make it appear more legitimate and
hide their tracks. For example, here is
one of those credential capture fishing
emails. We can see here in the subject
line that this email is supposedly
related to our Microsoft account and we
seem to have identified some sort of
unusual sign-in activity. And we can see
some information here saying that
apparently we've had a sign-in on our
Microsoft account well from Russia. And
if we think about some of these social
engineering tactics here, well, we might
have some urgency in this case because
apparently someone is in our account and
we need to look at the activity. And so
we have this call to action within the
email that says view activity. And if we
hover over this button, we can see the
URL that's going to take us to this
mc4-2.verell.app. Now immediately this
does not look like a Microsoft related
web page. But the typical person might
not notice this hyperlink, right? They
might just see this button and click on
it. And so let's do that. Let's see
where this link takes us. And so if we
click on the link, well, we're delivered
to this web page, which seemingly looks
like a genuine Microsoft login page. We
even have the Microsoft logo, the
signin, and honestly, even the
background here, this all looks to be a
legitimate Microsoft page. For example,
if we go to the real Microsoft page and
try to sign in here, well, we get a very
similar web page, right? If we go back
and forth uh and get the zooming
correct, if we go back and forth here,
well, it actually looks pretty similar.
and pretty convincing. And someone that
just got an email indicating someone's
in their account from Russia, well, they
might not notice the little details
here, like the font not being exact or
some spacing issues. And of course, if
we were to put in a fake username here
and click next, surely it's going to ask
us for a password. And if we type in a
fake password here, and before I hit
sign in here, what I'm going to do is
open up the developer tools under the
network tab because I want to see where
our credentials or our fake credentials
are going to get sent to. And of course,
this is not something we should include
in our methodology, but I just want to
demonstrate what an actual credential
capture web page looks like and how it
operates. So, let's just hit sign in
here, and we should be making a post
request. There we go. And of course,
we're getting this fake your account
password is incorrect. Surely, it's not
actually communicating with Microsoft
servers to determine if our credentials
were correct, right? But if we open up
this post request and expand this a
little bit, we can see we're making a
request to this mc4.onrender.com on
render.com specifically to this user/ad
endpoint. And if we look at the request,
well, we have our email and password
within the raw data that we sent over.
Now, of course, this is not an official
Microsoft website and likely the
attacker is using some sort of
legitimate service like on render to
actually submit data, right? And if we
were an actual victim falling for this,
well, the attacker just got our
credentials, right? They were sent over
to that
server. So, next we have malware
delivery. And in a malware delivery
fishing attack, also known as a
malicious attachment, uh, of course,
this is a type of fishing attack where
the attackers use some sort of email
that contains an attachment to
distribute malware infected files to
their victims. And honestly, often this
is done under the guise of like a fake
invoice sent by supposed customers or
third parties. And you know, depending
on the amount of effort and research
done by the attacker in the
reconnaissance phase, well, an attacker
might be able to actually spoof real
customers that a victim interacts with.
And these attachments are often things
like PDF documents or spreadsheets or
executable files. And it's either
infected with malware itself, or maybe
it contains malicious macros if it's an
office document, or maybe it's just a
benign and normal office document that
simply contains a URL inside it to
download a malicious file in something
what we would call a driveby download
attack. And a dry download is where
malware is automatically downloaded onto
a victim's computer without their
consent or knowledge, simply by visiting
a compromised website. And of course, as
we discussed during the fishing case
study section, well, these attachments
or files can often lead to devastating
ransomware attacks or deploy things like
remote access trojans that compromise a
victim's device or demand money or steal
sensitive information. And we're going
to cover analyzing fishing attachments
in more detail later on. So, let's look
at another example here. So, based on
the subject line, this appears to be a
due invoice payment. And based on the
contents of the email, well, it appears
they've attached some sort of invoice or
wire slip for us to take a look at. And
if we look at the attachment here in our
email client, we can see we have this
quotation file. And an ISO file is
typically an image of an optical disc,
like a CD or DVD drive. But it's
actually a common technique for
attackers to embed malware inside of ISO
files and distribute them through things
like fishing emails. And if we were on a
Windows endpoint, well, we might be able
to download this file from the email,
mount it to our system, and then execute
the malware. Now, we briefly covered
spear fishing before, but just to recap,
spear fishing is a targeted form of a
fishing attack in which attackers craft
personalized emails aimed at specific
individuals or groups within the
organization. And similarly, we have
whailing attacks. And whaling takes
spear fishing a step further and
specifically targets high-profile
individuals within an organization like
executives or senior managers or
individuals that would likely have
access to sensitive files or have more
permissions in general. And we also
covered things like fishing and smishing
and quishing. Now fishing of course is
short for voice fishing and is a type of
fishing attack that's conducted over the
phone. So in a fishing attack, well
attackers are going to use social
engineering techniques to manipulate
individuals into revealing sensitive
information like passwords and again
like credit card numbers or PII. They
typically do this by impersonating a
trusted entity like a bank or government
agency or even IT staff. Similarly, of
course, smishing is a combination of SMS
and fishing. And this is a type of
fishing attack conducted via text
messages or SMS. And in smissioning
attacks, attackers will send deceptive
text messages to individuals, typically
containing a link to a malicious website
or promoting the recipient to reply with
some sort of sensitive information. And
of course, lastly, we have quishing or
QR code fishing, which is a type of
fishing attack that exploits QR codes to
trick individuals into visiting
malicious websites or downloading
malicious content. And with fishing
attacks, well, attackers are going to
create QR codes that when a victim scans
them with their smartphone or some other
QR code enabled device, it will redirect
the user to a fishing website or a
credential capture page or even just
initiate the download of some sort of
malware. And quite honestly, this is so
easy for attackers to do. I just Google
generate QR code and I have all these
options to choose from. So, I'm just
going to click on this one here. And you
can see that we can generate QR codes
for all these different types of things.
For example, a URL or we can send an
email with predefined text or things
like displaying a PDF or images. So,
let's do a quick example here with a
URL. Suppose we've set up a malicious
website on example.com. Well, we could
just put in the address here and
suddenly we have this QR code that we
can then distribute. And sure enough, if
you open the camera app on your phone
and scan that QR code, well, you're
going to be redirected to
example.com. Now, of course, in this
case, it is not a malicious example, but
of course, we can put any URL here,
right? So, any attacker controlled URL
can quickly and easily be turned into a
QR
code. So, next we have business email
compromise. And this is also sometimes
known as CEO fraud or email account
compromise and is typically one of the
most financially damaging fishing
attacks. And in a business email
compromise attack, well, an attacker
might either spoof or actually gain
access to a trusted individual's email
account and use this credibility to
stage malicious requests. And these
requests can often come in the form of
things like unauthorized wire transfers
or invoice scams. And an example we
covered before is uh like a company CEO
asking an assistant to purchase gift
cards and then send the serial numbers
of those gift cards over to the
attacker. And we even covered the 2015
Ubiquity Networks attack which of course
led to the loss of 46 million which was
in fact a business email compromised
fish. And lastly here, well not all
suspicious or unwanted emails are actual
fishing attempts. And you know, spam
emails, they might not be blatantly
malicious in nature, but they are
typically unsolicited bulk emails that
are sent to a large number of people,
typically for commercial purposes like
advertising or uh promoting fraudulent
or sketchy schemes or dating websites or
things trying to sell like random junk,
right? And of course, spam emails can be
pervasive and persistent, and they can
be a nuisance for employees. And again,
while they're not typically malicious,
they can still carry risks and
implications. For example, it's possible
that an email that just appears to be an
annoying spam email is actually an
information gathering email used to
perform reconnaissance on a future
fishing
target. So, in general, these are the
common types of fishing attacks you'll
see in the wild. And in the next video,
we'll look at how to actually identify
fishing attack techniques, and we'll
cover things like what attackers
actually do to go about their
objectives.
So, we covered the different types of
fishing attacks that you might come
across in the field, but what specific
techniques do attackers employ during
their fishing campaigns to obiscate
their methods and deceive their victims?
Well, let's take a look at a couple
examples here. And although the list of
techniques and possibilities remains to
grow in the field, we'll take a look at
the most common ones that you might come
across. So, first we have pretexting.
And pretexting is a social engineering
attack used by attackers to manipulate
individuals under false pretenses. So in
pretexting scenarios, an attacker will
create some sort of fabricated story or
scenario to gain the trust and
cooperation of their targets. And
they'll often do this by exploiting
human emotions like curiosity or in
general the human willingness to want to
help others. And many of the methods
that we covered previously can all play
a role in establishing a credible
pretext. So things like spoofing or
impersonation or establishing
credibility through using trusted logos
or messaging within a fishing email. So
maybe it's an email impersonating the HR
department asking employees to provide
their bank account information so that
they can then update their records to
ensure they get paid on time. And
similarly we have spoofing and
impersonation. So as we just mentioned
spoofing and impersonation are common
techniques used by attackers to deceive
recipients and increase the credibility
of their emails. And like I said
earlier, because almost all of the email
headers can be completely modified and
spoofed on the attacker's end before
it's sent, we typically tend to see a
couple different variations of spoofing.
So we have email address spoofing. And
this is where the attacker will spoof
the sender's email address to make it
appear as though the email is coming
from a legitimate source. And we also
have domain spoofing. So in addition to
spoofing an individual's email address,
attackers might spoof an entire domain
to make their fishing emails appear as
though they originate from a reputable
source. So they might actually register
domain names with similar names to
legitimate companies and they'll try to
use this brand recognition to trick
people into believing the email. But
attackers can take this one step further
with URL manipulation. And there are
actually a number of URL manipulation
techniques that you should be aware of
when you're analyzing suspicious emails
because they're very easy for attackers
to take advantage of and sometimes it's
almost impossible to recognize without
careful inspection. So the first one
here we have is URL shortening. So
attackers can leverage URL shortening
services in emails to obscure their
malicious links or get around email
security features. And honestly, this is
surprisingly easy to do. And while there
are some security solutions out there
that will of course detonize and analyze
the true destination of these shortened
links, well, this isn't always the
case. For example, let's showcase one of
the most popular services for shortening
URLs, Bitly. But of course, there are
many others out there like Tiny URL or
short.io and many more if you just
Google. And bit.ly is a service that
allows us to do things like shortening
URLs or generating QR codes which we
showcased in the previous video. So if
we click get started for free, well, we
can sign up for a free account here. And
once we're signed in, we're taken to
this dashboard where we can do a number
of different things. So let's get
started and create a short link. So
let's say we wanted to create a
shortened link for TCM Security's
website. Well, I'll just paste in the
destination there. We can give it a
title and we can actually create what is
called a custom back half and this is
going to be what is shown in the URL
itself rather than a you know
automatically generated
string. So we can actually set this to
whatever we
want. And for example if I was trying to
impersonate a specific bank well I might
call this banking services or something
similar right as an attacker. But let's
just leave it with totally amazing
website and scroll down to create here.
You can see we have created the link at
bit.ly/totallyamazam amazing website.
And if you were to type this into your
browser, well, you're going to be
redirected to the TCM Securities
website. And so you can see if we were
to edit this URL to something malicious,
well, we can just give people this link
and they would be in the dark as to
where this link actually takes them. But
there are some services that we can use
to expand this link, right? So if we go
to unshorten.it
it. Well, we can paste in our bit.ly
link here and we click on unshorten
it and you can see it actually detonates
that link for us and follows all of the
redirects. So, in this case, we can see
where it's actually
going. So, next we have subdomain
spoofing. And subdomain spoofing is a
technique used by attackers to deceive
users by creating a fraudulent subdomain
that mimics a legitimate one. And this
method capitalizes on the trust that
users have in well-known domains or
subdomains. And this is actually a very
common tactic. So suppose a malicious
email that is sent from a real mailbox
of google.mmalicious site.com or within
a URL in an email that leads to
something like
facebook.loginsystems.co.uk. In this
case, these are legitimate domains. The
headers don't even need to be spoofed.
These are simply just malicious
subdomains registered under a
non-affiliated base domain. So the
companies that are being impersonated
like Google and Facebook have no
affiliation with this base domain, but
the attacker makes it look as though
they do. So someone not paying attention
might immediately assume the URL is safe
because it begins with Facebook or
contains Google in the URL. And these
are organizations that they would
typically trust. So next, let's talk
about a really interesting attack,
homographs. Now, technically speaking,
in grammar, a homograph is a word that
shares the same written form or spelling
as another word, but has a different
meaning. For example, bas in the fish,
or bass, the instrument. A similar
technique is sometimes done with domain
names to impersonate an actual
legitimate domain with a malicious copy.
So, in the context of fishing attacks,
attackers can use characters from
different character sets like cerillic
or Greek or Latin that resemble
legitimate characters in a URL. This
makes a URL visually similar to the
legitimate one but leads to a different
website. And so this specific method is
sometimes referred to as an
internationalized domain name or an IDN
homograph attack. And so can you tell
the difference between these two
domains? In this case with this font and
rendering you actually can't. But
there's a slight difference. In the
second domain, the C character has
actually been replaced with the cerillic
lowercase C, which looks identical to
the Latin lowercase C, but is a distinct
character in Unicode. So, visually, both
these domains appear the same, but they
are technically different due to the
character used. And so, how do attackers
actually come up with these domain
names? Well, they might use something
like this homoglyph attack
generator. So, first we would type in
the name of the legitimate domain that
we're trying to mimic. And you can see
here as we were doing that, it generated
all these different options for us. So
for example, we can replace the C with
all these different options or maybe the
M or the
S. And if we scroll down, we can see our
generated domain here. So obviously we
chose a capital M here, which is not
very smart. We can see some of the other
characters are pretty
close. On the topic of homograph
attacks, we have the general technique
of typo squatting. And typo squatting,
which is also known as URL hijacking or
domain squatting, is a technique that
exploits common typographical errors
made by users when looking at domains or
URLs. And so by registering domain names
that closely resemble popular or
well-known websites, well, an attacker
can trick a victim into thinking that an
email was sent by a legitimate sender or
a URL in an email is legitimate as well.
For example, instead of linked.com, an
attacker could purchase and register
linked.com with the simple omission of
the second I character. And you know a
user who is not paying close attention
might not notice this in an email. And
there are actually different types of
typos squatting techniques and we can
use a service like DNS twist to identify
potential typos squatting vectors for
our or any domain. So this is actually a
Python tool in which I'll have linked
down below but we can run it to find
lookalike domains that adversaries can
use to attack us. Alternatively, this is
actually something hosted on the web as
well. So we don't actually need to
download this and run it locally. So in
this case we can just put in a
URL and it will scan it for us and it
will start generating all these
different types of typo squatting
vectors. And we can see here the ones
with IP addresses and name servers have
actually been registered already. We
have different types here, right? We
have additions. So in this case we have
linked N with two N's. And if we scroll
down we can actually start to see some
homoglyph or homograph attacks. And this
one is omitting the I character in favor
for something that looks somewhat
similar. And you can see just how many
of these have been registered and
probably used for fishing campaigns in
the past. But many organizations will
proactively purchase some common typos
squat domains to prevent malicious uses.
For example, facebook.com with only one
O redirects to the legitimate
facebook.com. Goggle.com without the
second O redirects to google.com. And
actually, one of my first projects as a
junior security analyst years and years
ago was to build a tool very similar to
that DNS twist tool. And it was so that
our sock could proactively get alerted
on potential typos squatting domains if
they were to be registered and to also
provide a report on domains that we
could proactively purchase to mitigate
these attacks. And so next here we have
encoding. And encoding is a technique
that can sometimes be used by attackers
to obiscate malicious content or evade
automated detection. And sometimes this
is done on the email body content
itself, right? It could be using
something like B 64 or URL encoding or
HTML encoding to slightly obiscate the
contents of an email message until it
gets rendered in the email client. Just
as a very simple example, let's open
this encoded attachment here. And you
can see we have a very simple email here
with a hyperlink to proceed to wallet
verification, which of course this leads
to a credential capture page. And
although it looks very simple when it's
rendered, let's take a look at its
source to see what components make up
the
email. And if we scroll down past the
normal headers, well, we're going to see
a very long string of seemingly random
data at the bottom of this email. And we
don't actually see what we saw in our
email client, right? We don't see this
hyperlink with the proceed to wallet
verification. Instead, we just see this
long string of text, which as we can
infer from the content transfer encoding
header here, it is a string of B 64
text. So, let's copy this long string.
So, I'm just going to open a terminal
window here, and I'm going to echo out
that long B 64 string that we copied.
And of course, echoing it out like this
is not going to do anything interesting.
But what I can do is echo this out and
pipe it to the base 64 command. And then
I'm going to provide the tac d argument
to
decode. And you can see here it actually
managed to decode that URL that we saw
in the email when it was rendered. And
so that was just a very simple example
of B 64 encoding. But we're going to
cover encoding in more detail later on
in the course. As we discussed
previously, and we'll do so in more
detail shortly, a common technique in
fishing emails is to include a malicious
attachment or even a benign attachment
that eventually leads to a victim
downloading a malicious payload and
being
compromised. We also have abuse of
legitimate services. So, interestingly,
an attacker doesn't always have to rely
on their own means to deliver and host
malware and weaponize content shared
within their emails. Attackers
frequently exploit legitimate file
sharing and collaboration services such
as Google Drive or Dropbox and many
others to facilitate their fishing
campaigns and distribute malicious
content to users. And so by leveraging
the trusted reputation of these
platforms, attackers can evade
traditional email filters and security
controls, making it easier to get to
their victim's
inbox. And so an attacker would upload
their fishing content like their
malicious document or an executable to a
file sharing platform like Google Drive
or Dropbox. They might even password
protect it and zip the file so that it
can't be sort of detonated by any
automated means. They'll then distribute
the links or the public sharing links to
these hosted files within their fishing
emails and include some sort of call to
action for users to click on the links
and access the malicious content. And
because the URL is legitimately coming
from Google or Dropbox and the former
almost always being trusted within
environments, maybe not so much for
Dropbox, but definitely Google, these
URLs will often go undetected and
there's nothing preventing users from
downloading these files until their
endpoint security hopefully kicks
in. So to hopefully demonstrate the use
of a legitimate service, well, I'm using
a site called Fish Tank. And you can
think of this as a big repository of
potentially malicious URLs that people
can submit from all over the world.
We're going to cover this in more detail
in the URL analysis lesson, but for now,
I just looked at some of the most recent
submissions, and I can already see a
docs.google address right here,
indicating that someone is trying to
abuse Google Docs to fish someone. And
so, I'm just going to click on this
submission right here, and I'm going to
copy the URL to see if we can find out
what's being hosted. And so, again, this
is something you should not do, but
considering I'm in a VM, and I'm just
doing this for research purposes, I'm
going to see what is actually being
hosted here.
Okay, so very interesting. It appears to
be hosting some sort of image. And this
is of course an Amazon account lockout
image. This is not actual HTML. This
again just appears to be an image of
some sort. But it also has a hyperlink.
And if we just copy this link, well,
I'll just showcase it in a terminal
window. I'm going to paste it here. And
we can see some very interesting things
here. So it looks like it's using an
actual google.com base URL here, but
it's passing in an additional uh shorten
URL using bit.ly within this query
parameter. And so we could go ahead and
try to unshorten this like we've done
before and see what is actually on
there. But I think this sort of
demonstrates the point. And in this
case, we have a fishing attempt with a
malicious URL hosted on the
docs.google.com domain, which is most
likely not something that's going to get
flagged within many organizations
because of course this is actually
belonging to Google. And we can see the
certificate here is actually signed by
Google Trust
Services. And lastly here we have
farming. And farming is typically a
two-step technique. The first being more
so what we've covered before where an
attacker will redirect a user to a
fraudulent website that closely
resembles a legitimate one. And so as
such, this technique is often used to
perform credential harvesting attacks.
But it's a two-step process because
unlike other methods of spoofing or
impersonating, which we've talked about,
farming actually requires configurations
or malicious code to run on a victim's
computer or within their DNS server to
redirect the actual traffic to the
attackers's controlled website. And so
we have malwarebased farming which
occurs when a user unknowingly downloads
malware like a Trojan or a virus. And
this malware can then get in front of a
user's web traffic and redirect them
accordingly. On the other hand, DNS
server poisoning involves manipulating
the actual DNS servers or a user's local
host file or caches to then redirect the
user to a fake IP address instead of
legitimate
websites. In the immediate lessons
following this one, we're going to cover
a number of techniques and tools that we
can use to extract artifacts and analyze
emails. However, the key as I've
mentioned to effective email analysis
lies in establishing a structured
methodology that we can consistently
apply across various situations
irrespective of what tools we have
available to us. Right? So, your
methodology doesn't have to be exactly
as follows, but definitely consider
several of these essential steps as a
good starting point. So, first we're
going to need to do some initial triage.
And so upon receiving a suspected
fishing email, well, the initial step is
to conduct triage to quickly assess its
potential threat level. So this involves
identifying key attributes like the
sender details or the subject line or
other urgency indicators that we can
identify. And so triage helps us in
determining the appropriate level of
response and the appropriate timing of a
response and allocation of resources to
do our further analysis. So to put it
simply, in the triage stage, we need to
quickly assess and prioritize potential
impact, which will allow us to focus on
what's most pressing. For example, maybe
we have an email that initially looks
like spam that was sent to one employee
versus a reported email containing an
attachment that was sent to a number of
executives. And so next, as we alluded
to earlier, the header of an email
contains valuable metadata that we can
use to quickly analyze and assess its
true origin. So, an examination of an
email header will involve things like
looking at the routing path an email
took through the internet or the sender
IP address or the domain authenticity
and maybe if we can identify anomalies
or signs of spoofing. And so, when we do
sender examination, well, that's going
to include things like verifying the
sender's identity. For example, you
know, is this really a Microsoft owned
domain? Well, if we do a reverse DNS
lookup, what is the email server that
returns? Is it Microsoft owned? Did this
email pass an SPF and DKIM check? Well,
these are all things that we're going to
cover in the next lesson. And so, next,
we want to do some content examination.
And this involves analyzing the body of
the email for any suspicious elements
like grammatical errors or generic
greetings or unusual or awkward
language. And sometimes we can catch
some immediate red flags, even as far
back as in the initial triage stage. And
these red flags might really give an
email away as being fishing. However, we
can't always assume, which is why we
have to have this methodology. And we
can also look for any common social
engineering techniques that we looked at
earlier. So things like urgency or trust
or authority or scarcity. Fishing emails
will often contain course of language
and requests for sensitive information
or call to actions. Next, we'll want to
look at the web and URL artifacts,
right? So URLs embedded within fishing
emails need to be analyzed to determine
their legitimacy and their destination.
If we're faced with an oddlooking or
maybe worse a shortened URL, well, we
can employ various techniques such as
URL parsing or URL detonation and
scanning and domain reputation checks to
assess the risk associated with
accessing the link content. And like
with any URL artifacts that we find,
well, any email attachments also need to
be investigated. And so, we'll employ
malware analysis techniques like
sandboxing and file signature analysis
and behavioral analysis. These can all
be done through manual and automated
scanning means. But most commonly at
least the file hashes need to be safely
extracted as artifacts and reviewed
through a malware database to determine
if it's a known malware sample. And in
addition to the hands-on analysis we
perform, well, we should also include
some holistic analysis and consider the
broader organizational context as well
as recent security incidents to gauge
the credibility of a fishing email. So
we can look at patterns within our
organization or look in our ticket
system for recent or similar fishing
emails. You know, maybe we assess the
scope and look at the IoC's or artifacts
that we've identified and perform almost
a mini threat hunt over the
organization's email system to see if
there are similar attempts going on. And
maybe we can identify recurring themes
like a sender's address or tactics used
by threat actors that will allow us to
more efficiently and proactively
integrate defense measures. And speaking
of defense measures, well, upon
identification and verdict of any
fishing attempt, well, we need to take
either reactive or proactive defense
measures or both, depending on if the
attempt was successful or not. So,
reactive defense measures are going to
include things like invoking incident
response procedures for containment and
mitigation and remediation in the event
of a successful fishing attack. For
example, if a user was successfully
fished and they provided their
credentials, well, we need to initiate
instant response procedures to
temporarily disable their account or
review their login history and change
their credentials or rotate any keys and
even perform a full system scan or
reformatting depending on a deeper
investigation. And on the other hand,
proactive defense measures will involve
things like implementing technical
controls like email filtering or DNS
blacklisting and endpoint protection
based on the IoC's and artifacts that
we've identified. And we should also be
educating users about fishing awareness
and provide guidelines on how to
identify suspicious emails and how users
can report incidents quickly to the
sock. And lastly here, this brings us to
documentation and reporting, which in
reality should be a step that is
followed through each stage of the
methodology, not just something that we
shoehorn at the end. So while we
investigate emails and collect artifacts
and analyze our senders and even look at
URLs and attachments, well, we need to
keep detailed notes and update our
tickets accordingly and accurately. And
if we take any defensive actions, well,
we need to document these as well. Like
if 6 months down the road a stakeholder
is asking why the sock block a certain
domain or an email, well, we need to be
able to go back and justify our actions.
Our documentation needs to be clear and
thorough. So much so that any other
analyst can come by after us and make
the same determinations and verdicts
based on our findings. So, as our
investigation progresses, we should be
continually updating the status inside
our ticket management system. and we
need to make sure to close out the
tickets and communicate to users on the
reported emails verdict as
needed. Let's start analyzing some real
emails and learn how we can use header
analysis to identify the sender of an
email as well as their legitimacy. If
you recall, email headers are just
simply text files with multiple lines
indicating a header name and a header
value. Because of this, we can
essentially use any text editor or even
command line tools to view the header
information of an email as long as we
have a copy of the email saved. In some
cases, depending on the email client, we
can actually view these headers directly
in the program itself. For example, in
Thunderbird, we can just go under the
view tab here and click on message
source. In Gmail, for instance, we can
just hover over an email under the more
icon and either go down to download
message to download AEML file of the
email or we can go up to show original.
And if we click on show original, this
is going to give us a full output of the
email headers, which we can then
download or copy to our
clipboard. on an Outlookbased system,
specifically Outlook on the web, we can
do something very similar where we head
over to these three dots for more
actions. Click on it and we can then go
to save as if we want to download the
email or alternatively we can go to view
and click on view message source. And by
clicking on this again, we will get an
output of the email headers which we can
then
copy. And you can easily look up these
steps to view email headers depending on
the clients and the tooling that your
organization uses. Additionally, if
you're using some sort of ticketing
system like Jira or Service Now to
handle fishing reports and you have some
sort of workflow in place that allows
users within the organization to report
suspicious emails, what typically
happens is that the email will
automatically forward itself as an
attachment to a fishing analysis
mailbox. And there might be some further
automation in place that will
subsequently create individual tickets
or alerts within the ticketing system to
create cases for analysts to then triage
within these tickets themselves. The
extracted email and typically within a
ML file format will be available to view
and download. And this file contains all
of the original headers that we're
interested in. And note that if a user
forwards an email the typical way
through pressing the forward button in
their email client, in most cases, the
original headers will be lost, which
makes the analysis portion much more
difficult. This is why it's important to
forward the email itself as an
attachment, which is typically an option
in email clients if it's not already
being done through some sort of
automatic workflow. So, now that we have
some copies of emails we want to
investigate, we can use a number of
different tools or methods to view its
contents. So, first for this lesson,
navigate to the fishing analysis folder
on the desktop and then open the header
analysis folder. And from here, let's
start with sample 1. ML. So, we just
double click on this to open it up in
Thunderbird. And you might see this
connection failed. You can just ignore
that message, but eventually the email
will open up as seen above. So, this is
the first email that we're going to be
analyzing. And so, we can see what it
looks like initially. We can see this
Chase Bank logo. It appears to be asking
us to restore or reactivate our account.
And we can see some of the common
headers. So we have the from field here
which is
alerts@chase.com. We have the two field
which is bob sanders. The subject line
so your bank account has been blocked as
well as the timestamp over here on the
right which we've looked at earlier. So
these are some of the common headers
that we've seen before. But I mentioned
it's essentially just a text document
that makes up email messages. So if we
go back to our folder, I'm just going to
rightclick and click open in terminal.
This is going to open a terminal session
in the folder that we were looking at.
And from here, I'm just going to run an
ls to list out the contents. And we can
see the sample emails that we have in
this folder. I'm simply going to cat out
the sample one email file. And just as
you can see when we were exporting the
source of the email itself, we're
getting the same information here. So
this is the HTML markup that is making
up the email body. And if we scroll up,
all we can actually get to the actual
headers.
So much so that we don't need to just
cat out the file. If we wanted to find
something like the from header, well, we
could just run a GP command like this.
And we can see immediately we get the
from header returned with alerts at
chase.com. But again, working with it in
a command line like this isn't ideal. So
what we can also do is open it in a text
editor like Sublime Text. So to do that,
I already have Sublime Text installed in
this lab. So all we need to do is just
run the suvl syntax here to open up
Sublime Text and provide the file that
we want to open. Sample
1.ML. You can see here we have the email
message opened up in Sublime Text. But
when we open up an email in Sublime
Text, by default, we don't get the
benefit of syntax highlighting that
makes our lives easier. But fortunately,
Richard Davis, the founder behind 13
cubed, developed a super useful package
that we can install in Sublime Text to
assist with this. And I will have the
link down below. But essentially, this
is a syntax highlighter plugin that we
can use specifically for email messages.
So, all we need to do is go up into the
toolbar here under tools and click on
install package
control. We'll get this message that it
was successfully installed. And then we
want to press control shift and p to
open the command
pallet. We just want to type in install
package. And then we're going to click
on this option here. And then we can
just start typing in email. We can see
the first option here is the email
header syntax highlighting plugin
developed by 13 cubed. And this is the
one that we want to install. So I'm just
going to click on this. And now once we
go to our syntax here in the bottom
right, well, it's currently set to plain
text. If we click on this and we start
scrolling up, well, we can see this new
email header option here. So, if we
click on this, we can suddenly see our
file becomes much more readable. So, we
have some color and highlighting here
that is separating out the header name
versus its value. And we have an
additional color here to separate
extended or custom headers, which we're
going to talk about in a bit. And next,
I quickly wanted to look at the ANA or
the internet assigned numbers authority
page, specifically the standard that
outlines message headers. And so this
link contains all of the various
standardized message headers, including
their names and descriptions and any
associated protocols. And you'll see
that there are tons and tons of headers
here. Some of which are more common and
some not so much because I don't want
this lesson to be a week long, but we're
going to focus on the most common and
most useful and important headers that
you're going to want to know about. So
let's get back to the email and take a
look at some of these common headers. So
the first one here is the date.
The date header in an email specifies
the date and time when the message was
composed or sent. We'll often want to
document the date and time of an email
for our records. Whether it be this
timestamp directly from the header or
from the email client or from the ticket
that was created. Knowing when an email
was delivered can be very useful in
performing email searches across the
organization for similar emails or for
correlating other suspicious activity
that might have resulted in a fish like
in our SIM for instance. Right above
this we have the from header. The from
header, as we're likely familiar with,
specifies the supposed sender of an
email. This is the header that will be
displayed in email clients to show who
sent a specific email. However, because
the from header can be set to any
arbitrary value, well, this is one of
the most common headers that attackers
can spoof to make it look like a fishing
email came from someone else or a
trusted organization. But we should
still document this though because we
can use it to find discrepancies as well
as use it as an artifact to search off
of. So, next we have the subject
line. And again, we're used to seeing
the email subject, which is of course
the subject that appears in your email
client when you receive an email in your
inbox. Again, this is a useful header to
document because we can almost think of
it as a signature or a fingerprint of an
email should we determine it to be
malicious. For example, we can use a
subject line to perform searches against
our email gateway and look for other
associated emails or in rare cases
actually block specific email subject
lines from entering our organization.
And along the lines of fingerprinting an
email through artifacts, well, we have
the message ID field as you can see
here. And the message ID header is a
very useful one for us because it is a
unique ID generated by the first MTA
that the message traverses through. And
these message IDs should always be
unique by the server that generates it
and pertains to a single version of that
email. That means if we ever find a
duplicate message ID in our email
gateway, well, it could very likely be
an indication of something malicious
going on. And these IDs are made up of
two parts. And so anything before the at
sign here or this left side of the ID,
the standard documents that it should be
a unique identifier, although there are
no specific algorithm requirements in
the standard. And on the right hand of
the message ID, but we expect to see the
domain name or the IP address of the
host in which the message identifier was
created. That means in theory if we
identify a specific mail system domain
that the email originated from but the
message ID contains a different domain
name well again this could be a hint
that the email was forged. We also want
to document the recipient email address
during our triage stage because this is
where we can determine scope and we can
do this through the two header. If we
have multiple users that received the
same suspicious email, well we need to
be aware in case we need to take action
across anyone else that received it. And
you might not always be able to see
multiple emails listed under the
recipients. It's quite trivial for an
attacker to utilize blind carbon copy or
BCC to include multiple recipients and
prevent each of those recipients from
knowing who else received the email. In
this case, this is where our timestamps
and subject line and from headers become
useful to have documented so we can
perform our own search at the email
gateway level. And next here we have the
reply to address. The reply to address
in an email message specifies the email
address to which replies should be
directed to when a recipient responds to
it. And it's different from the from
address which indicates the sender of
the email. And of course, there are
legitimate uses for a reply to address.
But many times if an attacker is
spoofing a legitimate domain, well, they
have to specify a different reply to
address because they don't actually have
access or have control over the
legitimate domain that they're spoofing.
For example, if an attacker has spoofed
accounts@ microsoft.com in the from
header, well, any replies to this email
would not actually be received by the
attacker since they don't have control
over the actual accounts@ microsoft.com
mailbox. Instead, an attacker would
commonly insert the address of a mailbox
that they own under the reply to field,
such as
attacker123@malware.com to ensure that
they capture any replies. And we also
have the return path here. And this
header is also known as the envelope
sender address or the bounce address.
And it specifies the email address to
which bounce messages or delivery
failure notifications should be sent.
Similar to the reply to header, we can
check if this header matches what we saw
in the from header. And again, sometimes
there are legitimate purposes for why
this doesn't match. But if an attacker
is using a service to mass fish a number
of potential victims and doesn't care
about reconnaissance, they might want to
direct the bounceback somewhere else.
And so you'll notice with our syntax
highlighting, we can see these
standardized headers in one color and
these X-Type headers in another color.
And these X-Type headers are also known
as experimental or extension headers.
And often you'll see them referred to as
custom headers as well. And these are
additional headers that don't fit within
the standards adopted from the AA, but
they are sometimes used by mail
providers or security solutions to add
additional functionality to email
clients and filters and do things like
spam checks or tracking or
authentication results and other
additional metadata. And we have some
that are particularly useful for us, but
not always present. For example, here we
have the X sender IP. Now, this is one
of the most commonly seen X headers out
there and is actually pretty useful for
us as an investigator if it's present,
but of course, it's not always present.
You might also see a header called XO
originating IP and it essentially serves
the same purpose. And again, you might
see this or not or one or the other. It
entirely depends on the email
infrastructure. And the Xorinating IP or
the X sender IP header typically
indicates the IP address of the device
or server from which the email
originated from. and it's added to the
email headers by the sender's email
client or the message submission agent.
And the catch here is that certain
providers will not include this header.
For example, Google does not include the
header while Microsoft typically does.
And once we obtain the originating IP
address, we can perform certain
investigative actions like geoloccating
it to determine where the server is
geographically and what autonomous
system organization or ASN does it
belong to. We can also check the IP's
reputation or perform a reverse DNS
lookup to identify what domain or host
name the mail server resolves to. And
now if we don't have access to this
header, there are still ways in which we
can retrieve the originating IP address.
The most useful and reliable way is
through the received headers. And we
have to scroll to the top to see these
received
headers. Now, I wanted to cover some of
the more basic headers to get a feel for
what makes up an email. But there is one
type of header that in our
investigations is going to arguably be
the most important header that you're
going to come across. And that is of
course the received header. And now the
main thing you'll notice here is that
there are multiple received headers. And
this is normal and you'll typically see
more than one. If you remember when we
talked about how the email protocol
works, we mentioned that emails
typically go through a relay of mail
servers or MTAs as they are routed from
sender to recipient. The number of
received headers you see are going to
vary depending on how many MTAs the
message had to traverse within its
journey. And so each email server that
handles the message adds its own
received header, creating a
chronological record known as the
received chain. These headers typically
can't be spoofed as they're added by the
MTAs themselves. So they're often a
reliable metric that we can use to
perform our investigations. And you can
almost think of it like a passport. As
you travel across the world, well,
you'll likely stop in various countries
along the way. And at each stage in the
process, well, you'll receive a check or
a stamp as you pass through various
checkpoints or layovers. An important
point here is that the received headers
are in reverse chronological order,
meaning that the first header we see is
the most recent or closest to the
recipient. And at the bottom, the last
received header we find in the email is
the one closest to the sender or the
originating server.
Which means that if we want to figure
out where an email actually came from,
well, we should start from the bottom
and move upwards. Depending on the route
the email path took to get to our
trusted infrastructure, we might need to
look at a few of the earliest received
headers. And as such, it's technically
possible that the original sender of the
email might have included spoofed
headers to try and hide that they are
the original sender of the message
instead of just a waypoint along the
way. As such, the only received headers
that we should trust are the ones
generated by our own trusted internal
infrastructure or basically when the
email is passed along to the MTAs that
we trust. And so another way to put this
is that the most important hops in an
email's path across the internet is the
first time that our trusted
infrastructure, you could think of this
as Microsoft or our own organization's
MTA, interacts with the server that is
sending the email. And we could go as
far as to say that anything under this
trusted received header cannot be
trusted as the attacker could have
modified or spoofed anything below this.
In this case, we can see this first
received header here which was
supposedly sent by a proton mail
address. But we can see it was received
by the Outlook domain with the Microsoft
SMTP
server. And so we can be relatively sure
that this was the original sender and
this was the original sender's IP
address. And if you recall, this is the
same IP address that we saw in the X
sender IP header. So now that we've
identified some IP addresses that could
be useful to us, we can perform some
further investigation to obtain more
data about the original sender. So to do
this, we can use any free IP or domain
lookup service out there or even the who
is command in our terminal. And if you
don't have who is installed, well, we
can run pseudo app to install who is.
Just need to put in your password there.
And once it's installed, we can just run
a who is and paste in that IP address.
And if we scroll up, we can start to see
some very useful
information. Similarly, we can go to a
site like who
is.domaintools.com. And again, if we
paste in that IP address and click on
search, we're going to get the same
results in the browser. So here we can
see that the country that this IP
address belongs to is in Switzerland.
And the reverse DNS lookup or the
resolved host points to
mail-4140.protonmail.ch. And we can also
see the ASN or the autonomous system
number belongs to
Protonag, which confirms that we're
dealing with a Proton Mail email system
that originally sent this email. And
this obviously does not match up with
Chase Bank, which is what the sender
wanted us to believe by spoofing the
sender address as chase.com.
And of course, we want to ensure that
the results of this check are well
documented because they will come in
handy during our analysis. And so doing
this extra bit of reverse DNS research,
we're able to attribute the original
sending email server and confirm that
this email did not in fact originate
from anything related to Chase Bank.
It's also worth noting that while we
have some clever solutions to view these
headers, like with Sublime Text, we also
have some free tools available to us
that can parse email headers in an
easyto- read format.
One of which is the message header
analyzer tool which I'll have linked
down below. And using this tool, we can
paste in the headers from any email and
get a nice and easy to read table that
highlights some of the important headers
for our analysis. And it's worth noting
that all of the processing occurs client
side. So we don't need to worry about
any sensitive data from legitimate
emails being collected. And this is an
open source tool and the repository can
be found here or linked down below. So
we can just copy everything from our
email and paste it into this header
field here. And when we click analyze
headers, well, we can immediately see
that it gets parsed into this easier to
read format. And so we can see the
received headers here in this sort of
table format indicating each hop along
the way. We can also see the X sender IP
highlighted here with our IP address. A
second tool that we have access to is MX
Toolbox, which is a super useful utility
that can do a wide variety of things
like reverse DNS lookups or message
authentication checks and many more
things. One of its options is the email
header analyzer, which can be found in
the link below. Like with the previous
tool we just looked at, we can paste in
an email's header here or source and
click analyze header. And of course,
this will parse them to present the
headers in an easy to understand format.
So we can see we have the received
header relay here again with that IP
address
identified along with some email
authentication checks which we'll get
into
shortly. Often times attackers won't
even go as far as to bother with
spoofing addresses. In these cases, it
can be very quick to identify that it's
an email with malicious intent and can
expedite our investigation. For example,
let's quickly look at sample
2.ml. And this is a real fishing email
that I received in a honeypot
mailbox. And in this example, we can
clearly see that the sender is
attempting to impersonate CIBC, which is
a large Canadian bank. However, we just
need to look at the from header to
realize that this address is just a poor
attempt at impersonating CIBC using some
subdomains in the email address itself,
like CIBC-banking.
to make it look like it's affiliated.
And interestingly, the domain of this
mailbox,
cib.com, is almost an anagram of CIBC,
which makes me wonder if this was done
on purpose to attempt to fool someone
not paying close
attention. However, if we want to look
further, let's open this in Sublime
Text. We can notice that the return path
is set to a different email address,
which raises our suspicion.
Additionally, if we look at the received
headers from the bottom up, we can
notice that the originating mail server
is affiliated with Comcast Business. And
if we look at the X sender IP or
continue looking through the email
headers, we'll notice the IP address of
190.6.201.67. And so to be thorough and
complete here, let's do a reverse DNS
lookup again.
So, if we paste in that IP address,
we'll quickly find that the IP address
is located in Honduras and is affiliated
with a Honduran telecommunications
company called Cable Color, which is not
at all related to CIBC
Bank. So, I think that was a good first
look into email headers, and I'm going
to cut it short here so we can talk
about authentication headers
specifically in the next lesson.
Now, let's talk about email
authentication headers because we've
been hinting at them a few times so far.
There are three major email
authentication technologies out there.
We have SPF, DKIM, and Demar. And using
these protocols, we can check if a
domain actually did send an email and
essentially identify potential email
spoofing. So, first we have SPF or the
sender policy framework. And this is a
mechanism that allows domain owners to
specify which mail servers are
authorized to send emails on behalf of
their domain. And it works by publishing
SPF records in the domain name systems
or the DNS for a domain. And these SPF
records contain a list of IP addresses
or domain names of servers that are
authorized to send emails for the
domain. For example, we can check the
SPF records for any domain manually
using the NS lookup or dig command. So,
for example, if I want to check the SPF
records for
showdown.io, well, I can just use the
nsookup command, I can set the type to
text because this is the format in which
the SPF records are published. I can
specify the domain, so
shodden.io. And because this is going to
give us all of the text records for the
domain, well, I can pipe this to
something like GP where I can just
search for SPF records. And if we run
that, we can see this string here, which
is the SPF record itself. Now, before we
jump into this, we can also do this with
dig. So, if I run dig, I'm just going to
search for text records for
showdown.io. And again, I'm going to
pipe this to Grep where I can search for
SPF. And again, we get a very similar
string here, which is the record that
was published. So, let's look at this in
more detail. So, first we have the
version and this specifies the SPF
version being used, which in this case
and in most cases is going to be version
one. Next, we have this IP address here
along with this IP address. So, this
specifies that these IP addresses are
allowed to send email for the domain. We
also have include an S
spf.google.com. So, this includes the
SPF record of this domain here, this
spf.google.com when evaluating SPF for
the Showdown domain. So, this allows
Google's servers to send email on behalf
of Showdown. So, this is basically
saying include everything from this SPF
record. And if we were to look at that
SPF record, well, we can see everything
that it's going to
include. And lastly, here we have this
dashall. And this specifies the policy
for mail servers that don't match any of
the previous mechanisms. And in this
case, the dash all indicates a strict
policy, meaning that emails from
unauthorized senders should be rejected.
And the other one you'll see is the
tilda all. And this qualifier is the
soft fail. And this suggests that the
server should accept mail from IPs not
explicitly listed in the SPF record, but
it should treat them with suspicion. But
the dash all that we can see here, this
means a hard fail. So it specifies a
strict policy in which emails from IPs
not explicitly listed in this record
should be rejected. It is the most
secure option, but it can potentially
result in legitimate emails being
rejected if not configured properly. And
so when an email is received, the
recipient's email server is going to
perform an SPF check by querying the DNS
records of the sender's domain. If the
IP address of the sending mail server
matches any of the authorized IPs or
domains listed in the SPF record, well,
the email is going to pass that SPF
check. However, if the IP address is not
listed or is listed with a different
domain, the email is going to fail the
SPF check. And so you might be thinking
that this doesn't actually verify
whether a sender is legitimate or not.
All it does is verify that the sender
matches or is authorized by the domain
specified in the emails from address.
You'd be exactly right. If an attacker
registers their own domain, maybe a
lookalike domain, and sets up SPF
records themselves, or uses a service
like Gmail or Yahoo, well, the attacker
is going to pass that SPF check with no
issue. So it should never be looked at
in a vacuum. This is why it's equally
important for us to look into the
sender's actual domain along with
performing these authentication checks.
So next we have DKIM which stands for
domain keys identified mail and this is
a method used to authenticate the origin
of email messages. Its primary purpose
is to allow a receiver to verify that an
email message was indeed sent from the
domain that it claims to be and also
that the message content has not been
tampered with during transit. And it
does this using PKI or public key
infrastructure. And so when an email is
sent from a domain with DKIM enabled,
the sending mail server is going to add
a digital signature to the email header
using a unique private key associated
with that domain. The public key
corresponding to the private key that is
used is then published to the DNS record
of the sending domain. And so upon
receiving the email, the recipient's
email server is going to retrieve the
public key from the sender's DNS record
and use it to verify the DKIM signature.
If the signature is valid and the
message content hasn't been tampered
with, well, the email is considered
authentic or passes the check. And
again, it's crucial to note that DKIM
alone doesn't evaluate the content of
the email or the intent behind it. While
it establishes the legitimacy of the
domain, it doesn't assess whether the
domain itself or the sender's intentions
are malicious or not. For example, an
attacker could still use a typo
squatting attack to register a domain
that looks similar and set up DKIM and
SPF themselves to pass on their own
lookalike domain. Or perhaps a
legitimate mailbox was compromised. And
of course, in this case, it's going to
pass the DKIM checks if it's being sent
from an actual mailbox. And lastly here
we have Dmark or domain-based message
authentication reporting and
conformance. And DMARK works alongside
SPF and DKIM to enhance the overall
email authentication with additional
reporting mechanisms. And so while SPF
and DKIM individually authenticate
emails by verifying the sender's domain
and ensuring message integrity, Demar
adds an extra layer of control and
visibility for domain owners. And so
Demar allows domain owners to specify
policies regarding how their email
should be handled if they fail SPF or
DKIM checks. And these policies can
include things like none, which
instructs receiving mail servers to only
report on email authentication results
without taking any action. We also have
quarantine, which directs suspicious
emails to the recipient spam or
quarantine folder. And we also have
reject, which outright rejects email for
failed authentication. And so it's
important to note that demark policies
only outline what actions receiving
email servers should take when they
encounter emails that fail demar checks,
but they don't technically mandate or
enforce compliance. And so ultimately
the recipient's mail server
administrators can choose whether or not
to honor demark policies set by sending
domains. And now that was uh quite a bit
of theory here. So let's look at some
email authentication headers in action.
And so let's go to our fishing analysis
folder. Open up the header analysis
folder as well and go to
sample3.l and we can see here we have an
email that claims to be from namecheep
renewals and namecheep is a domain
registar and it looks like we're getting
some sense of urgency here because we
only have 7 days left to renew our
domain. So let's open this up in sublime
text.
When we look at the received headers, we
can identify when the email was routed
from the sender mail server to our
trusted Google mail server. And the IP
address that we can identify here is
149.72.142.11. So this is the received
header that tells us when the message
left the sender's hands or who the
sender claimed to be and into our
trusted infrastructure, in this case,
Google's mail servers.
And so we can genuinely trust that this
IP address relates to our sender because
it can't be spoofed. You know, there was
a genuine TCP connection that was made
between these two servers. And this is
the artifact from it, this received
header. And so if we perform a lookup on
this IP address, we can see that it
actually returns as send grid, which is
a very common email marketing solution,
which could in theory be abused. But we
can also see the reverse DNS of this
mail server which does in fact return as
namecheep.com. And so now that we know
the original sender and mail server,
let's look at the authentication
checks. And so this is where we should
focus our efforts particularly with our
first check which will be
SPF. We can see the header received SPF.
This is a very important header for us
because it provides information about
whether the email server that received
the message considers the sending server
to be authorized to send emails on
behalf of the purported sender domain.
So what basically happened is that our
email server or Google read the domain
from the return path email header. In
this case this mail service mailout
one.namecheep.com it then check that
domain's DNS records to ask something
like hello mailout 1.namecheep.com
namecheep.com. Do you have any SPF
records published? And if so, do you
send email from
149.72.142.11 because we just got an
email from this domain that claimed to
be from you. And so we can manually
check the SPF records ourselves and
mimic what Google did here on the back
end. And so if you remember, we can use
something like dig or nsookup to do
this. So I'm just going to look for text
records for mail
servicemail.namecheep.com.
It's actually email out one. I was uh
scratching my head figuring out why that
wasn't working. It's mail service email
out one. And if you remember, this is
going to return all the text records. So
I want to GP out specifically for
SPF. And we can see here we have the
full SPF record that was published. And
in this case, the SPF record is include
sendgrid.net, which means that it
includes itself and all of the records
within sendrid.net within this SPF
record. And if we look at all the
records designated by
sendgrid.net, well, we can see a number
of IP address ranges published as
authorized senders in their SPF record.
And specifically, we can see this block
here of
149.72.0.0 on this /16 subnet. And this
is a cider block containing all of the
IP addresses in the range of
149.72.0.0 all the way to 149.72.255.
255.255. And of course, the IP address
of the original sender that we
identified earlier and the one that our
email server used to check SPF is within
this range, meaning it passed the check.
In summary, the email originated from
this 022.mmail
service.namecheep.com with this IP
address, which is authorized to send
emails for mail
serviceout.namecheep.com. And the SPF
record for this domain includes
sendgrid.net, net indicating that emails
may be sent through Sengid's
infrastructure and the receiving email
server in this case Google server
verified this and allowed the email to
pass through. So next let's look at DKIM
and you can see we have a DKIM signature
header here. Well actually we have two
one for namecheep and one for send grid.
Both signatures seem to be using the
same body hash and including the same
set of header fields but they will come
from different domains and selectors.
And this can indicate what we already
confirmed, which is that the email was
processed through multiple email
systems, each applying its own DKIM
signature. And since we're looking for
integrity with DKIM, well, let's focus
on the signature closest to the source
or the namecheep one, and break down its
components. So, first we have the
version, and this is version one, which
typically should always be one. Next
here with this a field, well, this
actually refers to the algorithm that
was used to generate the signature. In
this case, we have Shaw 256, which is
what you'll typically see. But also be
warned if you see a weaker algorithm
like Shaw 1. It doesn't necessarily mean
that it's a malicious email. It just
means that a weaker algorithm was used
to generate the hash, indicating a
higher chance of hash collisions. But
it's not really something to worry
about. We also have this C equals
relax/reaxed. And this refers to the
canonicalization algorithm used for both
the header fields, this first one, and
the body of the message. So, DKIM uses
this to ensure that the signed content
like the headers and the body are
consistent across email systems to
prevent the signatures from being
mismatched or failing due to whites
space or formatting changes. And so,
relaxed means that you know minor
changes in the whites space and line
breaks are permitted between the header
and body which are accepted variations
that still maintain the contents
integrity. And we also have the domain
here. So,
namecheep.com and if we look down to s
here, this is the selector.
And so together the domain and the
selector are used to locate the
associated public key that email systems
can use to verify the signature. So now
that we know the domain and the selector
we can actually manually check the
public key ourselves through
DNS. And so to do this the syntax will
be the following. And again we can use
nsookup or dig to do this. I'll use
nsookup because we can also do this on
Windows as well. And I'm going to put in
that selector as the subdomain here.
And typically the syntax here is going
to be an underscore with domain key. And
then we're going to put in the domain.
So
namecheep.com. And if we look this up,
well, we get this
response. We can see there is a
canonical name set to this sendgrid.net
domain. But we can also see the contents
of the public key
itself. And if we go back to our email,
well, we also have a couple other
fields. So we have BH here. And this is
the body hash which was computed using
that hashing algorithm and encoded in B
64. And under that we have the B field
which is the DKIM signature itself which
is calculated based on the header fields
and the body hash itself. And now we
don't have to verify this manually. Of
course obviously our email system has
done this automatically for us but we
can also use several tools at our
disposal to do this ourselves. Now
instead of using NS lookup well we can
do this lookup through MX Toolbox. Now
if you remember we had the domain name
which was
namecheepief.com and we had the selector
or S1 and if we do a DKIM
lookup well we can get the same result.
We can see the public key here along
with the other details of that DKIM
signature. And now if we go to the email
header analyzer and we copy the contents
of our email and paste it in we can
analyze the header which will perform
some DM checks for us.
If we scroll down to
dkimnamecheep.com with this S1 selector,
well, this was the DKIM signature that
we were analyzing manually. If we click
on show here, we can see all of the
checks that were
performed. So, we can see that the DKIM
record was found and that the record was
valid. We can see that the public key
was present, which of course we verified
manually, but that the signature was
also valid. We can see that the
signature domain matched and there was
alignment with the signature in the
domain. And so alignment is when the
DKIM signing domain matches the header
from domain. In this case, it was
namecheep.com. So it does check out.
You'll notice that the body hash did not
verify. And this is something you want
to make note of because it means
something in the contents of the email
message were changed, obviously breaking
integrity. However, in this case, it's
actually expected here because for the
course, I had to manually redact some
identifiable information like the
original recipient. So just trust that
we don't need to worry about the body
hash check for this example.
So let's put all of this together using
the authentication results header which
we can see here. The authentication
results header is used to convey the
results of all these various
authentication checks. And in our email
it indicates that DKIM passed the check
for both namecheep and send grid. In
this case we can see that SPF passed as
well. And lastly we can see the actual
demark policy. In this case, we passed,
but had we failed, well, it's set to
reject, indicating that it would tell
mail servers to reject this email if it
did not
pass. So, after all of the analysis we
done, well, do you think this email was
real or was it a fishing attempt? Well,
if not obvious already, with all our
checks, it was in fact a legitimate
email. Now, I will stress again that
these email authentication checks are
not a silver bullet for determining the
legitimacy of an email. They simply
confirm that the email has passed
through certain authentication protocols
like SPF and DKIM. While passing these
checks is a positive sign, it never
guarantees that the email is completely
safe or genuine. Right? So attackers
have various methods to exploit
loopholes in these authentication
systems like for example registering a
lookalike domain and setting up the
infrastructure to pass these checks
themselves or actually compromising a
legitimate mailbox. or an attacker might
leverage legitimate email services like
Google or Yahoo, which will pass all of
these checks. So, of course, while
they're important, they should not be
blindly trusted. Malicious emails can
sometimes slip through these checks, and
legitimate emails might also
occasionally fail them, mostly due to
configuration issues. And so, it's
essential for us to conduct further
analysis beyond just relying on
authentication results. So we need to
verify the domain and the sending IP
address doing reverse lookups and seeing
what email server is actually on the
other end and also assessing the overall
context of the email and carefully
examining its content which we're going
to do in the next
lesson. Now that we've discussed header
analysis, let's shift our focus to the
substance of these emails, right? What
language does the email employ? Are
there any indicators of social
engineering tactics? How does the email
appear when it's viewed in the client?
We can think of considerations like the
content type, encoding or wording or
even grammar and
formatting. So to start, let's open our
fishing analysis folder and let's head
to the content analysis directory and
open up sample 1.
ML. So this is going to be the first
email that we're looking at. And
specifically, let's also open this up in
Sublime Text.
And so in a typical email file, the
actual body of the email consists of the
MIME or the multi-purpose internet mail
extension parts. And so if we look at
this header here, we can see the MIME
version of
1.0. And MIME allows emails to contain
different types of content like plain
text or HTML or images and attachments.
Each part of an email is typically
separated by a boundary similar to this
one.
So again, some of these headers we have
the mime version and so this indicates
the version of mine that's being used.
We also have the content type. So this
header will specify the type of content
in the email body. So it can be plain
text like we see here or it could be
text/ HTML for HTML content. And there
are many other
possibilities. And next we have the
content transfer encoding header. And
this header specifies how the content is
encoded for transmission. So common ones
you'll see are 7 bit or 8 bit or even
base 64 which we looked at earlier or
quoted printable and of course in our
example it's 7 bit and this means that
no encoding is applied and we talked
about the boundary and so each mime part
is separated by a generated boundary
string and so this boundary is used to
differentiate and distinguish different
parts of the email body and so the
presence of two boundary strings here
indicates that the email contains two
parts and this is a common practice in
mime encoded emails. to provide an
alternate representation of the same
content. In this case, we don't have any
plain text content. All of it is under
this HTML here. And we can see the text
HTML under the content type indicating
that this is going to be HTML rendered
content. Just as a quick aside, this is
a completely separate email, but you can
see if we scroll down to the content
section, we have two different types of
content here. The first version of the
email as signified by the content type
header is a plain text email. And we can
see here this email is just written in
plain text. If we scroll down, we can
see a second content type partitioned by
the content boundary. And in this case,
it is an HTML version of the same email.
And if we were to open this in our email
client, well, we can obviously see the
HTML version of the email signified by
the images and the different styling
here. But if we go up to the view tab
and go down to message body, well, we
can change it from original HTML to
something like plain text. And now we're
visually seeing that plain text version
of the
email. Now, let's return to the email in
the client. And we can see some oddities
right off the bat that might provide red
flags that this isn't a legitimate
email. Well, first off, the email is
claiming to be from Trust Wallet, a
cryptocurrency trading platform. At
first glance, I didn't know what Trust
Wallet
was. But a simple Google search showed
me that the organization that the email
claims to be from is somewhat
legitimate. However, the first thing I
notice is that there is a discrepancy
between how the company name is spelled
in the email versus how the company name
is actually spelled. So, we can see in
the email, well, we don't have a space
between trust and wallet. It's all one
word, but the actual company is two
words, trust and wallet. And there are
also a couple of random grammar and
spelling oddities in the email, such as
the greeting. So, we can see hi dear
semicolon customer. This appears to be a
failed attempt at writing a generic
greeting since it sounds awkward and
contains awkward punctuation. Sometimes
you'll see fishing emails that can
actually parse and decipher a mailbox's
associated name such as Andrew or Bob or
Emily. But in this case, less
configuration was done on the attacker
end to just give a generic customer
greeting. The first line of the email
here also indicates a potential attempt
at inducing a sense of urgency, claiming
that we have an unverified account that
will be suspended if we don't action the
email. And of course, this isn't always
a case closed kind of indicator, but
seeing these types of social engineering
tactics come into play should raise our
suspicion and warrant further
investigation. You'll often see this
done with expiring accounts or claiming
accounts will be suspended because in
many cases, money and bank details are
involved like with banks and
cryptocurrency exchanges. Well, victims
might feel a heightened sense of urgency
and quite easily click on malicious
links. And so, let's take a look at
sample two.
And again, this also claims to be from
Trust Wallet. And we can obviously go
into the headers and almost immediately
identify this as a spoofing or
impersonation attempt, but let's just
focus on the content. This time, they
seem to have typed the Trust Wallet name
correctly, but we're still getting a
generic greeting with dear customer, and
a lot of poor grammar. For example, we
can see the possessive accent here next
to NFTTS, which grammatically shouldn't
be there as it's indicating a plural.
Lastly, down here, the word assistant is
spelled incorrectly, indicating whoever
wrote this email might not have English
as a first language. And surprisingly,
this is a very common occurrence. You
know, you don't have to be an English
major, but being able to spot
grammatical or spelling errors can
quickly raise suspicion that an email
did not come from a professional source.
But on the other side, with things like
AI and options like chat GPT are
becoming so readily available, well,
attackers from all around the world can
quickly generate legitimate sounding
copy for emails, which is why this alone
can't be our only
barometer. So, next, let's take a look
at sample
3. And in this case, we'll find a
genuinely convincing looking body
resembling an Amazon account suspension
notice. And it uses all the correct
formatting and logos and fonts. They
likely copied this from a legitimate
Amazon email. And so you can imagine
that someone who might have recently
ordered something on Amazon, which of
course is quite common these days, could
receive this email and jump to
conclusions out of fear and manipulation
of authority. And in this case, the
content of this fish was done so well
that we can't just rely on content
inspection alone. And of course, we
never should. And so we'll need to look
at other methods of analysis like header
analysis and URL inspection, which we'll
get to in the next section.
And now we talked a bit about encoding
before. B 64 encoding is a method used
to encode binary data into ASKY
characters, making it suitable for
transmission over textbased channels
like email. And so B 64 is very common
within emails because it converts binary
data into a string of asky characters.
And so B 64 encoding is often
legitimately used within email messages
for things like presenting non-asky
characters or email attachments like
images or documents. But it can also be
used to offiscate the email's content
and potentially evade detection by very
weak email filters. Either way, we
should be familiar with recognizing and
decoding it to reveal the true email
content. For example, let's open up
sample 4. And let's also open it up in
Sublime
Text. So, if we scroll down to the
content of this email, and we can also
see it from the preview window here, we
have a long block of B 64 content. And
how do I know it's B 64 data? Well,
partly due to experience and knowing
what base 64 strings look like. And
admittedly, there's some common
indicators like this one or two equal
signs at the end which indicate padding
characters. But of course, we can also
just scroll up and realize that the
content transfer encoding here is set to
base
64. And I believe in a previous lesson
we looked at doing this through the
terminal. But we can also use a tool
like Cybersh to decode this for
us. So I'm just going to copy the entire
string here. And I'm going to open up
Cybersh. And in this input window here,
we can just paste in the contents. And
if we go under operations, well, we can
see it already. If we do from B 64, you
can see that this operation will decode
data from an ASKI B 64 string back into
its raw format. So if we drag this over
to our recipe and let it go, well, we
can see in our output that it was
successfully decoded into HTML text. And
so if we look at this, this is the
actual HTML and CSS markup that made up
our
email. So next, let's cover another
encoding mechanism called HTML entity
encoding, where in reality, this is
really just a sequence of characters to
represent specific HTML characters. And
so HTML uses entities to display
characters that are reserved for HTML
syntax or characters that have
specialized meanings like the angled
brackets here, the less than and greater
signs or things like amperands and
non-breing spaces. So for example, if we
go back into Cybersh and if we just put
an and symbol here and if we go under
operations and look for we can just do a
search for HTML entity. And if we drag
over to HTML entity, well, this is going
to convert characters into those HTML
entities. And if we drag this over,
well, we can see our and symbol here
turned into this and AMP with a
semicolon at the end. And for example,
if I were to check off this convert all
characters, well, this is going to
basically convert everything I type into
HTML entities. If I just type in test,
for example, well, we can see a number
of HTML entities. This one refers to the
letter T. This one refers to the letter
E and so
on. And so attackers often employ
various techniques to bypass spam
filters. And the use of HTML entities is
one such method. And you can likely see
how HTML entities can be leveraged. For
example, suppose we have a spam filter
in place to reject or quarantine any
emails that include the phrase Bitcoin.
And bear with me in this scenario. Maybe
our organization has nothing to do with
Bitcoin and we've been seeing an uptick
in cryptocurrency related scams.
In this case, an attacker could just
insert one of these entity characters to
potentially bypass the spam filter. And
I'll say any good quality filters will
be able to decode this and perform
static analysis to catch this evasion
attempt. Lastly, let's take a quick look
at URL encoding. And URL encoding is a
method used to convert characters into a
format that can be transmitted over the
internet. Again, this is often used for
legitimate purposes, but an attacker may
attempt to encode URLs to bypass some
weaker spam filters. And URL encoding
works by replacing non-alpha numeric
characters with a percent sign followed
by a two-digit hexadimal value that
represents the character in the ASI
character set. For example, let's paste
in the cybersh URL into the input. And
if we do a quick search for URL, well,
we should see URL encode as an option
right here. And this is going to encode
potentially problematic characters into
that percent encoding. So, if we drag
this over to the recipe and click on
encode all special characters, well, we
can see a number of those characters
like the colon and the backslashes have
been transformed into that percent
encoding. So, if we open up sample email
5 in sublime
text and scroll down to the body content
and if we hit F to do a search, we can
search for percent to E. And we can see
a long string of text here that is both
URL encoded and also HTML entity
encoded. And of course we can decode
this using Cybersh. So if I just find
where it ends based on the quotation
here and go all the way to where this
URL starts based on the first quotation,
I can just copy this. And interestingly
enough, if we scroll up here to the
content transfer encoding, we can also
see that this content is encoded with
the quoted printable. And so basically
that's three layers of encoding we have
here in that URL. So, let's head back
over to Cybersh and paste in that URL.
And we can see it doesn't really look
like a proper URL because it's been
encoded using that
quotable. So, first let's look up quoted
printable and we can select the from
quoted printable option. Let's drag that
over to a recipe and we can see our URL
is starting to look a little bit better.
But remember, we also have HTML entity
encoding. So, let's look up that as
well.
If we scroll down to from HTML entity
again, we can drag that into our
recipe and we can see that our URL was
cleaned up a little bit. And lastly,
let's look up URL and go down to URL
decode and drag that over. And we can
finally get to our full URL without any
of that
encoding. And so now that we have the
URL decoded, we can now pass it over to
some tools to conduct URL analysis. And
speaking of URL analysis, well, let's
get into that in the next
lesson. Now, arguably the most important
thing contained in the content of an
email message is going to be the URLs,
which is not something we've covered
yet. So, let's dive into URL inspection
and analysis within this lesson. So,
let's first quickly go over the anatomy
of a typical fishing URL because we can
learn to identify some indicators that
might heighten our suspicion as we go
about analyzing these links. So in a
standard URL like the one you can see on
screen, we often have some or all of
these components. So first we have the
protocol and this indicates the
communication protocol to be used for
accessing the resource and describes the
way in which browsers should retrieve
the information. So common protocols
you'll see might be HTTP or hypertext
transfer protocol or of course
HTTPS. But there can also be protocols
like FTP here as well. And next you
might have a subdomain. And so a
subdomain is like a subdivision of the
domain that can be used to organize or
distinguish different sections or zones
of a website. And so we can think of
mail.google.com or
drive.google.com. And in this case we
have the academy subdomain of the TCM
domain. And so next of course we have
the domain name itself. And the domain
name consists of the second level domain
which is the name of the website in this
case TCM sec and the top level domain
which specifies the type of website that
it's going to be. And so you might see
things like.com or.net or.edu or.gov or
even country specific names like
or.ca.is. And the combination of this
tople domain and the second level domain
is the only part that is unique in the
URL. And so this is very important
because attackers can spoof subdomains
or registered identical domains under
different top level domains, right? But
the combination between the second and
top level domain cannot be copied. And
so when we put all of this together,
this becomes the host name. And this is
made up of the domain name as well as
any
subdomains. And so next we have a
subdirectory. And this is a directory or
folder within the website's file
structure or a defined route on the
server side that is used to organize
content. In this example, we have a
subdirectory called courses which holds
files for various courses hosted on the
site. And speaking of files, well, this
is the specific file or resource being
accessed on the server. So, it could be
an actual file with an extension like
a.php or just a route that points to a
file in more modern applications and
might not contain a file extension. And
together, we refer to the file being
accessed along with any subdirectories
as the path or the entire location of
this resource. And optionally, you might
see things like parameters. And so
parameters in a URL are additional
pieces of information that are appended
to the end of the URL after the question
mark symbol. And these parameters are
often used to provide specific
instructions or data to the server when
you're requesting a resource. And
they're typically structured in these
key value pairs, right? We have t= 129.
And so we have the name of the key along
with its corresponding value separated
by an equal sign. And of course, we can
have multiple parameters in a URL by
separating them with the amperand. In
this case, this is just a madeup
example, but maybe the t key refers to a
timestamp of a specific video that
you're watching on the academy. In this
case, the value might refer to 129
seconds. So, when you navigate to this
URL, the server knows to retrieve or
display the video starting from the
129th second. And YouTube actually does
this exact thing.
Now, this was a clean example of a URL,
of course, but let's look at some actual
recent fishing URLs that I pulled from a
malware database. And we can see how
they're
constructed. And in this case, the first
thing that jumps out is the absence of
the HTTPS protocol in the URL. This
indicates that the connection to the
website is not secure. And most often
legitimate login pages, especially those
with sensitive information like email
credentials, will use HTTPS and
automatically upgrade non-scure
connections to encrypt data
transmission. And of course, there are
still legacy sites and bad
configurations out there, but it should
be one of those indicators that makes us
suspicious. And so next, we actually
have an attempt at subdomain spoofing,
which we can see here. The subdomain
apple-lo suggests that this URL is
associated with Apple's login system.
However, if we look at the base domain,
DNSD.net, well, this of course does not
match Apple's official domain. We also
have an somewhat unusual domain
extension. And this is not a huge
indicator, but we can see the net here
is a little odd because it's typically
not a tople domain that Apple would use.
And so, next here we have an odd
subdirectory. And to be honest, I'm not
sure what this means. And you might see
odd generated UIDs or strings or
specific routes in certain applications,
but in this case, it just seems a little
odd. And if I were to take a guess, the
attacker probably uses this base domain
to host a variety of different fishing
campaigns and likely titles them with
unique identifiers like this one. And if
we jump to the end here, we can see a
suspicious parameter. And this parameter
seems to be collecting email addresses.
And I actually redacted the original
email from the URL. But in the case of
this actual email, well, the victim who
received it had their email prefilled
into the URL. And this is actually
something you'll see quite commonly and
is one of those red flag indicators that
should immediately make you suspicious
of a URL. Like fishing websites will
often request personal information like
email addresses and passwords. And to
make them seem more credible, attackers
might try to prefill certain fields in
the URL or web page to make it look like
the website is real and it like saved
your information from last time, right?
Like email addresses. And they can do
this very easily by appending it in URL
parameters. So let's look at another one
here.
In this case, we have another example of
subdomain spoofing. The subdomain
MetaMask-restoration-sport. Well, this
suggests that there's a connection here
to MetaMask, which is a popular
cryptocurrency website. However, if we
look at the actual base domain, this
webflow.io, well, it does not correspond
obviously to MetaMask in any way. In
this case, we have the abuse of a
legitimate service. And so, Web Flow is
actually a custom website builder. And
attackers commonly use services like
this or services like Wix to quickly
spin up a hosted web page that already
has the trust of a legitimate service.
And speaking of that, here is another
example of subdomain spoofing and the
use of a legitimate service. And quite
honestly, I see the
wicksite.com/my site string so often
that in my opinion, it's probably a good
idea to just block any email containing
this string. And so, can you see what's
wrong with this URL?
Well, in this case, we have a form of
typo squatting where the letter R was
omitted to create a lookalike domain.
And so, a user not paying close
attention could fall for something like
this very easily if the web page itself
closely resembled
Microsoft. Now, how about this one? Can
you see any red
flags? Well, we have some potentially
suspicious subdomains and also this
query parameter is a little hard to
understand. But actually in this case
this is a legitimate URL and I wanted to
include this to show that legitimate
sites can have a number of subdomains
especially in the login process. In this
case we have
connect.secure but we can see that the
base domain or the full domain is
wellsfargo.com which is the legitimate
site for the bank. And legitimate sites
can also use weird or vague parameters
to control different aspects of the page
or rendering. In this case we have
origin equals co. And in this case, I'm
not actually sure, but it could be
indicating that the login request is
coming from the consumer online banking
or the COB platform. And of course, this
is just a guess. And we don't actually
have to go around trying to deconstruct
every parameter we find, but it's
definitely something to look out
for. And now, what about this one? It
looks very similar, but do you see it?
Well, the S was omitted to read Well
Fargo. Now, of course, this is not a
real example. I just modified the one
from before. But in this case, in our
example, the attacker would have set up
the web page and the subdomains in such
a way to mimic the original almost
exactly. This is why it's so important
to understand that the only true unique
portion of a URL is the combination of
the domain name and the top level
domain. Now, lastly, what about this
one? And it's identical to the ones
before, but in this case, the top level
domain has been changed. Now, remember
the second level domain or Wells Fargo
and the tople domain.com cannot be
spoofed. they're completely unique. But
in this case, an attacker would have
registered a very similar domain with a
tople domain that looks like.com, but in
this case isn't. And again, this isn't a
real example. And Wells Fargo might have
actually purchased the Docam variant of
the domain proactively to prevent this
kind of typo
squatting. Okay, let's get back to
business. So the first step in URL
analysis is of course extracting the
URLs from the email content. And this
can either be done manually or through a
number of different automated tools or
scripts. So the first method we'll cover
is not something I'd typically
recommend, but still something that we
can demonstrate. So first, let's
navigate to the URL analysis folder
within the fishing analysis section, and
let's open up sample 1.
ML. And you'll probably recognize this
chasebank fish from the header analysis
section. So now that we have the email
opened up in our client, we can actually
use our client itself to hover over and
view URLs or hyperlinks within an email.
So for example, if we move our mouse
over to the reactivate your account
link, well, we can see in the bottom of
our client where that URL leads to. And
for any links or URLs that we find, we
can rightclick on the link itself and
click to copy the link location
manually. And the issue with this method
is that when we're potentially dealing
with malicious URLs. So you can imagine
that a simple misclick like if you
accidentally hit the left mouse button
instead of the right, well, it means
that we could accidentally end up
visiting the page. And also this method
relies on visual inspection. And so it's
very easy for us to miss a hyperlink by
not seeing it in the email. Or even some
CSS styles could be implemented so that
URLs aren't colored blue or not
underlined or not in a button like this,
which we're used to seeing. You know, we
could even be dealing with an image
that's clickable that we won't really
notice unless we hover our mouse over
every word. And so, this leads us to
some more robust methods. And as you're
familiar by now, well, we've been
opening up emails inside of Sublime
Text. We could essentially use any text
editor, even like Notepad on Windows,
but Sublime Text is a useful and also a
personal choice.
And so once we open up sample one in
Sublime Text, we can use the native
search functionality to find any
instances of URLs in the file. So this
is going to require a bit of logical
thinking, but if we hit Ctrl+F, we can
open up this search pane. And then we
can search for specific strings like
HTTP. And we're not always going to get
a URL with this method because sometimes
HTTP is a string that's included in the
body of the content or maybe somewhere
in the headers. But if we keep scrolling
around, we can see we have four matches
here in total. And the first one here,
we get a URL. And the next one here, we
also get that URL. And this specifically
is the reactivate your account button
that we were looking at in the rendered
content. Alternatively, we can search
for things like the opening bracket in
HTML. And then search for the A which is
an anchor tag. And in HTML, an anchor
tag like this is used for hyperlinks.
And so again, we can immediately find
this reactivate your account link. And
of course, the advantages of this method
are that we have no risk of accidentally
clicking on a link. And also, we won't
miss any findings as long as we use the
right search strings. As another method,
we can also return to the ever useful
Cybersheef to automatically extract URLs
from an email file. And so, let's
navigate back to
Cybersh. And in this case, we can either
paste the entire contents of the email
message or alternatively, we can click
on this open file as input button. And
from here we can navigate through our
explorer window to find the specific
file that we want to upload. And you can
see here once doing that we've uploaded
the entire file into the input. Now if
you remember this specific email was
encoded with that quoted printable
encoding. And in this type of encoding
well our URL is actually being split
into multiple lines. Meaning that if we
were to just try to extract URLs the
normal way, well we wouldn't be able to
do that. So if you remember what we need
to do is to first decode this from that
quoted printable encoding and so we can
just search for quote here and we can
select the from quoted printable and
drag it into our recipe and from here we
can then search for URL and what we're
looking for here is extract URLs and
what this is going to do is as the title
suggests extract any URLs from the text
and you can see here once we drag that
into a recipe we are getting those two
URLs that we identified earlier. And
lastly, while we're here, and this is
something we'll cover shortly, but we
can use Cyerechef to defang the URLs.
And to defang a URL means to modify it
in such a way that it no longer
functions as a clickable hyperlink. And
this is often done for security
purposes, especially in context where we
might not want to click on a malicious
link. Now you can imagine that as we
document these specific URLs either in
our report or in a ticket. Well, when we
paste them into our ticketing system,
these URLs can sometimes be
automatically converted into a clickable
hyperlink. And obviously, as we are
dealing with potentially malicious URLs
here, well, we want a way to prevent
them from being automatically turned
into links. And so by adding the defang
URL option, which we can simply search
defang, we can drag over the defang URL.
And you can see these hyperlinks were
changed slightly. Instead of the
protocol as HTTPS, it added these two
X's here to make it an invalid protocol.
Additionally, certain things like the
dots separating the subdomains or the
col/ slash to indicate the protocol have
been squared out in these brackets.
These defanged URLs are now safe for us
to document and it is of course best
practice to do so.
And lastly, there are of course other
ways to do this. And I want to
demonstrate a tool that I wrote
specifically for this that can save us a
lot of manual work. And this is the
email IC extractor. And it's definitely
not the only kind of script out there
for this purpose. But it is a Python
script that is designed to aid in email
forensics and analysis by extracting
various components from the email files.
So it will extract things like the IP
addresses, the URLs, and even headers
and attachment information. And it will
all do this in this defanged format. So,
if you're curious, we can open it up
here by clicking on ei.py and click on
the raw view. We could clone the entire
repository, but we really only need the
script itself. And back in our terminal,
I'm going to back out into the tools
directory. And then I'm just going to w
get that URL to copy the Python file.
And now all we need to do is run the
Python script. And we can do that with
Python 3 and then provide the name of
the script. And you can see we're
getting the usage information here. So,
it wants us to provide a file path to
the email file that we want to
investigate. So, in this case, we can
back out of the tools folder, go into
our URL analysis folder, and then we can
select sample 1. ML. And when we hit the
enter key here, it's going to run those
automated checks for
us. And so, you can see if I scroll up,
we extracted several things like the IP
addresses, and these were specifically
from the email headers if you remember
correctly. And this script even
introduces some enrichment capabilities
to do that IP lookup. So we can see the
AS number and we can see the location of
this IP address. In this case, we don't
get the information for the first IP
address because if you recall, this is a
private IP address. But if we scroll
down, we can see the extracted URL
section. And much like with Cybersh, we
getting that same output in defanged
format.
We can also see some common and useful
headers for us like the authentication
results, the from the date, the message
ID, all of these things that we
typically want to document. And of
course, this is a very quick and easy
way to do it. But of course, it's not
foolproof. So that's why I wanted to go
through manually extracting headers
first so we understand the reasons why
and the methodology before we start
relying on tools like this. And now once
we've extracted the URLs from our
suspicious email, well, we're of course
going to want to analyze them and
perform reputation checks to help us
determine if they're malicious or not.
And of course, we have plenty of tools
at our disposal to perform these checks,
which we're going to cover in this
lesson. And again, it's important to
note that these tools are not foolproof.
And what I mean is we can't just blindly
trust these tools to give us a verdict.
We have to use critical thinking skills
and make our own judgment. And so just
because a URL is not identified as
malicious by our tooling, well, it does
not mean that it's safe. It just means
that the URL in question might not have
been submitted and reported before. And
now a blessing and a curse here is that
malicious websites often get taken down
quickly. Either through individuals and
organizations investigating them and
reporting these websites or the ISPs
themselves and the registars being made
aware through alerts and taking them
down or even services like Google Safe
Browsing and Microsoft Smart Screen
updating their signatures to block these
sites. And so because of this, some of
the URLs in the emails here might not be
live when you're watching this lesson.
And so to get some live and recent URL
samples, I'm going to be using Fish
Tank, which I briefly showcased before.
And essentially, Fish Tank is a database
where researchers can report malicious
fishing URLs for community review and
categorization. So let's start looking
at a tool that is self-proclaimed as a
screenshot as a service tool. So, you
might have wondered if there's a way for
us to get a visual representation of
what a specific website or URL looks
like without us having to actually
navigate to it and potentially expose
ourselves to a malicious site. Well, we
can use a tool called URL to PNG for
this. And I'll have this link down
below. And by inputting a suspicious URL
into this site, we can generate a
snapshot of its current appearance,
allowing us to assess if it's legitimate
based on visual cues like the design and
content and layout. Of course, this
isn't foolproof, but it's a great
resource for us to be able to grab a
screenshot of a website that we can put
in our reports or tickets. And of
course, just like I mentioned, this does
not provide any insight into the
underlying safety or security of the
website. So, even if a site appears
benign in a screenshot, well, it could
of course still be malicious. And so, as
such, we need to complement this tool
with other analysis methods that we're
going to
cover. So, I'm going to try to find a
live link here that we can analyze. And
specifically, I can see this one near
the bottom. this
sp5618.com/lo because it says /lo. Well,
this is particularly interesting for me.
This is most likely a credential capture
page. So, I'm going to copy this link
and head back over to URL to png. From
here, I'll just scroll down to where we
find this URL bar. And I can just paste
in our URL here and click on I'm not a
robot. And from here, I just click on
the green button here to start the scan.
And you can see almost immediately we're
greeted with what looks like some sort
of credential capture page.
Specifically, it looks to be
impersonating the Shopppee service. And
if we look up Shopppee, well, it appears
to be some sort of e-commerce platform
based in Southeast Asia. And of course,
the actual domain here is shopppee.com
and not this
SP5618. So, it's clear that we most
likely found a credential capture page
here. And so, this leads us to
urlcan.io. And this is an online
sandboxing tool that allows us to
analyze and inspect the behavior of URLs
in a controlled environment. So, I'm
going to head over to URLcan.io. And we
can see a bunch of recent scans here
that other people have performed. And
one of the key advantages to URL scan is
that its ability to provide detailed
reports on the analyzed URL's behavior.
And these reports can then include
information about the reputation score
of the domain or verdicts based on
previous reports and scanning or even
the underlying web technologies that
make up the site. And similar to URL to
PNG, we can often get a screenshot of
the site as well. So, it really does it
all. So, one thing to note here is we
want to go under options and click on a
private scan. If we don't, well, our
scan result and report is going to be
made public, which you can see with all
these results here. And sometimes you
might be dealing with a potentially
sensitive URL that might contain some
real data, right? And so to preserve
some of our privacy, we're going to
click on this private scan here. And
then we're just going to paste in our
URL. So, let's use the same one from
before and run a private scan.
And now the report is finished. We can
immediately see some interesting things.
First, it looks like it did manage to
get that screenshot for us. And we're
seeing the same credential capture login
page. But we also get a ton of more
information. Specifically, we can see
the IP address related to this domain or
this website. And specifically, if we
look at the summary here, we can see
that the website contacts two different
IPs at runtime. We can see the main IP
of the website is this and it's located
in Singapore. We can even see who it
belongs to or the ISP. And some even
more interesting information is under
this live information tab. Specifically,
we can see that the Google safe browsing
service already has identified this
website as malicious. And very
interestingly, we can see when the
domain was created on May 10th of 2024,
which at the time of this recording was
yesterday, which is almost a silver
bullet for us because honestly, if a
domain was registered yesterday or even
in the last 30 days, most likely it is
some sort of fishing attempt. And often
what organizations will do will block
any email sent by or containing a URL
that has a domain created in the last 30
days just because this is so prevalent.
And so another tool in our arsenal is
going to be Virus Total. And Virus
Total, which we're going to look at so
many times within this course, is an
immensely popular online service that
can aggregate multiple antivirus engines
and other security products or tools to
scan files or URLs or even just hashes
for potential threats. And so what we
can do here is go under the URL tab and
paste in that URL. We'll use the same
one we've been using. And by submitting
a URL to Virus Total, well, we can
leverage its extensive database of
signatures to assess the safety of the
link. And also, Virus Total will allow
us to view the historical data and also
community feedback about a URL. And by
doing this, we can gauge its reputation
over time. So, I pasted in that URL, and
I'm just going to hit the enter key to
run our scan. And we can see almost
immediately two of 92 security vendors
flag this URL as malicious. Most likely,
just because it's so new, I expect to
see this number grow as time goes on.
But we can see one of the vendors here
flagged it as fishing. And if we go
under the details
tab, we can again see some interesting
information. We can see the final URL in
the case of any redirects. We can see
the serving IP address. We can even get
a hash in Shaw 256 of the body of the
HTTP response that was sent back from
the server. We can get all of the
response headers as well. And so again,
Virus Total is going to be a very useful
tool for us, and we're definitely going
to return to it once we get to the file
attachment analysis
stage. Now, again, if you recall, we did
not have an option to do a private scan
here. So, of course, you want to be very
careful when submitting sensitive data,
specifically with URL parameters into
Virus Total. For example, maybe if this
URL had a parameter like email equals
and then some sort of internal email
address at our company name. Well, it
would typically be best practice to
remove this parameter from the URL
because we don't want it to be scanned
and logged on virus total. And now
before we move on, there are a couple of
other useful tools that I'll cover. So,
URL void is another such tool that can
help us detect potentially malicious
websites and also perform some checks on
the website's domain or URL reputation.
And this service is going to run our URL
through over 30 block list engines and
also website reputation services to
generate a verdict for us. So again,
let's paste in this same URL we've been
using and hit scan
website. Interestingly enough, we did
not get any detections this time.
However, we get a number of useful
information that we're used to seeing.
But in this case, the website was likely
too new to be captured by any of these
detection engines. So, of course, this
is a good example of why we don't just
blindly trust one tool because if we
were to only use URLvoid, well, maybe we
would blindly assume that the site is
safe. Now, what if we wanted to get the
actual contents of the web page? You
know, we've gotten a screenshot before,
but what about the actual markup and the
HTTP response? Well, we can use a tool
like W browser to simulate a browser and
get the response for us. So, I'm going
to paste in the URL and hit get here.
And in our response here, we can see
general info, but if we scroll down to
headers, we can get all of the response
headers. And interestingly, if we go to
the body, we can see the entire body of
the response. And interestingly, we can
see some inline script tags with this
JavaScript here. So in cases where we
wanted to return the actual markup or
response of the body, well we can use a
tool like wannab
browser. We also talked before about
shortened URLs and how attackers can use
services like bit.ly or tiny URL to
shorten and offiscate their malicious
URLs to get around detection. Well,
fortunately we can also use a tool like
wannab browser to detonate that
shortened URL and also follow any
automatic redirects to arrive at the
final true website. Now you might
remember from a previous lesson I set up
this bit.ly URL to /totally amazing
website which in turn redirects to TCM
security. And so if I paste in that URL
here and hit get one browser is going to
simulate a browser and follow any
redirects. And if we look under the
headers we can see that we got a 301
response at first. And if we look under
the location header we can see that we
were redirected to
tcm-sec.com. And the second response
here the 200 is from tcmssec.com.
In the previous lesson, we demonstrated
unshorten it to do this similar thing.
So, let's demonstrate that
again. And you can see the destination
URL was in fact
tcm-sec.com. And lastly, there might be
cases where we don't get any solid
results using the above methods. In this
case, we can turn to some open source
malicious website exchanges like fish
tank, which allow researchers to submit
suspected fishing emails to verify and
analyze submissions. So, for example, we
can do a search for that same
sp5618.com website and click on is it a
fish. And when we click on that, we can
see the previous submission. So, while
this hasn't been assigned a verdict yet,
we know from our analysis that it most
likely is a credential capture page.
Similarly, URL house is a collection of
malicious URLs submitted by researchers
and automated scanners. When we view the
database, we can see when a specific URL
was added, the URL itself, as well as
its status, like is it still up or has
it been taken down, and we can also get
some tags like what kind of fishing or
credential harvester is hosted, as well
as who reported
it. And lastly, we can use Google Safe
Browsing to check the status of a
specific domain. If you recall, the
domain that we were looking at was
apparently flagged by Google Safe
Browsing. So if we were to check the
status here and click search, well you
can see that this site is unsafe. And if
we were to attempt to visit this in a
Google browser, well, we would receive a
similar
warning. I'll also mention that it's
very important for us to also do a scan
of the base domain. And what I mean by
that is suppose we identify a URL that
has multiple subdomains attached to it
or maybe for instance we have a number
of subdirectories in our URL or various
query parameters. Well, when we want to
understand the extent of the attack and
the scope, well, it will be just as
important for us to understand what the
base domain of the URL is hosting as
well, we might be able to determine if
the fishing attempt is isolated or if
it's part of a larger campaign or if the
attacker is attempting to use a
legitimate service to conduct their
fishing operations. Or perhaps the base
domain itself is an actual legitimate
website that the attacker managed to
compromise and started to host malicious
subdirectories and files on the website
itself. Ensuring that we scan both our
URL as well as the base domain will
ensure a more thorough response and it's
just something that we always want to
document as
well. And now you might come across URLs
that actually come from legitimate
services like Google or Dropbox. In
these cases, of course, the URLs and the
email itself can't be immediately
written off as clean. Remember, the
technique that attackers often use is to
host malicious websites or documents
using legitimate services to get around
spam filters and security analysts. Take
for example this Google Docs URL. Well,
this is going to come back clean on all
of our checks because it's affiliated
with the legitimate Google service. And
so, we'll need to dive deeper into the
contents of the URL and what's actually
being hosted on Google Drive to continue
our
investigation. And you can see here when
we submit this to URL scan, well, it's
coming back as no verdict. We're not
getting any malicious classification
here. When we look at the summary, well,
we can see this is a legitimate Google
URL that belongs to Google US. And we
can see the main domain is in fact
docs.google.com. And we can see all the
IP addresses that were contacted do in
fact belong to
Google. But interestingly, we can see
this screenshot here. And of course,
like we looked at before, this is
another one of those images that is
attempting to impersonate an Amazon
security alert. And I'm sure if we click
on continue verification here, well, it
would lead to a malicious website. But
sometimes you might get a Google Drive
link. In that case, you need to get a
copy of the file hosted on Google Drive
and then perform attachment analysis,
which we'll get into in the next
section. Now, at this point, if you
still haven't been able to make a
determination either way, even after all
of these tools and services, it might be
time to start looking at and setting up
a secure virtual machine to sandbox the
link and do some manual inspection and
analysis. But remember, it's always best
to air on the side of caution. If we
still have suspicions at this stage,
well, it's often best to assume it's
malicious. And we can also leverage our
additional analysis that we should have
already done at this stage. For example,
if we can already determine the original
sender was fishy during our header and
content analysis, well, it's likely that
this URL can't be trusted either. Now,
alternatively, we could use a tool or a
service like Joe Sandbox, which if we
use the free or basic version, it allows
us to run a maximum of 15 analyses per
month. In many of the socks I worked in,
we typically invested in a tool like
this that allows multiple analysts to
run many more scans per day and it can
be quite useful in expediting the triage
process. And we're going to get more
into Joe Sandbox later on and
specifically use it for attachment and
malware analysis. But just note that it
can also be used to browse and
dynamically detonate URLs. And so
lastly, just remember that tools are
always evolving. There are always going
to be new tools and new updates to
tools. So we need to understand the
methodology first. And this methodology
is that we need to collect artifacts in
the form of URLs and check their
reputation against known sources as well
as using our own analysis to determine
if they're safe to open. And so in the
next video we're going to get into email
attachment analysis which is going to
have a similar methodology but we're
going to use some additional
tools. So far we haven't dealt with any
emails that contain attachments. So
let's change that and start
demonstrating how we can safely analyze
email attachments. And so email
attachments can come in various forms.
They can range from things like actual
innocent, benign documents to
potentially harmful files like
executables or malicious macros and
scripts. And now a word of caution is
that anytime we're dealing with
analyzing potentially malicious files,
well, we need to do so in a secure and
controlled environment. And we have many
tools at our disposal, which we'll cover
that allow us to abstract any potential
dangers and analyze files for us. But in
most cases, we don't even need to look
at or run the file to perform a quick
analysis and perform reputation checks.
And that can be done through file
hashes, which we're going to focus on in
this lesson. So, as we mentioned in the
fundamental section, file hashes and
hashes in general play a crucial role in
cyber security and file integrity
verification. Essentially, a hash is a
unique fingerprint generated from the
content of a file. It's a fixed length
string of characters that's typically
represented in hexadeimal format. And so
even a minor change in a file's content
will result in a wildly different hash
value. So what that means is that if a
specific malicious file or document was
found in an attachment we're analyzing,
we can potentially look up the unique
file hash or fingerprint to see if it
has been reported elsewhere or
automatically picked up by a number of
different antivirus and threat
intelligence platforms. And so common
algorithms that we use to generate file
hashes are things like MD5 and Shaw 1
and most specifically Shaw 256.
And while in practice it's typically
recommended to use a stronger hash value
like Shaw 256 due to things like hash
collisions, well, it's not as important
when we're dealing with collecting a
files hash for reputation checks. And
it's also very simple to just quickly
collect all three. Now, how you actually
obtain the attachment for analysis
entirely depends on your organization's
workflow and tooling and procedures. For
example, if you're dealing with a
fishing report through an alert in a
ticketing system, well, there might be
some workflows and data enrichment
capabilities in place to extract the
attachment from the email or even do
things like retrieve its file hash for
you. Otherwise, you might need to
manually extract the attachment for
analysis. And most email clients allow
you to save attachments to your local
system. But of course, ensure that you
handle the attachment with caution to
prevent any accidental execution. And so
our goal is to save the attachment to
our computer and of course not open or
execute the file inadvertently. So just
as a quick example, let's go to the
fishing analysis section and go under
the attachment analysis directory. Let's
open up sample one. And we can see we
have a suspicious email here requesting
a wire transfer. And specifically, if we
scroll down, you can see there is an
attachment associated with this email.
And so what we can do specifically in
Thunderbird is rightclick on the
attachment itself and we can hit save
as. And so we just need to select where
we want to save this. I'm just going to
put it right in the attachment analysis
folder. And I'm going to hit save. So
you can see here that we successfully
extracted the attachment from the email
and saved it into our directory. In a
Microsoft environment, specifically
through using Outlook on the web, we can
simply click on the action icon next to
an attachment and click on download. And
of course, this will download the file
to our disk.
And within a Googlebased environment,
it's quite honestly as simple as
hovering over the attachment and
clicking on download. And this is going
to download the file to our
disk. Next, I'll showcase an additional
script that will allow us to extract the
attachments from emails all from the
command line or the terminal. And this
is the email dump.py script, which I'll
have linked down below. And this is
actually part of the Dier Stevens suite
of tools, which we're going to cover
some more of these tools later on. And
so to get this script, well, we can just
click on the raw view here. And we can
simply w get this URL. However, you
should already find it in the tools
folder. And so to run it, I'm just going
to call Python 3 and back out into the
tools folder and find that email dump.py
script. And to get some usage
information, I'm just going to append
the tag for the help page. And if we
scroll up, we can see basically the
options of how to use this tool. So
essentially, we just need to provide it
the mime file along with any options
that we want to include. So to start
off, I'm just going to provide it our
sample email and hit
run. And so you can see it extracted
multiple parts of this MIME file. And it
breaks it down in different indexes. For
example, we have the header information
here, but then we have the HTML content
of the file. And lastly, in this fourth
header, well, we have the quotation.iso
file that we want to extract. And so to
extract this, well, we just need to
modify our command and specify the
stream that we want to collect. In this
case, it's four because this fourth
index here is the stream of the
quotation.iso file. We also want to
provide the tac d argument to actually
do the dump itself. And if we just run
this as is, well, it's going to print
everything to standard output or to our
terminal, which we don't want. So, I'm
just going to direct the output into a
quotation.iso file. And if we just run
that, you can see there we have the
quotation.iso file. So again, that's
another way to extract attachments
without having to use the GUI of your
email
client. So now that we have our
attachment extracted, I'll demonstrate
how we can collect its file hashes on
any Unix based operating system like
Linux or Mac OS. And so there are three
commands that we need to remember
depending on what hashing algorithm we
want to collect. So the first one here
is Shaw 256
sum and then we just need to provide the
name of the file. So if we run
quotation.iso, well there we go. We're
getting the Shaw 256 sum of the
quotation.iso file. Similarly, we can
also change this to get other hashes as
well. So if we were to change this to
Shaw 1 sum, well, we're getting the Shaw
1 hash of the file. And lastly, we can
just change this to MD5 sum to get the
MD5 hash as
well. Alternatively, we can run all
three commands at the same time and
separate them with two amperands to run
them consecutively. And you can see here
we're getting all three hashes, which is
very useful for our documentation. And
so now that we have these three hashes,
we definitely want to document them and
note them in our reporting or ticketing
system. And unlike IP addresses or URLs,
we typically don't need to defang hashes
in any way since they're just fixed
length strings of data. I also want to
demonstrate the email IOC extractor tool
that I showed in the previous lesson. So
I'm going to go back into the tools
directory where I have my eioc.py pi
script and I'm going to call it with
Python 3 and then I'm just going to
provide the name of the email. And if we
run it on sample one, well, we can go
all the way down to the extracted
attachments. And you can see here we
have the file name of quotation.iso as
we expected. And we also have the MD5,
the SHA 1, and the SHA 256 hash. So
using this tool, it was technically
safer because we didn't even need to
extract the attachment manually. And we
also have a nice output that we can then
copy for our
documentation. So next I'll show you how
to do this similar thing on a
Windowsbased machine. Now luckily we're
not just limited to Unix based systems
because it's just as likely that you'll
be using a Windows machine over
something like Mac or Linux at some
point in your career. And luckily we can
also extract the same hashes using the
ever useful PowerShell scripting
language. So, I've switched over to our
Windows lab here, and we can navigate to
the same extracted attachment located in
the fishing analysis folder,
specifically in the attachment analysis
folder. And if I run a dur to list out
the files, well, we can see we have the
same quotation.iso file. And so, all we
need to do now is run the get file hash
command and provide the name of the
file. So if I type in get-file hash and
then provide the name of the file with
that dot
/sourcing I can just hit tab to
autocomplete and then I'm just going to
hit
enter and you can see by default we got
the Shaw 256 hash and so if we don't
provide any parameters well we will get
the Shaw 256 hash by default but of
course we can also get different hashing
algorithms as well. For example, if we
wanted to get the MD5 hash, well, we can
simply add the TAC algorithm
flag and then provide MD5. And if we run
this, well, you can see that we're now
getting the MD5
hash. And of course, if we go back and
change this to Shaw 1 and hit run, well,
we're getting the Shaw 1 hash.
Now bear with me because I had to zoom
out a little bit, but we can combine all
three commands together using the
semicolon character separating each
command. In this case, if we hit run,
we're going to get an easyto- read
output of all three file hashes that we
can then copy for our
report. So now that we have the hashes
associated with our suspected file, we
can now use some file reputation
services to gather more information
about them. And these file reputation
services are like online databases that
store information about files including
their hashes and metadata and historical
behavior. And these services will
collect data from various sources like
antivirus vendors or security
researchers and user
submissions. And one commonly used file
reputation service is called virus total
which we looked at in the previous
lesson. And as you remember, Virus Total
can aggregate data from multiple
antivirus engines and other sources to
provide a comprehensive analysis of URLs
and files. We used it previously to
analyze suspected URLs, but we can
perform file reputation checks with it
as
well. And you can see that we can
directly upload a file itself or under
the search tab, we can input a Shaw 256
hash. And so the decision to upload
either a file's hash or the file itself
to Virus Total depends on a number of
factors, specifically our organizational
policies, as well as the nature of the
suspected file and also what our
objectives are. My personal
recommendation is to only ever upload a
hash to Virus Total. Imagine if you had
a suspected file like an invoice, but it
turns out it was actually clean. Well,
if you submitted it to Virus Total,
anyone with the enterprise subscription
will be able to download it. And so by
uploading a file hash, well, it's
considered generally safer from a
confidentiality perspective because it
does not expose the actual contents of
the file to any third party. In many
cases, SOCK analysts might initially opt
to submit the file hash to Virus Total
for a quick assessment of its
reputation. And if the hash lookup
yields any inconclusive results, or if
further analysis is needed, we might
then choose to upload the file itself
after some more thorough examination.
but typically we'll have more private
means for dynamic analysis like Joe
Sandbox assuming we have a company
subscription. So in this case let's copy
the file hash. Specifically I'll use the
Shaw 256 hash and head over to virus
total under the search tab. I'll paste
in the hash here and hit enter to
run. And you can see almost immediately
we got our results returned with 43 out
of 61 security vendors flagging this
file as malicious. And if we start to
look at some of the analysis here, we
can see that many of these vendors
indicate it as a Trojan backdoor. Some
vendors are even associating it with a
specific type of
malware. And if we look under the
details tab, well, we can get some more
information as well. We can also get the
MD5 hash and the SHA 256 hash from
previous uploads and reports. If we look
under history, we can see when it was
first submitted all the way back in
2020. We can also see some other names
of this file and these are file names
that would have been associated with the
exact same hash which is also very
interesting and useful for us if we want
to do a search for something like
application.bin in addition to
quotation.iso within our environment.
Under the relations tab, we'll see many
different things. So we can actually see
things like contacted URLs and domains
that this piece of malware contacts
during its
execution. We can also see the IP
addresses that were contacted.
Specifically, this IP address was
detected as malicious. Under the
behavior tab, we can see some
interesting things about the actual
executables behavior when it's executed.
So, we can see it's making an HTTP
request for some reason to get the root
certification from apple.com. But we can
see it's also resolving some other DNS
names. And we can see that it's actually
dropping a file. In this case, this
protected_68A4BO.exe file. And lastly,
if we go under the community tab, we can
see some other results. For example, we
have an any run scan here, which shows
that the verdict is malicious. We also
have some other checks here that we can
dive into should we want to. But it's
very safe to say that this file is
indeed
malicious. Another tool that we can use
to perform file reputation checks along
with even IP or URL or domain reputation
checks is Cisco Talos. And Cisco Talos
is a threat intelligence and research
organization operated by Cisco systems
and it specializes in providing advanced
threat intelligence and research and
analysis and other cyber security
services to help protect against a wide
range of cyber threats. And so if we
scroll down here to the intelligence
center, well, we can simply paste in the
SHA 256 file hash of our suspected
malicious
file. So I'll paste in that hash and
click on search.
And if we scroll down here, we can see
much like with Virus Total, this file
has been determined to be malicious. And
we can see very similar detection
aliases that we saw on Virus
Total. Like with all of our checks and
analysis thus far, we always need to
ensure that we're documenting our
findings during the process. So we can
take screenshots of our virus total or
Cisco Telos outputs or even having
reports downloaded are great methods to
ensure the information is not lost. We
can actually copy the links to virus
total scans, but we can't always assume
that these links are going to be
accessible as our only documentation.
So, it's always important to manually
collect this information and even
collect screenshots as much as possible
because of course having strong
documentation in our tickets ensures
that the organization has a clear record
of all of the analysis that we performed
including the files that were checked
and the hashes and of course the
obtained reputation verdicts. And of
course, this documentation is critical
for us when it comes to making verdicts
and taking appropriate actions. For
example, if we find a file to be
malicious and we take defensive actions
to block the sender and perform a deeper
investigation into the user's computer,
well, we need to have documentation in
place to justify why we took these
actions. So, hopefully that was a nice
overview of how we can investigate file
attachments using their reputation from
their hashes. In the next lesson, we'll
look at some more dynamic attachment
analysis and also some sandboxing
capabilities.
So, let's talk a little bit about
dynamic attachment analysis and
sandboxing. And sandboxing is a security
technique used to isolate potentially
harmful files from the rest of our
system. And when it comes to fishing
attachments, well, sandboxing involves
opening the attachment in a controlled
environment separate from the user's
actual system. And this controlled
environment is known as the sandbox. And
it mimics a typical operating system but
ensures that any malicious activity
within the attachment well is contained
and cannot harm our actual computer or
network. And so by using sandboxing and
dynamic analysis tools for fishing
attachments well we can analyze
suspicious files safely and determine if
they contain malware or other threats.
And we can do this by documenting things
like the behavior of the file. And so
typically when we want to perform
dynamic analysis we're looking for four
common things. So the first is the
process activity, right? So what
processes are being spawned and what is
the parent child relationships of these
processes. We also want to look at any
registry changes and so are there maybe
any persistence mechanisms being
executed with the file. You know, is it
writing or overwriting any of the
Windows registry entries? We also want
to look at network connections. So we
want to look at things like what
connections does the file make when it's
executed, right? Is it talking to anyone
on the internet? Is it communicating
with some sort of C2 or command and
control server? And lastly, we want to
of course look at file activity. So, is
it dropping any other files or is it
writing anything to the disk in any way
or modifying any
files? And in the field, you might use
some proprietary tools or dedicated
malware analysis VMs. But for this
lesson, we're going to look into free
online platforms to perform this
analysis for us.
And I'll say if you're interested in
this topic and you want to dive deeper
into building your own malware analysis
lab, well, I can definitely recommend
TCM's practical malware analysis and
triage course produced by Matt Keley or
Husky Hacks. And in that course, well,
you will go through building a malware
analysis lab and doing things like
performing static and dynamic analysis
along with a number of other topics like
decompiling and disassembling malware or
performing shell code analysis and more
advanced maloc analysis as well. And so
I highly recommend that course if you're
interested in going down the route of
malware analysis. And so let's locate
some files that we can use for our
dynamic analysis and sandboxing. And so
let's go into the fishing analysis
folder and head to attachment analysis
and then go into the malware samples
directory. And from here we'll see a
couple of samples of real genuine
malware that we can use for our
analysis. And the first tool that we'll
look at is called hybrid analysis. And
hybrid analysis is a free malware
analysis service that can detect and
analyze malware and is powered by the
CrowdStrike Falcon Sandbox, making it a
very powerful and accessible tool for
analysts to use in the field. And
optionally, you can create an account on
hybrid analysis to unlock some more
features like the Yara search and the
string search functions. Additionally,
you'll unlock some more reporting tools
as well. But for this example, we won't
even need to create an account. And with
the samples that we submit, hybrid
analysis will generate and provide us
with a detailed report about the
observed behavior and activity on the
simulated endpoint. So now that we're on
the hybrid analysis site, we can simply
drag and drop a file for analysis.
Alternatively, we can open up our file
explorer here and I'm just going to
locate this DOCX document or this Word
document. And so I'm going to double
click on that to select it. And you can
see we're presented with some options.
Now, we can enter an email address if
you want to be notified when the
analysis is complete. So, because this
is a free service, well, sometimes
you'll be behind others in the queue and
you'll have to wait a little bit to get
your
report. You can also provide a comment,
which is optional, to basically describe
your sample. Now, I'm just going to
click on this to agree to the terms and
make sure that I'm not a robot. And then
I'll hit
continue. And from here, we get some
more information as well as some options
for our analysis. For example, we can
get the mime type of the file as well as
the SHA 256 hash if we hadn't already.
And interestingly, we can choose what
kind of machine we want to use for our
sandboxing. In this case, I'll leave it
at the default Windows 10 64-bit, but we
can also choose Windows 11 or Windows 7
machines, even Linux, Mac, and Android.
However, I believe you need an account
to use some of these options. And if you
click on runtime options, you can see we
get some more options available to us.
So we can choose a runtime action script
where we can simulate some user
behavior. We can also choose the
duration as well as any custom command
line options or commands that we want to
run when the system
executes. If for example you upload a
file like an office document or PDF that
requires a password prompt, well you can
put that in here. Additionally, if you
upload a password protected zip file,
you can also put in the password. We
also have some other options here, but
I'm just going to go back and keep
everything default.
And I'm simply going to click on
generate public report. And remember,
this is a public report. And anyone in
the community would be able to access
the report and look at things such as
screenshots or even strings that were
extracted from the file itself. So, I'll
stress this again. Make sure we're not
submitting anything here that is
potentially sensitive. And if you're not
sure, it's better to air on the side of
caution and use some of the other
analysis methods that we've covered thus
far. So, I'll click on generate public
report. And we might need to wait for
the report to load, but you can see
already this was classified as
malicious, likely because it's been
reported before. We can also see a
specific CVE number that this file or
this malware was labeled as. And if we
look up the CVE number itself, we can
get some more
information. It appears this CVE affects
a number of Office versions and allows
remote attackers to execute arbitrary
code via a crafted document.
If we scroll down to the antivirus
reports, we can see the Meta Defender
report is currently running. However, we
have a CrowdStrike Falcon report that we
can also look into. And from here, we
can see with 100% confidence the static
analysis and machine learning
capabilities detected this file as
malware. If we scroll down to the Falcon
sandbox reports, well, this is where we
can actually see the dynamic analysis in
action. This is the one that we
submitted on our Windows 10 machine. But
we can see this file was already
analyzed on a Windows 7 machine. And so
while we wait for ours to finish, we can
take a look at this dynamic analysis.
And we can see at a high level there
were 19 malicious indicators. And if we
click on this to view more information,
we'll be taken to the actual report of
this dynamic
analysis. So again, we can see the
result of this analysis was malicious.
While waiting for the report to finish,
I was looking into the CVE number that
we identified. Specifically, it appears
that there's an attack chain that we
could potentially look for in our
report. First, an attacker is going to
target a user with a Word document. And
this Word document is going to have an
OLE2 embedded link object inside of it.
And when the user opens this document,
well, the Microsoft Word executable is
going to issue an HTTP request to the
attacker server to retrieve a malicious
hta file. The file that's returned by
the server is going to be a fake RTF
file with an embedded malicious script.
When Word tries to handle this script,
it's going to inadvertently invoke the
Microsoft HTA application or
MSHTA.exe, which will then execute and
run the embedded malicious script. And
in this medium link, which I'll have
linked down below, we can see a more
visual representation of this attack
chain. So, with that in mind, let's
return to our report and see if we can
identify any of those indicators. Right
off the bat, of course, we can see that
this was identified as malicious. Now,
we could technically write off our
report here and be fairly confident that
this was a malicious file. And if it was
attached to an email, well, we could be
very confident that that was a fish and
respond appropriately. However, let's
look into this report in more detail so
we can understand its components. If we
scroll down, we can immediately look
into those 19 malicious
indicators. Starting out, we can see we
identified some exploit or shell code
that was related to that CVE number. And
if we scroll down some more, well, this
starts making more sense. We can see
that the sample executed some get
requests to download files from a web
server. Specifically, we can see the
request itself. We can see the host,
which was potentially the attacker's
command and control server or the server
that they were hosting the second stage
of the malware on. We can also see the
URL
itself. If we scroll down to the get
line, we can see the actual file that
was downloaded, this doc file, which in
the case of the attack chain we
identified, this is most likely the fake
RTF file, which has the embedded
malicious script.
If we scroll down some more, we can
identify that the file spawned a number
of processes, which is definitely
something we want to look into. And
specifically, we can see that the file
spawned a number of PowerShell
processes, which is very suspicious. A
Microsoft Word file should not be
spawning
PowerShell.exe. We can see that the
malware is attempting to configure
Windows Defender to exclude specific
file paths from its scanning and
protection mechanisms. Likely this is an
attempt at AV evasion. And we can see
the two executables that were excluded
from scanning. And this is very useful
for our notes. And under these
processes, we can see another one here
which appears to be a potential
persistence mechanism. In this case, we
can see that a new scheduled task was
created using the Windows taskuler
executable. And specifically, we're
seeing the same name here that we
identified earlier. If we scroll down
some more, we can get to the screenshots
section. And in this section, we can see
some actual screenshots that were taken
on the sandbox machine itself as it was
executing the file. And if we scroll
through these, we might get a better
idea of what actions were performed on
the
sandbox. Specifically, we can see that
Microsoft Windows was opened, but the
file appears to be
blank. If we go under the network
analysis section, we can see some DNS
requests that were made. Specifically,
we have these two domains here, which
appear to be the attacker's command and
control server and potentially the
server that was hosting the stage two of
the malware. In this case, TT.VG is in
fact yet another URL shortening service
that the attacker seems to be leveraging
to disguise a malicious
URL. And we can also see the IP
addresses of these domains along with
some additional information like the
register and the country they belong to.
And in line with the attack chain we
identified, it appears that the Winword
or the Microsoft Word executable was in
fact making those HTTP requests over
port 80 and 443. And it was making these
requests to that TT.VG domain which we
identified was hosting the fake RTF file
that had the embedded malicious script.
Under HTTP traffic, we can see the
actual request that was made to the web
server. Specifically after some
redirects, it appears to be this request
here as we can identify by the same file
name in the
URL. If we go to the extracted file
section and scroll
down, we can in fact identify that fake
RTF
file. We can even take that SHA 256 hash
and head over to Virus Total for more
analysis. If we paste in the hash and
run the scan, well, we can immediately
see that over half of these security
vendors flagged this file as malicious.
Now, that was quite a bit of
information, but the main thing that we
can take from this is just the large
amount of malicious indicators that we
found. And so, it's no question that
this file is malicious. And if it was
attached to an email, well, we can
definitely write the email off as
fishing and respond
appropriately. Now, we also have Joe
Sandbox. And Joe Sandbox is a very
powerful malware analysis engine. And it
allows us to analyze files on Windows or
Mac and even Android operating systems.
But unfortunately, Joe Sandbox requires
us to register with a business email and
they will manually verify your account.
And so because of this restriction, I'll
quickly showcase it here, but we'll
stress that hybrid analysis is a much
more accessible option. But fortunately,
with a business email account, we can
access the Joe Sandbox cloud basic tier,
which limits a number of configuration
options such as custom commands or
browsers and network options, but we'll
still have access to some really useful
features. For example, I'm going to
upload the same file that we've been
using. And scrolling down, I can select
the analysis system. And we have access
to Windows 10 or Windows 7. For this
case, I'll just leave it on Windows 10.
And now we have this option for live
interaction. And this will allow us to
dynamically interact with the sandbox as
needed. And so I'll check this off to
demonstrate. And I'm also going to check
off generate deep analysis report after
execution. Now we can enter some
settings here like we can add a comment
and change the execution runtime. And we
can click here to show the advanced
settings. So, we can do things like
turning off internet access, which we
don't really want to do. And so, I'll
just leave everything as default. And
before we analyze here, remember once
again, anything we submit here is going
to be published and accessible to
anyone. And anyone will be able to
download the sample as well as look at
the screenshots. If we want to run
private scans, well, we're going to need
to pay. And so, with that in mind, let's
click on analyze with Joe Sandbox, and
it'll give us that warning once again.
And so right now our sandbox machine is
booting
up and you can see it's opened up to the
Microsoft Word
document and we can interact with this
sandbox, right? So I can close it and
reopen it. And you can see already we're
getting a number of signatures and IPs
detected. So I'll wait for the report to
finish to start looking at these. But
just note that this is an interactive
environment. I can type whatever I want.
And this is very useful if we're dealing
with embedded files or objects or
scripts within a Word document, for
example. And we can dynamically interact
with the document and click on any links
that we need to or download any files
from a Google Drive, for example. And so
this is why sandboxing is so useful for
us as a sock analyst if you're trying to
do more deep
investigation. And so I think we've let
this run for long enough. So I'm just
going to hit stop in the top right
here. And now Joe Sandbox is going to
generate that deep malware analysis
report for us. But we can already see
some interesting things here.
Specifically under signatures, well, we
can find a number of malicious
identified signatures. If we look in the
IP section, well, we can see some IP
addresses that were contacted.
Specifically, we have three down here
that were identified as clean. These are
most likely normal Microsoft IP
addresses. However, we have the same 172
address that we identified earlier as
malicious.
Under domains, we can see that TT.VG
domain that once again was identified as
malicious. And we can even see the URL
that was hosting the second stage of the
malware. So after a few minutes, the
report is finished and ready for us to
take a look
at. And we can see immediately the file
itself was identified as
malicious. And if we look down, we can
start to see some IoC's, specifically
the IP address and the domain.
If we click on full report here, as the
name suggests, we get a full report of
everything that was detected and
run. If we scroll down, we can
immediately see all of the signatures
that were detected. The red means that
it was most likely malicious. Under the
detection, well, we can see that there
was a 100% confidence rate that this was
a malicious file. And we get some more
general information like the sample
name, the hashes, and the screenshots
from the execution.
You can see this was everything that we
performed when we were in the
sandbox. Now, I'm not going to go into
this report with the same amount of
detail that I did with hybrid analysis
because we should see many similar
things here. So, at a high level, it's
just important to note that there are
other sandboxing tools out there like
Joe
Sandbox. Speaking of other tools, well,
the last one I'll quickly cover here is
called Any Run. And like with Joe
Sandbox, in order to use the free
version, well, you need to sign up for
an account. And unfortunately, you do
need a business email in order to sign
up for an account. And so, as such, you
don't really need to follow along here.
I'm just going to showcase how to
quickly start and run a scan. And as
mentioned earlier, I would definitely
recommend hybrid analysis due to its
accessibility. And any run is an
interactive malware analysis sandbox
that allows us to provide things like
URLs or files or even email files. And
it will dynamically investigate and
extract things like IoC's and look at
behavior. And because it's interactive,
well, we can actually interact with the
sandbox like we could with Joe sandbox.
And so our options are going to be
severely throttled and limited with the
free version. But I'll quickly showcase
how we can analyze a file. And it's also
important to note that anything we
upload, well, we'll be publicly
available. If we look at public reports
here, we can see all of the public
submissions from other users. And so
even if you don't have an account and
you're interested in seeing what the
report looks like, well, you can go
through the public submissions here and
you can even search based on hashes or
tags if you're interested in a specific
sample. But to start our own analysis,
I'm just going to click on analyze files
here. And as you guessed, I'm going to
pick the same files so we can compare
the different
services. So I'm going to select this
bank payment
document, which will open up this new
analysis window. And from here, I'm just
going to click on pro mode so we can see
all of the options. And now we can
choose a number of different things. For
example, we can change the start object
from where the sample is executed. By
default, it will be the temp directory,
which I'll leave it at, but we can also
choose things like the desktop or the
user's home directory. We can change
some network settings. For example, we
can completely disable the network from
the sandbox. However, since we're
analyzing malware and want to see those
network connections, well, I'm going to
leave it connected. And note under
privacy here we only have the public
option. If we were on a higher tier or a
business plan or an enterprise plan, we
would be able to run private scans.
Under operating system here on the free
tier, we only have access to Windows 7.
So I'll leave it at that. And so with
these selections, I'm just going to
click on run a public analysis. And it's
going to give us a warning that this is
of course a public task. So I'm going to
click I agree. And it's going to start
up the sandbox for us. So you can see
our sandbox and our dynamic analysis VM
is starting to boot up and we can see in
the preview window here it's currently
opening Microsoft Word and we can
interact with this machine. For example,
I can click on the start menu here and I
can start clicking on any of these
applications. But I'll just let it do
its thing and open up
Word. Similar to Joe Sandbox, we can see
under here some of the OC's. We can see
some connections that are being made. We
can see some DNS requests. for example,
this TT.VG domain, what we're quite
accustomed to
seeing. And so once our sample is
complete after that minute, we can look
at the full report. Specifically, we can
start with looking at some of the IoC's
that were detected. And so we're getting
the hashes of the file itself along with
the DNS requests. And you can see here
that this domain has been identified as
malicious, which of course we've already
found out. We can see the IP addresses
of the connections along with the URLs
that were contacted as well. So
specifically, this was the URL that we
identified previously was hosting the
second stage of the
malware. And so as you can tell, we're
getting a number of the same information
and the same classifications. For
example, this of course has been
identified as a malicious file. But
anyone can provide us some very useful
reports that we can download and put
into our documentation. If we click on
text report here, it's going to take us
to this full report of all the behavior
and activity that it analyzed. And if we
wanted to, we could click on the print
option here and save this as a PDF. And
this would be very useful to include in
our report or documentation. And just to
very quickly cover this report, but we
can see very quickly under the tags
here, we're getting that same CVE
number. We're also getting the file
hashes as well. But as we scroll down,
you will see a number of interesting
sections within this report like the
behavior activities or the screenshots
from the report itself and all of the
processes that were captured along with
this behavior
graph. We also of course get things like
registry
activity and file
activity and of course network activity
as well.
And like with all the tools and
solutions we've looked at in this
lesson, they all provided us with very
interesting information and also gave us
a verdict on the malicious activity of
the file we
submitted. And just to wrap up, like I
said before, sandboxing is a very useful
technique for us and it can really allow
us to do some deeper analysis on files
that we haven't been able to determine
are malicious or not. And through using
interactive sandboxing tools, we can do
interesting things like safely download
files or browse through malicious URLs.
And so I'll leave it with the sentiment
that dynamic analysis and sandboxing is
always going to be a very useful tool in
your arsenal, but it should never be the
only thing that you rely on. And so I
hope this was a good introduction into
some of the options out
there. Before we dive into our next
section, I just want to again thank our
sponsor for this video, Flare Academy.
Cyber threats are evolving fast and
staying ahead is not just an advantage,
it's a necessity and that's where Flare
Academy comes in. Flare Academy is an
educational hub designed to democratize
cyber security knowledge. Backed by the
Flair research team and leading threat
intelligence experts, they provide
accessible training, collaborative
discussions, and cutting edge resources.
With the support of Flair's
industry-leading research team, members
gain access to hands-on insights and
training while connecting with peers and
experts to tackle the toughest and
newest challenges together. This is
through practical sessions designed to
solve real world cyber security
challenges. The opportunity to engage
with industry leaders, researchers, and
fellow professionals to grow your
skills, community meetups to share
insights and experiences in both virtual
and in-person events, and exclusive
research and tools such as access to
cutting edge reports, tooling, and
intelligence from Flair's experts
tailored specifically for the community.
With Flare, you can learn and grow
through in-depth training sessions on
credential management, reconnaissance
techniques, OSENT, and much more.
Delivered by industry leaders like Jason
Hadex, and backed by Flair's research
team, you'll get exclusive access to
expertly crafted solutions, playbooks,
and session materials designed to
address real world cyber security
challenges. You'll be able to
participate in expert-led discussions
and Q&A channels and stay ahead of
emerging threats with exclusive reports,
feeds, and insights from Flair's
comprehensive cyber crime intelligence.
And verified members gain access to
premium resources and private insights
while contributing to a community that
thrives on shared knowledge. And so, if
you're ready to level up, join Flare
Academy today through the link in the
description.
Now let's take a very basic look into
performing static analysis on malicious
office documents or malocs. And I really
mean a basic analysis. I don't want to
turn this into a malware analysis
course. For that expertise, I would once
again suggest the practical malware
analysis and triage course by Husky
Hacks. And even performing some of this
analysis is a bit of an overstep and
most likely not something you'll have to
do in the field. However, I still think
a basic analysis of Malddocks can fit
nicely into this section because you
will definitely come across malocs or
macro enabled word files or Excel files
very often in the field. You know, if we
think about the ubiquity of office
software, we have tools like Word and
Excel and PowerPoint. And while this
ubiquity is a gold mine for attackers to
try to exploit due to the number of
organizations and businesses that use
them daily. And so a maloc is short for
a malicious document as you probably
suspected. And it refers to a weaponized
document file such as a word document or
an Excel spreadsheet or even a PDF that
has been crafted and modified to carry
out malicious activities when it's
opened. And so commonly this is done
through things like macros embedded in
the file or different embedded objects.
And so macros are scripts that are
embedded into these Office documents
that can be programmed to execute a
series of commands automatically. And so
when a user opens a document and enables
the macros, well, these scripts can run
without further interaction. And macros
are a legitimate and powerful tool that
can be used to automate repetitive tasks
in these files. However, of course, this
power can also be exploited to run
system commands. And attackers can write
malicious macros to perform things like
downloading and executing malware or
stealing data or altering system
settings or even providing remote
access. And since a lot of end users
might not fully understand the
implications of enabling macros, well,
they can quite easily be tricked into
enabling them and allowing this
malicious code to run. And VBA or Visual
Basic for applications is typically the
language used to write these embedded
macros. And so to effectively analyze
Malddox, well, we can combine various
static and dynamic analysis techniques.
And of course, in the previous lesson,
you learned how to dynamically analyze
samples in an online sandbox. And this
is typically as far as you're going to
need to go. But in this lesson, we'll
quickly look at a simple utility or tool
that can carve through these Office
documents and find potentially malicious
embedded content. And ultimately though,
no matter our method, well, our goal is
going to be to determine, of course, if
the document contains malware and if we
can extract specific indicators of
compromise like IPs or URLs or domain
names or even specific scripts that we
can then use to fuel our team's threat
intelligence and detection capabilities.
And because we're going to keep it
short, I'm going to introduce you to one
simple tool called OLED dump.py. And you
might recognize this repository because
it's part of the Dier Steven suite of
tools that are very useful for analyzing
these types of files. And previously we
used the email dump.py script to extract
attachments from emails through our
terminal. And this script will be linked
down below, but I have also included it
in the tools folder. And so what does
OLE mean, right? Well, OLE stands for
object linking and embedding. And it's a
technology developed by Microsoft that
allows embedding and linking to
documents and other objects. And so, OLE
is used in all of these different
Microsoft Office applications like Word
and Excel and PowerPoint to embed
objects like spreadsheets or charts or
images. And so, you can think about how
you're able to embed or link Excel
charts or tables and other objects into
Word documents or within a PowerPoint
presentation. Well, OLE is the
underlying technology that makes all of
that possible. And OLED dump.py will
allow us to dig into this embedded media
and look at different properties and
components that make up the document.
And so to get started, let's navigate to
the MALDOC analysis folder. And from
here, we can see an attachment with
axlsm file extension. And this extension
is typically a macro enabled Excel
document. And in this case, we suspect
that it might have a malicious VBA
script embedded inside of it. And so
it's honestly quite simple to use this
tool. I'm just going to call Python 3
and back out into our tools directory to
find that OLED dump.py script. And from
here I'm just going to provide the
sample name. And a lot of work has
already been done for us. So you can see
that OLE dump kind of carved into this
file and assigned indexes or data
streams that relate to different
portions or sections of the document.
And again to keep things concise, well
we can see this capital M here. And this
means that there is an embedded macro in
this specific index stream. And so now
that we know the stream is this fourth
index here, well, we can run this
command again and specify the fourth
stream. And that might be hard to see
because it's cut off, but that's just a
tac s with the number four. And so if I
run that, well, we're now getting an
entire hex dump of that macro. So these
are the raw
bytes. And of course, this is pretty
hard to read on its own, but we can
almost start to make out some
interesting things. For example, we have
an HTTP protocol here, apparently going
to some sort of IP address and some URL.
So, let's look at this in more detail.
What we can do is append to our command
the capital S flag. And this is like
running strings against the file or the
macro. So, if we run this, well, we've
started to extract some strings. And
again, this also isn't super interesting
to read, but we can see some things like
the invoke web request. And if you're
familiar with PowerShell, well, this is
a way to make a request to a URL. And we
can see the URL or the URI here. And
again, it looks like there is an IP
address with a file
extension. Now, the final command we'll
run, let's take out that capital S and
run something to actually attempt to
extract the entire VBA script. So, with
that, we'll do two dashes and then we'll
type in
VBA decompress corrupt. And it's an odd
name, but if we run this, we should
extract the full VBA script. And you can
see we've done that
here. And in this case, this is the
interesting
OC using the invoke web request
function. Well, it's making a request to
this URL. And this URL is simply an IP
address that of course we can do IP
lookups on. And we can actually see it's
downloading an executable file. And then
through this start process command,
well, it's actually executing the file
that it downloaded. And so in summary,
this macro is designed to run a hidden
PowerShell command that will download
and execute a file from this URL. And of
course, we can infer the overall intent
here is likely to run some sort of
malicious code and executable on the
user's machine without their knowledge
because this will run in the background
when the file is
opened. And so I'll admit this kind of
static analysis is a bit out of scope
for the course. You know, it's doubtful
that you'll be expected to do this kind
of analysis on the job. And you're
typically much better off simply
analyzing file hashes and performing
dynamic sandboxing as necessary. But I
thought it would be very interesting to
include a quick demo here because it's
such an easy script to demonstrate and
it's really a good foray to those who
are interested in more in-depth malware
analysis. Along with malicious office
documents, well, one of the most
prevalent attachmentbased threats that
you'll encounter as a sock analyst is
malicious PDFs. And similar to the
previous lesson, we're not going to do a
full curriculum on static malware
analysis. However, I think that
understanding the composition and
structure of PDFs along with some simple
tools that we can use to dig and carve
into them to find anomalies and embedded
content can benefit your overall
comprehension when it comes to analyzing
attachments. To be honest, in most
cases, attackers don't even go as far as
to embed malicious content within PDF
files themselves. I would argue that the
most common technique that I've seen in
the field involves simply containing a
clickable URL within a PDF file that
then leads to a malicious web page or
drive by download. And the reason why an
attacker would use a PDF to send a
simple payload like a URL is due to
things like user trust and familiarity
and potentially the ability to evade
email filters. For example, most
organizations will allow for PDF
attachments since it's so widely used
across organizations for a number of
different business purposes like
invoices or forms or policies. And as
such, users are very accustomed to
receiving PDFs and will typically trust
them more than any other file type since
they interact with them daily.
Additionally, email gateways and email
security technology may not have the
capacity to open up the documents
themselves and statically analyze or
extract any URLs within the content
itself. So it becomes an easy payload
delivery option leaving organizations to
rely on their EDR or web proxy or
network traffic analysis solutions. And
just as an example, let's go into the
Malddock analysis folder and then into
the PDF directory. And I'm just going to
open up
statement.pdf. And this for example is
what one of these PDFs might look like.
And so you can see here we have some
communication impersonating Amazon. And
with a common pretext that we've seen so
far, it appears there's been some
unusual activity on our account and our
account has been placed on hold. And the
main point of this PDF is to get the
user to click on this link here, which
most likely leads to or is led to a
credential capture page. And for
example, we can get the hash value of
this
file. And as we're used to doing
already, well, we can search for this on
something like virus total.
In this case, it doesn't appear that
there were any matches found for this
PDF document. And so, what should we do
now? Well, assuming we never opened up
this document, well, we can still open
it up and carve into the file via the
command line. And there are ways for us
to extract any embedded URLs or files or
scripts directly from the terminal. And
one of these tools that we'll start with
is called PDF parser.py. And it is part
of that Dier Steven suite. And it's
designed to parse and analyze the
structure of PDF files. It allows us to
inspect the contents and extract or
analyze embedded objects or search for
specific elements. And by doing this, we
can detect any potential malicious
content. And so, let's run this tool on
the file. And you'll find it within the
tools directory. And for the argument,
I'm just going to simply provide the
name of the file. And so we can get a
better output, I'm going to pipe this
over to the more command so we can
scroll through the results. And as we
run this command, well, we can
immediately see some interesting
information. And so PDF parser is going
to carve through the file and extract
any of the objects found in the makeup
of the PDF itself. In this case, this
first object here was able to extract a
link in the form of a URI. And
specifically, we were able to extract
the exact URI that we found when we
opened up the file. And so, of course,
this is a useful IC for us. And although
we didn't get a hit on virus total for
the files hash, well, I'm going to copy
this URL and see if we can find anything
about its reputation using this web
artifact.
And so I'm just going to paste it in
here and hit run. And when doing that,
we can see that at least one of 94
security vendors flagged this URL as
malicious. And we can see in this one
example, it was flagged as fishing. And
so I would typically expect to see more
here. But given the fact that it's using
a legitimate Google service and it was
probably taken down quite quickly, well,
we don't have many results to go off of.
But being able to extract and analyze
the URL itself instead of just the file
hash gave us a bit more to go off of. So
let's look at another example here. In
this case, we can look at the book04
PDF. And in this example, it appears the
attacker is using a blurred image to
make it look like there's a PDF on the
other side of this download link. And of
course, we can extract the URL from the
PDF itself. But we can also do it
through safer means in which we don't
need to actually open up a PDF
viewer. In this case, I'll run PDF
parser again and provide that book file.
we do end up getting a lot of
information. But since we're looking for
a URL, or rather a URI, what we can do
is make a slight modification to the
command. We can add the S flag to search
for a specific object. In this case, I'm
going to search for /
URI. And you can see we were able to
pull back this URI object specifically
with the URL itself.
And so once again, if I copy this URL
and take it over to Virus
Total, I can paste it in and do a
search. And in this case, we have two
instances of vendors flagging this URL
as malicious, which gives us a bit more
to go off of. And remember, I'm just
using Virus Total here for a short
example. But as discussed in the URL
analysis section, well, there are so
many tools that we can use at this point
to analyze the reputation of URLs and
domains.
And so that was just two quick examples
of how we can extract and identify any
URLs embedded inside of a PDF without
having to open it in any PDF viewer.
Now, let's talk about PDFs that can be a
little more sinister and actually
contain things like embedded malware or
scripts or even
documents. Well, in this case, we'll use
this example to go off of. And this is a
test PDF file developed by Dier Stevens
that we can use to test some of the
tools like PDF parser or PDF ID, which
I'll cover next. And PDF ID is a
lightweight tool that can scan a PDF
file and provide a highle overview of
its structure. And in doing this, we can
of course identify any suspicious
elements or objects that shouldn't be
there like JavaScript or embedded files
and other open actions. And so it's
quite simple to run. I'm just going to
call Python 3 and go back into the tools
directory and call PDF ID.py. And then
I'll simply provide the name of the file
as the argument.
And in this case, we get a very easy to
read output of all of the components and
objects that make up this PDF file. And
as I mentioned, there are a couple of
objects that we typically want to look
out for when analyzing a PDF. For
example, we want to look for any
JavaScript or JS objects, which would
indicate that the PDF contains embedded
JavaScript. And we can see that this
file has both JS and JavaScript objects.
And these embedded scripts can be used
to potentially steal data or make
connections to an attacker's server or
attempt to start and execute external
programs on the victim's system itself.
We also want to look for any open
actions, which we can see this file has
one. And open actions can potentially
cause the PDF reader itself to take some
sort of action when opening the file.
And we also want to look at any launch
objects. Again, this could be used to
potentially launch some external
software when the PDF is opened. And of
course, we want to look for any embedded
files. In this case, we can see that
there is an embedded file. It's possible
for an attacker to embed malicious files
like macro enabled word documents or
malware into the objects of the PDF
itself. And so, we can use PDF parser to
extract the embedded files contained in
the PDF and also look at any embedded
scripts. And so, I'm just going to call
PDF
parser and provide the name of the
file. And again, I'm going to pipe it to
the more command. So we can scroll
through the output. And so we can see
this first object here, this catalog
object is referencing a file called EIC
dropper. And this is probably the
embedded file. But we can continue
scrolling through this output to find
the actual object that contains the
file. As we scroll through, we can see
object 7 here, this filespec object is
making another reference to this doc
file. And we can see object 8 here
actually refers to the embedded file
object. And so we can see the file's
data stream along with its length. And
so we can actually extract this file.
But first let's take a look at object 9.
In this case it appears to be the
embedded JavaScript. And it's telling
the PDF viewer to execute JavaScript
code when the action is triggered. And
it appears to be attempting to launch
the dropper document. And so let's go
ahead and extract the file. And of
course we can do this through PDF parser
itself. So I'm going to rerun the same
command here but I'm going to provide
some additional
arguments. For example, we identified
that the object containing the embedded
file is object 8. And so let's provide
that using the double dash and then
object argument. Next we can see that
the file itself has been encoded. And so
we can provide the filter flag to decode
the data stream. We also want to provide
the raw flag to display the output in
raw format.
but we don't want to display it to our
terminal. So lastly, we want to provide
the dump
option and save it to a file. In this
case, I will call it the same name that
we've identified through the file
itself. And so with all of that set, I'm
just going to hit
run. And we can see that the file was
decoded. If I run an ls, we can see the
eicar dropper.doc. And if I run the file
command on this file, we can see that
it's a composite document file version 2
document. And this is an older Microsoft
Office document format that can contain
embedded macros. And so since we've
extracted a doc file, well, we can
perform similar actions that we did in
the previous lesson to look for any
embedded macros or malicious scripts
inside the document. And if you
remember, we use ole dump.py to do that.
And so just as a quick example, I can
run it against the file where we can
identify the module one macro on the
seventh index identified by the capital
M. And so I'll leave you to do any
further analysis on this macro if you'd
like. But at a high level, we covered
some various methodologies and tools
that we can use to either extract URLs
from PDFs or extract any embedded media
or scripts. And similar to the previous
lesson, checking the files hash
reputation and potentially performing
any dynamic analysis is typically the
quicker and easier option in the field.
And you'll typically not be required to
go in depth into static analysis or even
perform static analysis at all in the
day-to-day. But I thought it would be
interesting to include some basic
methodologies and syntax within this
section. And so I hope you
enjoyed. Now, wouldn't it be great if we
could expedite the fishing analysis and
triage process with some automated
extraction and enrichment and analysis?
Well, we've covered some tools and
scripts already that can simplify the
artifact collection process. But is
there some sort of magic solution out
there that can take all of the manual
effort off of our shoulders? Well, I
wouldn't say it's a magical solution,
but in this lesson, I want to introduce
you to fish tool, which is a web-based
fishing analysis solution that allows
analysts and researchers to quickly and
automatically analyze and categorize
emails and generate investigation
reports. And so, using fish tool, we can
gather contextual analysis of email
metadata and URLs and attachments and
quickly turn those into actionable
findings.
And now there is an enterprise edition
of fish tool. But fortunately we can do
all of the analysis we need using the
free tool. And so I'll have this site
linked down below. And so we can just
click on get fish tool now for free. And
of course this is going to require an
account. So we can just sign up here.
And fortunately we don't need a business
email account. So you can use any Gmail
or Yahoo or Hotmail account that you
want. And once we're signed in here you
can see we're taken to this dashboard.
And once we start uploading some emails
to analyze, well, this is going to start
getting filled up with interesting
charts and graphs. But we can start by
analyzing our first email. So we can
either head over to the analysis section
here or just click on this blue analyze
button. And upon doing that, you can see
we can drag and drop an email or we can
just click on choose file to select one
from our explorer window. And from here,
I'm just going to go into the fishing
analysis section and go to the header
analysis. And from here, I'm just going
to select sample one. And if you
remember that was the Chase Bank
Fish. And so it's going to upload. And
you can see we immediately have a number
of useful indicators. On the right hand
side, well, we can see a rendered
version of the email. If we click on
HTML, we can see the actual HTML markup
that makes up the content or the body
content of this email. If we click on
source, we can get the full source of
the email file, which is what we were
looking at when we opened it up in
Sublime Text. And on the left hand side
here we can see some interesting
artifacts that were automatically
collected from the email. For example,
we have the subject line at the top. We
have the from and the to header. We have
the timestamp of the email. We have the
reply to and the return path along with
the originating IP and the RDNS or the
reverse DNS. If you remember, this is
the resolve host field that we were
looking at when we were doing the IP
lookup. In this case, Fish Tool
conveniently did this lookup for us. And
we can see the proton mail address. Now
you'll notice some exclamation marks
next to reply to and return path. If we
click on the exclamation mark, we can
get some more details as to why this was
flagged. And of course, this immediately
highlighted that the reply to email
address is inconsistent with the from
header, which of course is something
suspicious that we should keep in
mind. The same deal if we look at the
return path, we can see that the domain
name proton.me is inconsistent with the
chase.com domain from the from address.
If we click on the received lines tab,
we can get all of the different hops or
the MTAs that the message traversed
through on its way from the source to
the destination. And these are all
extracted from the received headers. We
can see we get the timestamp and the
mail server that sent it and received
it. In this case, we can get the IP
address of the original mail server,
which was of course that
proton.ch. This tab makes it really easy
for us to look through each of these
hops. under the X headers. This is going
to specifically extract any of those
extended or custom headers. You can see
we get the X sender IP under here as
well. Under security, we also have some
additional flags. We can see that SPF
has passed because the resolved host was
proton.ch which matched the originating
IP. However, if we scroll down, we can
see that demark had failed because of
the spoofing attempt of chase.com. If
there were any attachments on this
email, well, we would see them in the
attachments tab. However, we can go over
to message URLs where we will
conveniently find that
DSGO.TO
address. Now, fish tool can even do
things like integrate virus total.
However, to configure this, we need to
generate a virus total API key. I'm not
going to show going through that in this
lesson, but that is something you can do
if you're interested. This will allow
you to get virus total insights on any
attachments and URLs and file hashes all
from the same console. Once we've
identified that a email is malicious or
clean, well, we can click on resolve
here. And in this case, we can edit the
email disposition to
malicious. If we click on flagged
artifacts, we can choose why we decided
that this email was malicious. Of
course, in this email, it was the return
path and reply to indicating that this
was likely spoofed. We also have this
URL which was using a URL shortener
service to offiscate a malicious link.
Under classification codes, we can
choose what techniques the attacker
used. In this case, we know there was
definitely spoofing going on. And if the
URL was still live, potentially
credential harvesting as well. And from
here, we can just click on resolve to of
course resolve this
email. And when we return to our
dashboard, well, we can start to see
some metrics are being filled in. Let's
quickly analyze one with an attachment.
So in this case, I'm going to go back to
our fishing analysis folder and go under
attachment analysis. In this case, I'll
choose sample one that had that
malicious quotation
attachment. In this case, we don't need
to go through every section, but let's
go under the attachments tab. In this
case, you can see it automatically
extracted the file name along with the
associated hashes. If we had our Virus
Total API key configured, well, we would
obviously get the result here that the
file is malicious. In this case, we can
just copy one of these hashes and
manually head over to Virus Total. I
just wanted to showcase that it's also
able to extract attachments along with
URLs. So, I hope that was a very
interesting look into a powerful tool
that we can use to automate some of the
manual work. And I can't say for sure
that you're going to be using fish tool
in your sock, but it is definitely a
useful resource to have in your arsenal
to save a lot of time.
So far, we've done a fantastic job at
identifying and analyzing fishing
incidents. However, let's think back to
the sock and its role and recall that
the last step in the key functions of
security operations is to respond to
incidents quickly and effectively. Now,
what would any of our in-depth analysis
and investigation be for if we did not
appropriately respond to fishing
incidents and take defensive actions to
mitigate their impact and prevent future
ones? And we can break down the
defensive measures we take into either
reactive, so occurring as the result of
us identifying and analyzing a fishing
incident, or proactive, so using what
we've learned from our analysis to
proactively improve our detection and
security operations. And so in this
lesson, let's focus on the reactive
defense measures. And specifically,
these are measures that we want to take
in order to address and resolve the
incident and minimize the risk of the
malicious email that we identified
arriving in employee inboxes. And
assuming through our analysis we've
already identified and classified an
email as a fishing attempt, we typically
want to take the following reactive
response actions. And these response
actions will typically follow the
classic incident response framework
after the detection and analysis phase.
And we'll cover these in much more
detail within the IR section of this
course. But at a high level, we want to
first think about containment
strategies. So, as mentioned, after
we've detected and analyzed the fishing
incident, well, we'll need to perform
some containment actions. And this
involves taking immediate steps to
isolate the fishing threat and prevent
it from spreading further within the
organization. So, the first thing here
is we want to determine the scope. And
for example, was this an email that was
just sent to a single user or was it
sent to an entire department or team?
And also, was this a thirdparty
contractor that rarely uses their email
account or was it a high-ranking
executive with access to critical
systems and sensitive information? And
so understanding these details is
essential as they really directly impact
the severity and potential consequence
of the fishing attempt. And we can
determine the scope either at the email
header level. So, you know, where we're
looking into the recipient or the carbon
copy headers, and through these headers
attempt to determine all of the users
who receive the email. However, it's
often more efficient and effective to
perform this kind of scope analysis at
the email gateway level. And so within a
Microsoft environment, we can typically
utilize the message trace functionality
to determine the scope of an email
message. And so using the artifacts we
collected during our analysis stage,
things like the sender's email address
or the timestamp or even the subject
line, well, we can easily identify all
the recipients and copied recipients of
an email. And the exact steps and
procedures will be different depending
on your organization's infrastructure
and tooling of course. For example, in a
Google or a G Suite environment, we can
utilize the email log search feature for
the same
purpose. But no matter the tool, the
methodology remains the same with the
same objectives of using artifacts that
we previously identified to narrow down
our search and find every recipient of
an email. And so now that we've
identified the scope of the fishing
incident, the next important step in the
containment process is to prevent
further spread and mitigate potential
damage. And one effective containment
strategy here is quarantining. And so to
quarantine involves isolating suspicious
or potentially malicious emails or files
or attachments and prevent them from
reaching end users inboxes or systems.
And in both Microsoft and Google
environments, we can utilize the native
quarantine features to isolate fishing
emails and associated attachments.
And so next we can get into blocking
specific artifacts. And so at this stage
we've likely identified a malicious
sender, a sender who is most likely
related to an ongoing fishing campaign.
And as such, we need to ensure that we
prevent future fishing attempts from
reaching users inboxes. And we can use
various strategies to block sender
artifacts, including things like
blocking specific email addresses or
domains or IPs or even subject lines of
the email itself. And all of these
artifacts that I just mentioned should
have already been collected during our
triage and analysis stage. And so again,
we can block things like the specific
email address, but that might be less
effective against sophisticated
attackers who can frequently change
their email address or use disposable
mailboxes. Or we can just block entire
domains, and that of course can be an
effective strategy, but we need to be
careful because it might lead to
collateral damage, especially if the
attacker is using a legitimate service.
We could block the IP address of the
mail server. But again, we have to be
very careful here. Attackers can easily
change their IP address or use a
different mail server. And of course, we
could block the subject line of the
email, but of course, that's very easy
to change. And I mentioned being
cautious around blocking entire domains.
And so, you can imagine identifying a
fishing email that used genuine Gmail or
Outlook as its email infrastructure.
Well, you can't just go ahead and block
gmail.com or outlook.com. Of course,
blocking legitimate domains like these
can lead to a number of false positives
and also disrupt business operations.
And quite honestly, people are not going
to be very happy with you, especially
the IT support staff when they start
getting thousands of requests as to why
their emails aren't sending. So, just to
give you a bit of an example on how a
sock analyst may go about creating rules
to block certain artifacts. Well, I've
spun up a Microsoft Exchange email
server in a lab environment just so we
can go through some of the UI and the
different options you might have to
create rules. And by all means, you do
not have to follow along here. It's more
so just a demonstration for you to
watch. If you are curious, you can look
up any tutorial out there on how to set
up an Exchange server, but I won't cover
how to do it in this course because it
takes a bit of time to set up and won't
really be relevant to other sections
that we'll cover here. And this will be
quite similar to what you see in an
Exchange online environment or a
Microsoft 365 environment as well. And
so, let's think about how to block an
email address. For example, maybe we've
identified a fishing attempt that has
clearly come from a malicious mailbox or
sender. Well, in an Exchange
environment, we can go over to the
mailflow tab and then into rules. And
mailflow rules are created to define
specific actions that should be taken on
email messages based on defined
conditions. And so these conditions can
be based on the message content or
sender or recipient and other attributes
as well. And this section is where
administrators and security staff can
create and manage and modify the
mailflow rules, also known as transport
rules that apply to these email
messages. And so to create a rule, we
can just click on this plus tab here and
click on create a new rule. And from
here, we can start defining the
conditions of our rule. And so for the
name, I'm just going to put in an
example name. But in my experience in
the sock, we would typically categorize
and set up more generic rules like email
address block or domain block or IP
block. And within these separate rules,
well, anytime we identified a malicious
artifact that matched one of these
categories, like an IP or a domain,
well, we would add it to this rule. We
would modify and add it along to the
rule instead of creating separate rules
for every, you know, identifier or
sender that we discover. And so it all
depends on the workflow and how you want
to categorize and keep things organized.
But in this case, let me zoom out a
little bit here. Uh we can select apply
this rule if and this is going to give
us the
conditions. And so in our case, we're
looking to match a sender, right? But
you can see we can also match on
different things like the actual
recipient of the email or where the
sender is located. So we can actually
take a look in the received headers and
figure out where the original mail
server is located, which is pretty
useful, right? But in this case, let's
just choose the sender is. And I keep
having to zoom out. And in our case, we
can go under this box here and just type
in an example email address that we want
to block. So I'm just going to put
test.com. And then we're going to click
on okay. And you can see here we've
entered test at
testest.com. But if we go back in here,
you can see we can actually add more
individuals as well. For example, test
two at test.com. So you can see how we
can slowly start adding to this rule
over time. And once we're satisfied with
all our conditions, well, we can move on
to the action section. And in this case,
we can go under this dropown menu. And
you can see we have different options
for what we want to do or what actions
we want the email server to perform once
it finds an email that matches our
condition. So you can see we can do
things like forwarding the message for
approval or we can redirect it to
another mailbox. But in this case, let's
just delete the message without
notifying anyone because in this case,
of course, it's a fishing email that we
don't want. And once we're satisfied
with our rule conditions and actions,
well, we can scroll down and make sure
it's enforced. And then we can click on
save. And you can see once our rule is
saved, we can look over to the right
here and start walking through what this
rule is going to do. So for example, if
we receive an email from
test@est.com or
test2@test.com, well, we're going to
immediately delete that message without
notifying the recipient or the sender.
And optionally, we can add rule comments
here. So if we go back into the
rule, we can click on more options. And
you can see once we do that, we unlock
some more features, right? we can start
adding more conditions and start
stacking multiple things. Right? So, if
we click on the recipient, we can start
choosing other options here like
specifying if the recipient is external
or internal or if they're a member of a
specific group in our organization or we
can start specifying domains, right? And
if we scroll down, you can see we can
actually add a comment. So, for example,
we can put in something like fishing and
maybe we want to reference a specific
ticket or incident ticket that we can
refer to later on. And so you can see
once we've saved that, we have this rule
comment now under the rule comment
section. Now when we think about other
sender artifacts, we don't have to
specifically choose a mailbox. For
example, let's create another rule here.
This time I'm first going to scroll down
to more options so we can unlock some
more conditions and actions. In this
case, I'm just going to call it example
domain block. I'm just going to search
for the sender and specifically I'm
going to look for the domain. And in
this case, we can specify an entire
domain. For example, if I choose
malicious
domain.net, well, we can add that to our
rule. And remember, we can start
stacking multiple domains into one rule
to keep things clean. So, now that we
have some domain set here, we can click
on okay. And you can see we've listed
them here. And in this case, we can just
delete the message once
again. And I'll put in a comment once
again and hit save. And you can see on
the right here, our new rule is created
to match any email with the sender's
address matching one of these domains.
Now, we can also block sender IP
addresses. For example, if I create
another rule here and go down to more
options, well, I can go under our
conditions and once again go under the
sender. And in this case, I want to go
down to IP address is in any of these
ranges or exactly matches. And as this
suggests, we can choose a valid IPv4
address range or just a specific IP
address. For example, we can start
putting in some IP addresses or we can
put in an entire
range. And once we hit okay, well, we
can once again select our action. In
this case, we'll just block and delete
the emails. And so you can see here we
had three different ways of blocking
these sender artifacts based on IPs or
domains or even the specific mailbox.
And lastly, let's look at another option
that we have. If we go to create a new
rule, instead of going under the sender,
we can go to the subject or body. And
here, of course, is where we can match
specific subject lines or any phrases
included in the body of an email. For
example, I'll go to subject includes any
of these words. And from here, we can
specify words or phrases to match. For
example, maybe we've been getting a
number of emails with urgent request.
and maybe some sort of unique identifier
like two exclamation marks at the end.
Well, we can add that to our rule here.
And of course, we can block the email
and click on save. And with this rule
enabled, well, we will match any email
that comes in that includes the phrase
urgent request with two exclamation
marks in the subject line of the
email. Now, in addition to blocking
senders, we also need to consider
blocking various web artifacts that
we've identified. things like the URLs
or the domains associated with fishing
emails in their campaigns. And this can
be done at the email gateway level to
again ensure that we block any emails
that arrive with these malicious URLs.
But importantly, we can also block URLs
and domains at the endpoint level
through our EDR tools or even at the
network level if we're using an
organizationwide web proxy. But with the
rise of remote and hybrid work, well,
the web proxy example is becoming less
common. But there are still ways that
organizations can funnel employee
traffic through a secure gateway, like
using VPNs and blocking URLs at the
firewall level. But ultimately, our goal
here is to prevent users from accessing
malicious links that were contained in
fishing emails. And by doing this, we
can effectively reduce the risk of
compromise and also reduce things like
employees falling victim to credential
capture techniques. And we can either do
this from a specific URL or endpoint
level. For example, if a credential
capture page is hosted in a specific
subdirectory, we can block that whole
subdirectory or we can look at more
generic domain and subdomain blocks. But
again, we need to be very cautious about
blocking specific domains and be sure
that we conduct thorough analysis and
due diligence on the reputation and
context around the domain first. Because
while this can be a very useful
technique if an attacker is using a
malicious domain to stage multiple
campaigns, for instance, well, it can
lead to disaster pretty quickly. For
example, you know, it's very easy to
block a domain of malicious site.net,
but what if you identify a URL that
abuses a legitimate service like Google?
Well, blocking google.com again is going
to be a very bad day for the
organization. And so, we always need to
gauge and understand the potential
business impact by blocking a domain.
And so, ask yourself questions like, are
employees and executives ever going to
need to visit this domain in the future?
If not, then you're most likely good to
block it. But a URL block is more
specific and typically safer from an
availability standpoint. For example,
what if we wanted to block any email
message that contained a specific URL in
the body? Well, of course, we could
create another rule for
this. And in this case, we can look for
the condition of specific words in the
body of the email. So in this case, I'll
select subject or body includes any of
these words. And from here, I can put in
a URL.
Or I could even put in a domain
itself. And this will match any email
that contains these phrases within the
content of the email
itself. A good metric that you can use
is the age of the domain, which we can
find out by doing a domain lookup. You
know, for example, has this domain been
around for years or decades? Well, if
so, then make sure you really do your
due diligence on the domain. If it was
registered yesterday or last week, then
it's most likely a fishing web page that
should have already been proactively
blocked. And when we talk about
proactive methods, well, we'll talk
about some strategies to proactively
block these domains as well. Just to
showcase how we can look up the domain
age. Well, I'm just going to find a
random URL on this page. For example,
let's try this one,
shopppeevip.shop. Well, this one sounds
like it might have been registered
recently. I believe earlier in the
course, we actually found a credential
capture page that was impersonating this
shoppee website. So, it seems to be a
popular target for
impersonation. I'm just going to head
over to the who is domain tools website
and I'm going to paste in that domain.
And I'm just going to click on
search. And from here, we can
immediately see under the dates category
that this domain is only 2 days old. And
we can also see it was registered with
godaddy.com. And quite honestly, because
of how recent this was registered, it's
fairly safe to say that this is a
malicious domain that was used to
impersonate the shoppee
website. And lastly here, we should
block file artifacts. And so blocking
file artifacts, things like the file
name or the hashes associated with
malicious files, is another important
aspect of fishing incident response. And
so by preventing users from downloading
or accessing or worse executing
malicious files, well, we can mitigate
the risk of malware infections and data
breaches. And an effective tool that we
can use to block file artifacts is to
leverage our endpoint security solutions
like our EDR to block files based on
their attributes like again their name
or their hash. And so this is why it's
so important for us to extract things
like the MD5 or Shaw 1 or SHA 256 hashes
from malicious documents so that we can
then block these files from appearing
within our organization. And so this
means that whenever a file with this
hash is downloaded or accessed on an
employee device, well, the EDR tool will
kick in and immediately flag and delete
it from the system and also notify the
sock. But of course, this is not a
foolproof method. Like I mentioned
before, hashes are so easy to change and
they're so susceptible to change. You
know, one slight alteration to a file is
going to result in a completely
different hash. And this gets kind of
into the pyramid of pain, which I'm
going to talk about later in the threat
intelligence section.
And so technically we can also block
file names, but often this is not the
best method unless the file name is
extremely specific or uses a unique
identifier for us to alert on. And often
there's no reason why we wouldn't just
use the hash instead. For example, if we
wanted to create a rule around file
attachments, well, we can do just that.
If we click on create new
rule, well, we can select the condition
under any
attachment. And from here you can see we
have various options. For example, we
can block any email that might have
executable content or is password
protected. However, you can see we can
also match file names. For example, we
can include any email that includes the
attachment name of
quotation.iso and we can add that to our
condition. And so this leads us to
eradication. And this is where we're
aimed at completely removing all traces
of the fishing attack from within our
organization. And so of course we want
to remove the malicious emails from our
email servers. And often we can do this
through things like content searches and
eiscocovery. And the specific ways and
processes to do this is organization and
tooling dependent. But we should in
theory conduct a comprehensive content
search and eiscocovery phase to remove
any additional instances of malware
content like the fishing emails or
attachments that might have been
overlooked during our initial detection.
I'll quickly demonstrate how we can
trace email logs within an Exchange
environment. However, I'll mention that
more modern solutions like Exchange
Online and Google Workspace have much
more robust message trace and content
search functionality. And so, it's not
as important to get hung up on any
specific tool that allows you to do
this. For example, in a Microsoft 365
environment, we could leverage the
security and compliance center or the
Microsoft Purview functionality to
perform a content search and capture all
instances of a malicious email and then
purge them using the compliance search
purge feature or through PowerShell. and
more so we should just focus on the
methodology and what our objectives are.
Right? We can always look up the
documentation if we need it. In this
case, I'll just showcase the message
tracking feature in Exchange. So, we can
first go under the mailflow section and
then into the delivery reports tab. And
this is quite a limiting feature, but it
allows us to search for delivery
information about emails sent to or from
a specific person. For example, I can
specify a mailbox here. Right now, I
just have the administrator user. And so
I can search for any messages sent to
that administrator user. And so I'll
just add that there. And then if I just
hit search, well, we can see we have two
results just from previous testing.
Optionally, if we wanted to, we could
search for messages from a specific
sender. So I could add the administrator
here or put in whatever I want,
right? So if I run this search, well,
we're not going to get anything. But in
theory, you could search for a specific
email address, right? We could also
search for specific subject lines,
right? So if I switch this back to
administrator, you can see we have two
results. But if I search for a specific
keyphrase in the subject line like
hello, well, we've limited our results
to one. So this is not a very in-depth
example here, but you can see sort of
how we can start narrowing down
mailboxes and track specific emails.
To gain a bit more flexibility and
power, we can use something like the
exchange management shell to search for
email within our email server using
various syntax. And the commandlet that
we want to use for this is called get
message tracking
log. And there are a few parameters that
we can use for this command lit like the
tax
sender or
recipients or even with the message
subject. So, for example, if I wanted to
find all the emails delivered to the
administrator user, well, I could simply
put in recipients here of that
administrator
user. And if we run this search, well,
you see, we can pull back all of these
examples of just test emails that I've
sent. If I wanted to find all the emails
sent by a particular address, even an
external one, well, I can run a similar
command, but change this to sender and
then put in whatever I want for the
email address.
And of course, this is not going to
return anything in this
example. Or if I wanted to search for a
specific subject line, I can specify a
sender as well as the subject argument
and then put in any keywords or phrases
that I want. In this case, we'll search
for hello again. And you can see we
limited our original search down a
little bit to only contain messages with
that hello in the subject line. And
there are of course many other filtering
and formatting options that we can apply
to only search between specific time
ranges or you know other qualifiers for
example. But we don't have to turn this
into a whole lesson on the get message
tracking log feature. And again I'll
also point out that this is not the most
userfriendly option. And as I mentioned
with modern Exchange online environments
well we can utilize things like the
message trace and content searching
features that make it a lot easier for
us to find and search for specific
emails. And if you're curious about how
those tools work, well, you can
definitely look up the Microsoft
documentation, which I'll have linked
down below as well. And I mentioned
removing malicious files. So, if there
were any attachments that were
downloaded or even still in employee
mailboxes, well, we need to remove them
from these systems and the servers and
endpoints. And so, we might need to
leverage our EDR tool to quarantine and
delete these files. We might need to run
PowerShell scripts in our Microsoft
Exchange environment to look through our
email server and delete all the
instances. If the fishing attack
involved using malicious domains or URLs
to host fishing websites or distribute
malware, well, we should always report
these domains to relevant authorities
and registrers. And by reporting
malicious domains, well, it will help
further spread an abuse, and the
registars themselves may be able to
suspend or take down the malicious site.
And so, let's return to the domain tools
website for that shoppee domain. If we
scroll down, you will typically find an
abuse contact which we can see under
this register abuse contact email. And
this specifies the email address where
abuse complaints or submissions can go
to. Alternatively, since we identified
that GoDaddy is the registar here, we
can simply do a search to see if they
have a public abuse form, which is quite
common for large
registars. So, I'm just going to look up
GoDaddy abuse. And we can see a number
of results here. If I just head to this
first
page, we can see the terms that GoDaddy
has around reporting abuse. And if we
scroll down, we can see the different
types of abuse because they all have
different abuse report forms. In this
case, we've identified this is a fishing
attempt. And we can see all of the
required information that's needed to
make the report. For example, we need
the full domain path, which we found on
the fish tank website. And note that in
the case of a fishing report, the
website must be live and it must contain
a login area or a credential capture
page. And if we head back over to this
URL and paste it into URL
scan, we can see that it is in fact
hosting some sort of credential capture
page which was just cut off in the
bottom of this
screenshot. And as such, we have all the
required information needed to make our
report. And if we click on abuse report
form here, we'll be taken to the report
fishing wizard. And from here, we just
need to input our email address as well
as paste in the URL entry that we
identified. And now we'll be asked for
some more information. For example, if
we know the brand or company that is
being impersonated, we can click yes.
And we know that the URL in question is
impersonating the legitimate shopppee
website. And so I can just paste in the
name as well as the legitimate domain.
We can also enter some additional
information if anything else is required
to view the page. In this case, we can
just hit
next. And in this case, we can provide
some more additional information. For
example, if we identified this URL in a
fishing campaign or any other additional
information that might be relevant for
GoDaddy to complete their
investigation. And once we confirm and
submit our
report, we can see that our request has
been submitted for the following URL.
and should any action be taken will most
likely get an email at the email address
that we
specified. And next, as a precautionary
measure, it's typically advisable to
implement credential changes for any
users who might have been affected by
the fishing attack. So, we would need to
do things like reset passwords and
reroll access tokens. And this is
especially important if we can confirm
that the employee has visited a
credential capture page or worse made
any kind of post request to one, which
we can typically find out through EDR
and proxy logs if we have them. Because
oftent times we can't just trust an
employee to admit that they fell victim
to a fish. And no fault of their own, no
one really wants to admit that they've
fallen victim. And in cases where the
endpoints or these systems themselves
have been compromised by malware or
other malicious activity that we've
identified, well, reimaging is most
likely necessary to ensure that all
traces of the attack are eradicated. And
so we're going to need to use things
like backup images to restore the system
to a known good state, which obviously
leads us into recovery where we need to
restore the affected systems to normal
operations. So again, we might need to
restore from backups or reinstall
software and implement additional
security measures to prevent similar
incidents in the future. And so through
all stages of our response, well, we
need to make sure that we're
communicating properly to end users and
stakeholders to make sure everyone's
informed and to mitigate any potential
confusion or misinformation. And so we
need to do things like notify the
effective users about the fishing
incident. So this might involve sending
the users an email letting them know
that they received a fishing email and
provide them a timestamp and description
and also let them know what actions
we've taken and what we need to take.
And so having this clear and concise
communication is going to help ensure
that all of these users are aware of the
situation. And this might also extend to
stakeholders like senior management or
IT teams. We need to make sure that
everyone that might be involved is
informed if we need to take specific
response actions or schedule certain
procedures, but we need to make sure the
relevant people are aware. We can also
talk about user education because if an
employee falls victim to a fish, well,
that's kind of on us to make sure that
they're properly trained to identify
suspicious emails and report them
effectively. So, oftent times,
organizations will budget for solutions
that allow us to enroll employees into
security awareness training. And through
this training, the goal is to teach
employees how to recognize fishing
attempts and what to do if they
encounter suspicious emails or links and
also how to report fishing incidents to
the IT or security team. And so while
user education is an ongoing and
proactive thing, we also have the option
of assigning employees remedial training
if they were to fall victim to a fish.
And speaking of proactive measures,
well, let's get into that in the next
lesson. Along with our reactive defense
actions, well, there are of course more
proactive actions that we can also take
to help mitigate the risks and impacts
of fishing attacks within our
organization. And not all these
strategies we talk about here will be
feasible or available within your
organization due to tooling or budget
restrictions, but these are just some of
the general ideas to keep in mind that
can supplement our reactive
functions. And so to kick us off here,
we have email filtering, which we've
talked about quite a bit already. And
email filtering is also a foundational
proactive defense measure against
fishing attacks. And we can do things
like automatically detect or block
suspicious emails before they reach our
end users inboxes. And we can do this
either through predefined conditions or
rules or by using more advanced threat
detection techniques like heruristic
analysis or pattern matching, behavioral
analysis and even machine learning
depending on the solutions that we have.
And we covered creating some reactive
email filter rules in the previous
lesson. But there are tools and
solutions that we can leverage to focus
on filtering proactively as well. And so
we can do this through email security
appliances. And so we can think about
deploying security applications or tools
and various email gateway solutions to
proactively prevent fishing emails and
malware from entering the organization.
And so some of these commercial tools
can utilize detection capabilities like
the ones we've talked about earlier. So
heristic analysis and pattern matching,
machine learning, and even threat
intelligence to detect and block fishing
emails. And these solutions can also do
things like scan email attachments and
any URLs or links and use signaturebased
detection and sandboxing techniques. And
some examples of these appliances
include things like Barracuda or Proof
Point or Mimecast and Semantic. All of
these solutions can help provide that
multiple layer of fishing detection and
mitigation. But we can also consider
implementing some proactive efforts to
keep employees alert and remind them
about the risk of certain senders and
emails. And so a very popular way to do
this in many organizations is to mark
external emails by prepending them with
warning messages that can prompt
employees to be more aware and more
focused when they receive an email from
a potentially unknown sender. And so
marking external emails can allow users
to quickly distinguish between an
internal or an external communication.
And it can raise that awareness about
potential risks associated with emails
from unknown senders. And most email
server technologies like Microsoft
Exchange or 365 and even G Suite
environments will have their own
specific way to do this. And typically
it's just a quick Google search away to
find the correct documentation. But
let's walk through setting up a simple
rule like this in
Exchange. So in a Microsoft Exchange
environment, we can create a simple
mailflow rule to mark external email in
the subject line as well as in the body
content.
So, if we go over to mail flow under our
rules tab here, well, we can create a
new
rule. In this case, I'm going to click
on more
options. And I'm simply going to call
this rule mark external email. And under
our condition here, we're going to apply
the rule if the sender is
external. And so, in this case, we can
change this to outside the organization.
So currently we're matching any emails
that reside from outside of the
organization. To be more specific here,
we can add a second condition this time
under the recipient. And we can make
sure that the recipient is internal to
the
organization. And with these conditions
in place, we can create our
action. In this case, we're going to
prepen the subject of the
message simply with the following text
to mark it as external. And I'm just
going to hit okay there. And I'm going
to add a second action now. This time to
add a disclaimer to the message. And I
want to prepend a disclaimer because I
want this to be at the beginning of the
email. In this case, I can click on
enter text here. And I'm going to paste
in this HTML code that is essentially
going to create a colored box for us.
And inside the box, I'm basically just
going to say that this email is from an
external sender, prompting employees to
be vigilant and not open things like
links or attachments without verifying
them first. And so I'm just going to
click okay there. And then we need to
select a fallback action in case the
disclaimer can't be inserted. In this
case, I'll just set it to ignore. And so
I'll save our rule here. And we can now
test it out with an external email. And
now I'm going to move over to my inbox
on Outlook on the web and just wait for
an external email to come
in. And now that an email's come in,
well, we can see the external tag has
been automatically prepended to the
subject line. And if we were to click on
this email to open it, well, we can
immediately see this giant red box that
we inputed by prepending it to the
beginning of our email message. And
maybe I could have picked a better
styling for this as it's kind of
obtrusive and large. Um, but you can
sort of see the idea here and how this
can be implemented in the real world.
And so an employee opening this email,
well, we'll immediately be greeted with
this warning that, you know, Bob Jones
is an external sender and we should be
careful about clicking on any
links. And so, while we can create our
own rule to apply external warnings,
more and more email systems and
providers are starting to integrate
native functionality into their email
clients, which we should definitely take
advantage of wherever possible. Which
brings us to URL scanning and blocking.
And as we talked about before, well, URL
scanning and blocking mechanisms are
very effective in preventing users from
accessing malicious websites, linked in
fishing emails. And in previous lessons,
we discussed reactive methods for
blocking URLs and domains after a threat
has been identified. But we can also
implement proactive strategies as well
to prevent users from accessing harmful
sites before they cause any damage. And
we can do this through things like
real-time URL inspection. So through
some of our tooling, we might be able to
dynamically analyze website links that
are embedded in the emails and determine
if they're safe or not. Or we can also
implement email and endpoint security
solutions that can perform things like
URL rewriting or redirection. Or we can
route any links through a proxy server
for inspection before allowing users to
access them. And one effective proactive
measure is to block access to any
recently registered domains. And we
demonstrated in the previous lesson on
how we can perform lookups on specific
domains to find out when they were
registered and determine their age. And
obviously attackers are typically going
to use newly registered domains for
their fishing attacks because setting up
credible domains and reputation well
requires a lot more effort especially
when you're constantly being taken down.
And so by blocking any domain registered
in say the past 30 days, organizations
can reduce a huge amount of risk in
users accessing malicious sites and also
cut down on fishing attacks
significantly. And it's pretty rare that
there will be a legitimate business
purpose to interact with a mailbox
attached to a domain that was only
registered in the past month. But for
these rare cases, well, exclusions and
exceptions can easily be made and
documented. And like with most
strategies we've mentioned so far,
various email security appliances and
tools are available to implement this
kind of enrichment capability that can
perform these domain reputation and age
checks for us to dynamically filter out
the
noise. And so we also have things like
attachment filtering and attachment
filtering plays a crucial role in
mitigating fishing attacks that leverage
of course malware or malicious
attachments. And so in the previous
lesson, we talked about some of the
methods that we have available to us,
such as reactively blocking hashes of
known malware or file names. However, we
should also think about how we can
proactively block malicious attachments
from a wider context. For example, what
types of files or file extensions will
our employees typically need to send
over email? Well, most likely it'll be
things like PDF documents or Word
documents, so doc or doc X or Excel
spreadsheets or sometimes image files
and maybe zip files. And of course the
list can go on. But on the other hand,
what types of files or file extensions
will they most definitely not need to
send? And so we can think about things
like executables or VBS, so Visual Basic
scripts or any PowerShell scripts like
PS1s or ISO files or batch files or ISO
files. You know, the list of course goes
on. Attackers can also trick people into
opening things like HTML or HTM
documents or even running JavaScript
with.js documents. And to be honest,
it's typically better to implement an
allow list strategy for specific file
types rather than a deny list because
the allow list will be much shorter. And
so there's going to be many different
strategies and opinions on the matter.
So it's best you do your own research if
you're implementing this kind of
thing. So just as a quick example at
attachment filtering, well, we can go to
our mailflow section and create a new
rule. And from here, I'm going to go to
more options. And I'm simply going to
title this file extension filter. And
for our condition, I'm just going to go
under any attachment and choose file
extension includes these words. And with
this window here, we can start to
specify specific file extensions that we
want to
exclude. For example, any executables or
Visual Basic scripts or PowerShell
scripts, any ISO files or batch files.
And so you can see how we can start
filling up this rule with either
suspicious or non-used file extensions
to lower our attack surface and
proactively prevent malware from making
its way into our users
inboxes. And then of course we can
select the
action. In this case I'll just block the
message. We can hit
save. And we also have attachment
sandboxing. So, some of our security
solutions might be able to actually
execute suspicious emails in a
controlled environment automatically.
You know, we talked about how to do this
ourselves using some various tools, but
in some cases, we can deploy sandboxing
solutions that can automatically analyze
attachments in a secure environment for
us. And let's not forget about email
authentication methods. And so,
enforcing things like SPF or DKIM or
Demar, well, these can all help verify
the legitimacy of incoming emails and
detect spoofed or forged messages. And
so, of course, in the email
authentication lesson, we talked about
why these technologies are important and
how they can be useful in catching
spoofing attempts. And so, wherever it's
possible and feasible, organizations
should configure these authentication
protocols to reject emails that fail
authentication checks, which of course
will reduce the likelihood of successful
fishing attacks. And of course, there
will always be push back on this
strategy because it can result in false
positives. But there are also ways and
best practices around this. For example,
when implementing demark for instance,
it's often recommended to start with
just a monitor policy, right? So, if we
think of the P equals none and we begin
monitoring before we start quarantining
or rejecting email. And so, this allows
the organization to gather data on email
sources and authentication issues
without immediately going into affecting
email delivery. And so, lastly here we
can talk about user awareness training.
And of course, we talked about user
education and awareness training in the
previous lesson with the strategy of
assigning remedial awareness training to
employees who have fallen victim to a
fish. However, we can also look at
awareness training from a proactive side
as well. For example, it's pretty common
for organizations to invest in a fishing
awareness tool like Novaore or Boson
Security or Huntress Sat and many
others. And these solutions are often
configured to automatically assign and
deploy security awareness training to
employees or specific departments. And
it can be done annually or maybe every 6
months to help build that consistent
culture of awareness and reduce the
likelihood of social engineering and
fishing attacks. And this training is
often in the form of short videos or
presentations. And it can be paired with
things like quizzes or activities to
track employee progress and completion
which can also help for compliance
purposes as well. Additionally, these
solutions can also provide the option of
simulating fishing attacks within the
organization to gauge how susceptible
their organization is to these attacks.
And so these simulations can help
identify which employees are more prone
to falling for fishing attempts and also
highlight areas where additional
training might be necessary. And these
simulated attacks are designed to mimic
real world scenarios. And so it often
includes things like of course email
fishing but also fishing and smishing
techniques as well. And so by conducting
regular fishing simulations while us as
a security team can assess the
effectiveness of our training program.
We can also measure how well employees
can recognize and respond to fishing
attempts. And we can also provide
targeted training to those who need it
most. And lastly, it's important to
implement methods for employees to
easily report suspicious activities to
the security team. And of course, this
can be done through various means or
technical controls to ensure that there
is a streamlined and efficient reporting
process. For example, it's common to
integrate a report fishing button
directly into email clients that allows
employees to quickly flag suspicious
emails with minimal effort. And like
with marking external email, well, more
and more email clients and email service
providers are integrating more native
functionality to offer this feature as
well. And these fishing reports can
often be sent directly to the sock for
analysts to be alerted and then
investigate the emails to determine
their legitimacy. However, I'll mention
that reporting should not just be
limited to email-based threats. And so
organizations need to extend these
reporting mechanisms to cover other
types of social engineering attacks like
smishing or vishing or just essentially
any kind of security incident that might
be going on. And so there needs to be a
clear and defined process for employees
to report any suspicious activity that
they encounter in their job regardless
of the medium. And these reporting
methods need to be clear and
userfriendly and accessible or else they
won't be used. And so this is not an
exhaustive list, but hopefully it gives
you some ideas on some of the proactive
fishing defense measures that
organizations implement in the
field. As I've mentioned all throughout
this section, accurate and thorough
documentation is going to be the most
important part in your investigation and
response to fishing emails. And so
strong documentation of course ensures
that all actions are tracked and
justifies any response actions you've
taken. It provides a reference for
future incidents and ultimately it aids
in the continuous improvement of the
sock processes. However, we want to make
sure that when we're writing our
documentation and updating our tickets,
well, we're keeping our notes clear and
relevant and concise. And many
organizations will have their own
templates and possibly even some
automated functions to assist in having
you write concise and consistent
documentation within tickets. So, the
exact method you go about this will
definitely be something you pick up on
the job. However, to prepare you, we can
keep things at a high level and keep it
more general to make sure you know what
is important to include. So, just know
that what we'll cover here is just a
starting point. You can definitely grow
and expand on this as you'd like. And
essentially, we can return to the
methodology that we outlined earlier in
the section to guide us through our
documentation. And so as we investigate
an email message either through its
headers or body content or URLs we
identify or attachments well we will of
course collect a number of artifacts in
the forms of IoC's or indicators of
compromise. And we can think of
indicators of compromise as any artifact
that we observe that will most likely
help us with attributing and linking an
attack in this case from a fishing
email. And so we're definitely going to
want to document these IoC's as we find
them to fill out a report. And after
identifying all these artifacts, we of
course want to analyze them and obtain
evidence that will support our eventual
verdict and conclusion. And after our
analysis has been completed, we need to
of course give that verdict and document
any defensive actions that we've taken
or need to take in order to resolve the
incident. So to start off, let's head to
the fishing analysis folder and then go
into tools and finally the report
directory. And let's open up sample 1.l.
And we'll use this email as our example
as we walk through the documentation
process. And while we open the email,
I'm going to open up the report
template.txt file in Sublime Text. This
is a sample generic document that I put
together that we can use to guide us
through the analysis and make sure that
we document everything typically
required as we work through an alert.
And feel free to save this template for
your own use. It'll also be included for
you under this video as well and it will
come in handy during the challenges that
are coming up at the end of this
section. And so you can see that this
template is divided into several
sections that will help us
systematically analyze the email and any
associated artifacts. And so starting
off we have this header section where of
course we want to document some of the
most important headers that will be used
in our analysis later on like the
timestamp or subject and different
things like sender IP. We also of course
have a section for URLs and attachments
that are involved in the
email. Next, we have a section for a
description and this is where we can put
in a short description of what we find
in the body content of the email. For
example, what social engineering tactics
have we identified or what is the email
actually asking us to do. We also want
to ensure that we provide detailed notes
on all of the analysis actions that we
performed such as the sender or URL and
attachment reputation checks. This will
be the section that supports our verdict
from a technical and evidence level and
should include screenshots and tool
outputs as needed. Under the verdict
section, well, this is where we
summarize our analysis and determine if
the email was in fact malicious or safe
to action. And speaking of actions, we
have the defense action section where we
need to outline what response actions we
or the sock need to take both from a
reactive and proactive angle. For
example, do we need to reactively block
a specific sender or URL? Do we need to
perform a deeper incident response on
any affected users or hosts? Of course,
there are so many variables here and
they should all be documented in the
report. And keep in mind that as I
mentioned before, using screenshots is
best practice when it comes to
documenting tool outputs and findings
from our various analyses such as who is
lookup results or email authentication
checks or virus total and hybrid
analysis reports. However, in this case,
since I'm just using Sublime Text to
demonstrate, well, I'll skip embedding
screenshots. But your ticketing system
will always have the capacity to accept
and upload screenshots to the ticket
itself. So, to keep the focus on
reporting and documentation rather than
analysis, which we've already covered,
I'll quickly go through this email and
note what I would document as I analyze
it. So, first, let's start off with the
description, which we can gather by
taking a look at the email itself in our
client. We can see that it's claiming to
be from Amazon Prime support and is
asking us to verify our account which
has been placed on hold due to a
suspicious login. It looks like there
are some hints of urgency as our account
will be suspended by a specific date if
we don't verify our account before then.
And obviously this email is a little
outdated. It's just an example for this
practice section. Well, let's document
this information in our report
specifically under the description
field. And so in this description field
here, again, I just want to provide a
brief description about what we just
talked about. So what is the email
asking us to do? What is the context
around the email? Are there any specific
call to actions that we can identify? Or
are there any specific indicators of any
social engineering techniques that we've
talked about earlier, like urgency or
trust or
intimidation? Well, we should note these
here so we can better understand the
content and the context of the email
message itself.
And so with that out of the way, let's
start filling in useful headers that we
want to be sure to document.
Fortunately, the eioc.py script that I
showcased earlier can gather a lot of
this information quite quickly for
us. And so I'll just run the script here
and provide the sample email file. And
you can immediately see we've extracted
a number of useful headers which matches
up quite nicely with our template
document. And so I'll just start copying
these headers over to our template
document. And since there's no reply to
header in the original email, well, I'll
just take that out from our template for
now. We also need to figure out the
resolve host. And if you recall, we can
do that using the domain tools website
or any website that allows us to do a
reverse IP
lookup. And so I'm just going to paste
in the IP address we identified here and
click search.
And you can see that we've extracted the
resolve host or the reverse DNS lookup
of that IP address which points to a
google.com domain. And so I'll just
paste that in here to fill out our
headers. And next, in terms of any email
authentication checks, it looks like
this email was lacking any SPF or DKIM
information. However, we did note that
the resolved host or the reverse DNS for
the original setting email server was a
Google address, which is a bit odd from
an email claiming to be from Amazon
since they typically have their own
email infrastructure. Additionally, the
return path domain that SPF would object
ends in OVH, which is an odd top level
domain because that means it's
affiliated with OVH cloud, which is a
cloud company that offers virtual
private servers and other dedicated web
services. And so, I'll just make a
mental note of that for now. And we
don't have any attachments to go off of
on this email. So, let's get into URL
analysis. And you can see we have quite
a number of URLs in this email file.
Mostly, it looks like it's linking a lot
of external resources like fonts and
images. However, what I'm really looking
for is the link that we can identify
when we hover over the button here. And
I can see the domain in the URL begins
with
cabinet. And so, I can return to our
output from eioc.py pi and simply pipe
it to the grip command where I can do a
search for the word cabinet. And once I
do that, we can identify the domain in
question, which I'll just copy so we can
do a lookup. So, I'm just going to take
this domain and paste it into
urlcan.io. And I just need to refang it
here so URL scan can analyze it
correctly. And once our scan finishes,
we can see it has been identified with
potentially malicious activity.
And so I just want to make sure I note
this URL and paste it into our template
or our report into defang format because
it's definitely something useful to
us. And I also want to make sure that I
take a screenshot of the URL scan output
because this is going to become very
useful for us when it comes to making
our
verdict. When we view the screenshot
from URL scan, well, it definitely looks
like some sort of credential capture
page which is impersonating Swiss Pass.
It also appears to have redirected us
from our original URL to this host
domain as identified from the submitted
URL versus the effective
URL. To make sure we get a second
opinion here, I'm going to go over to
Virus Total and also paste in the same
URL. And once our scan is complete,
well, we can identify that seven out of
94 security vendors flag this URL as
malicious due to fishing.
And so I of course want to get a
screenshot of the virus total output as
well because this is once again more
supporting evidence that this URL is
indeed
malicious. And so let's start to fill
out the analysis section of our report.
So let's start with sender analysis. And
as we identified, although claiming to
be from Amazon Prime, the from address
in the header clearly indicates a
mailbox originating from an unrelated
domain.
Additionally, the return path and
received headers indicate that this
email originated from a google.com mail
server and it also utilized OVH cloud
hosting, neither of which are typically
affiliated with
Amazon. And so on to URL analysis. Well,
after performing our URL reputation
checks using URL scan and virus total,
well, the URL within the call to action
button of the email was found to be
malicious as it redirects to a fishing
website. Additionally, it appears to be
hosting a credential capture page which
we identified through a URL scan. And
due to the nature of these pages, we can
infer that when submitted, it will log
and steal the credentials of any
victims. And so with all of this in
mind, when it comes to our verdict,
well, due to the original sender being
unaffiliated with Amazon, well, this
email is a clear impersonation and
spoofing attempt. And secondly, after
analyzing the URL contained in the call
to action, well, it was flagged by
multiple vendors as malicious. And of
course, we want to be sure that we
include any screenshots here that we
took previously. In this case, since I'm
just doing a short example here through
Sublime Text, I can't actually insert
screenshots. And so to wrap up our
report, well, let's think about defense
actions. So, what actions do we need to
take in order to respond to this fishing
incident? Well, first of all, let's say
we've done our scope analysis already.
And so after performing a message trace,
we identified that no other users within
the organization received an email from
this sender or with a similar subject
line. And so because of that, we can
move on to reactively blocking the email
sender. And so to prevent the malicious
sender from sending any other emails to
the organization, well, we can identify
the email address in the from header.
And so we can be sure to and document
that we blocked that email address at
the email gateway level.
And let's also think about the URL that
we
identified. Well, we want to be sure
that we block and also document that
we've blocked any incoming emails that
contain that
URL. Well, we also need to ensure that
no employees or users can access that
malicious URL either. So, we want to
document that we block the domain at the
EDR level as well as the web proxy level
if
applicable. And so, this was just a
quick run through to show how we can
start filling out this template. And
again, just use this as a starting
point. When we move on to the challenges
in the following lessons, well, you can
use this template to guide you during
your analysis. And speaking of those
challenges, well, I think now is time
that we finally get into them. So, join
me in the next lesson where we take a
look at the first
challenge. Now, I definitely encourage
you to continue practicing your fishing
analysis skills. And so to cap this
section off, I wanted to give you three
resources that you can use to find
additional email samples and URLs and
malicious files to investigate. And I'll
have links to all these resources down
below. And so the first one here is
going to be this GitHub
repository. And this fishing pot
repository here, well, is a collection
of real fishing samples that were
collected with Honeypot email accounts.
And so the purpose of this repository is
to provide a reliable database for
researchers and students and developers
to practice their analysis or to develop
detection solutions. And so you can use
this resource to look through and
download real fishing emails and perform
things like header and content analysis
to test your skills. So if we just open
up the email directory here, well, we
can see thousands of sample emails for
us to look through. And if you want to
download one, well, you can just click
on it. And once you have it open, click
on the raw view here. And we can just w
get this URL. So I'll just open up a
terminal and w get that URL. And now we
have that sample email for us to look
through. So we can open this in Sublime
Text, for example, and start going
through this email and looking at the
headers. And if you really wanted to,
well, you could clone the entire
repository and get access to every
single sample email. And next in the
list, what we've of course looked at
fish tank before, which is a collection
and database of live suspected fishing
URLs. And as you've seen me do
throughout the course, well, we can use
fish tank to perform URL inspection and
analysis and test out our tools like URL
scan and URL to PNG as well as other web
artifact investigation methods. So we
can go through any of these URLs here
and just click on its
ID. And once we have the submission
open, well, we can see the full URL
here. And in this case, it looks like
it's using some sort of URL shortening
service. So this is a perfect
opportunity for you to use your skills
to unshorten this URL and investigate it
properly. So fishtank is a fantastic
resource if we want to look at URL
analysis. And lastly here we have
malware bazaar which is a database of
malware provided by the threat
intelligence community. So if we click
on the database
here, well we can start to browse
through and see some of the malware that
has been submitted. In this case, we can
see various signatures and tags along
with the file type telling us more about
what the actual malware is doing. In
this case, it looks like we have some
macro enabled Excel documents. We also
have doc files and
executables. And there's actually a
search syntax that we can use. So, if we
click on search syntax here, well, we
can look for specific things. For
example, if we were looking for PDFs to
analyze, well, we can type in file type
with a colon here and then just put in
PDF.
And once that searches, well, you can
see now we're just pulling back PDF
files for us to
investigate. And if we find a file that
we want to analyze, we can click on this
link here of the SHA 256
hash. And this will bring us to the
specific entry for that malware. And you
can see we get a number of different
information here. For example, the
original file name along with all of the
hashes. And if we wanted to download the
sample, we can click download sample
here.
It's going to download in a password
protected zip file which is quite
standard and also what is quite standard
is the password will be
infected. So if we click download here
well we're going to download that zip
file and we can just extract this file
by clicking extract here and put in the
password
infected. And you can see that was
successfully extracted into the PDF
file.
And from here we can start following our
file attachment analysis methodology and
do things like submitting the hash to
virus total or doing dynamic analysis or
in the case of a macro enabled word file
or excel file. Well, we can start doing
some more static analysis if we wanted
to. And so I hope you find these three
resources useful if you want to get some
additional practice
in. All righty everyone. Well, I
certainly hope you enjoyed that deep
dive into well fishing analysis and all
the different uh investigative
methodologies and tools and procedures
and techniques that we have as analysts
to diagnose potentially suspicious
emails, right? Um, and I will say we did
have to cut a few lessons here and there
just so we could fit that in along with
some of the other domains that we want
to cover in this long video. But again,
this is my calling here to encourage you
uh to check out the full sock 101 course
if you are enjoying this content so far.
Again, this whole fishing analysis
section is just one domain out of I
think eight or perhaps nine. And we're
always adding uh to the course as well.
And so um I would encourage you to check
uh check out the TCM Academy. We will
have the link down in the description so
you can get started in the full sock 101
course. Uh but for now, let's uh sort of
move our way over into network security
and network traffic analysis. uh which
is another extremely important
foundational aspect for um not just sock
analysts but um sort of anyone in IT or
cyber security alike but we're going to
learn how we can use tools like TCP dump
and wireark uh to capture and analyze uh
network traffic in order to find evil or
find anomalies or malware going over
that sort of network layer uh and also
how we can set up rules and detect using
things like snort uh or siraata or
different IDs and IPS systems. So uh the
network security or network traffic
analysis section is another big one,
another very important one uh and one
that I'm really excited for you to jump
into. So I will see you over
there. Welcome to the network security
and network traffic analysis section of
this course. And I'm really excited to
cover this topic because these concepts
are so important and foundational to
understanding how interconnected systems
operate and how so much of business
operations these days relies on being
interconnected and networking securely.
And so as a sock analyst or even someone
just getting into security, well, you'll
quickly discover that networking is an
essential skill used throughout the sock
and within organizations as a whole. And
it's going to keep coming up time and
time again because so much of IT and
security operations are built from it
because at its core, networking is the
backbone that allows for devices and
systems and users to all communicate
with each other. And so virtually every
asset that we aim to protect, you know,
whether it's data or applications or
infrastructure, well, it all operates on
a network in some capacity. Like unless
we're talking about a nuclear power
plant's control system or a root
certificate authority that's completely
airgapped, well, essentially every asset
will most likely be connected to a
network in some form, whether it be
through an internal network or with the
wider internet. And so consequently, all
of the controls that we implement to
secure these assets, well, they will
also interact with the network
environment as well. And as such, this
is also where we're going to find and
come across many of our organization's
threats. For instance, a sock analyst
might need to occasionally investigate
in network related alerts that come from
things like our IDs or IPS. And these
alerts can indicate a wide variety of
things, right? Like unauthorized access
attempts or unusual traffic patterns or
recognized malware communication. And
back in the intro section of this
course, well, we looked at a sample
snort alert and we're going to get more
into snort. Of course, in this section,
in some cases, a sock analyst might need
to actually capture or analyze traffic
on a live endpoint to analyze it further
and look for malicious activity like
command and control communication or
drop malware or sensitive information
being extracted ultimately with the goal
of mitigating potential security threats
and analyzing IoC's like IP addresses or
domain names or other network and host
artifacts.
And so let's talk about our objectives
for this
domain. Well, first we of course want to
understand fundamental network security
principles. So we're going to look at
things like packets and frames and
various concepts that make up our
network stack and communication
channels. So we'll look at common ports
and protocols and services as well. And
so we want to explore network packets
and flows and security controls. And so
we'll deep dive into how data is
transmitted across networks and various
security controls that we can put in
place to protect it. And so we'll look
at protocols and headers and payloads
and different methods for analyzing
network statistics. And we also want to
develop some hands-on skills in
performing live packet captures using
various tools. And so we're going to
learn how to capture network traffic
using tools like wire sharkark and TCP
dump. And we'll understand the
importance of packet captures and how
things like pcaps will assist in our
identification and analysis of network
related security incidents. And of
course once we capture these packets
well we want to learn how to investigate
them and perform network traffic
analysis. And so we'll learn to
understand what's going on at the
communication level. We'll learn to
identify anomalies and intrusions and
other potential threats. Right? So we're
going to learn to examine the packet
content and identify patterns and
correlate data to understand the scope
of the captured traffic. And so a lot of
what we just talked about is focused
around network traffic
analysis. But we're also going to touch
on some network security monitoring
concepts as well. And so we're going to
learn to configure and manage intrusion
detection and prevention systems. Right?
We've mentioned IDS and IPS solutions so
much already and so it would be a crime
not to cover them in detail here and so
we'll look at tools like Snort and
Siraata and how we can actually deploy
these solutions to detect and mitigate
network threats in real time. And
similarly we'll learn to actually write
and implement network prevention and
detection rules. And so we'll look at
how we can configure the abovementioned
solutions to write things like custom
detection rules. So we'll look at rule
syntax and logic and best practices for
writing network monitoring rules. And so
that's going to be quite a bit of
exciting stuff to cover. And so with
that, I will see you in the next lesson
where we'll jump right into the fun
stuff. If we're going to be analyzing
how computers talk to each other, well,
we need to make sure we understand how
computers talk to each other and how
actual data and what we refer to as
packets traverse across networks. And
this is not going to be a network
fundamentals course, as this stuff can
easily turn into a 10-hour course alone
on networking, which I don't want to do.
We'll refresh on some basic networking
concepts, particularly as they relate to
the sock and incident response
activities, but I trust you to
understand the most foundational
concepts like how IP addresses work, how
they're assigned, and things like the
OSI or TCP IP model. But ironically,
speaking of the TCP IP model, well,
let's kind of start with that. Um, let's
talk about how different network layer
protocols work and how they work
together to encapsulate and transmit
data across networks. because later on
we're going to be looking at packets and
doing actual packet capture or pcap
analysis. And so I don't want to bore
you too much with the highle stuff, but
I do think it will be important and
beneficial to walk through a quick catch
up here before we dive in. And so let's
start with a protocol you're most likely
familiar with, the internet protocol or
IP. And the internet protocol is the
fundamental communication protocol that
facilitates the transmission of data
packets across networks. And so it's
kind of that backbone of the internet
and it's responsible for addressing and
routing packets from its source to
destination. And if we are thinking
about that OSI model or the open systems
interconnection model, well the internet
protocol falls into the network layer.
And at the heart of the internet
protocol is the concept of IP addresses.
And you're most likely pretty used to
seeing IP addresses now. In fact, we
looked at a number of them in the
previous section. But an IP address is a
unique numerical label assigned to each
device connected to a network that uses
the internet protocol for its
communication. And if we want to get
super technical, well, it's a 32-bit
binary number uh which is represented in
that human readable form, right? So we
have a series of four numbers separated
by periods. So like
192.168.0.1, right? And IP addresses
themselves can be categorized into the
two types, right? We have IPv4 and IPv6.
And IPv4 addresses are the traditional
format that you're used to seeing and
are still widely used today. But due to
the limited number of IPv4 addresses,
remember we think about that 32-bit
binary number, we sort of started to
make a transition to IPv6 to address the
exhaustion of IPv4 addresses and to sort
of futureproof the everexpanding
internet. But honestly, for the most
part, as it stands now, uh you're
primarily going to be dealing with IPv4
in the day-to-day still. And we can also
think about the concept of IP routing.
And this is the process of how data
packets are directed from their source
to destination across a network. And
routing is going to do things like
determining the most efficient path for
the packets to traverse through the
network. And so when a device sends a
packet to a destination outside of its
local network, well, it's going to be
forwarded to a router which is going to
examine the packet's destination IP
address and basically look into its
routing table to determine the next hop
along the path to the destination. And
that process is going to repeat and
continue until the packet finally
reaches its destination.
And so this kind of brings us to TCP or
the transmission control protocol. And
this is the other core communication
protocol within the TC IP suite. And it
kind of provides that reliable
connectionoriented communication between
devices over a network. And it operates
at the transport layer of that OSI model
and kind of sits on top of the internet
protocol layer. And so when we think
about the TCP protocol, well, the word I
want you to remember is reliable. And so
TCP establishes a reliable communication
channel between devices by using various
mechanisms like acknowledgement flags
and sequence numbers. And so when a
device sends data over a TCP connection,
well, the receiving device is going to
acknowledge the receipt of each packet
by sending back an acknowledgement
packet themselves. And if the sender
does not receive that acknowledgement
within a specified time frame, well,
it's going to retransmit the data packet
to ensure that it's delivered. And it
can do this because it assigns things
like sequence numbers to each packet and
allows the receiving device to reorder
and reassemble packets to the correct
sequence as needed. And we also think
about how it's described as this
connectionoriented protocol. And so it
employs this magic thing that we call
the three-way handshake that we'll cover
later to basically establish a
connection between devices. And it can
also implement things like flow control
and congestion avoidance mechanisms to
regulate the flow of data and prevent
network congestion. And we also have the
concept of multipplexing and
demultiplexing of data streams which
sounds pretty high level and complex but
basically you know we can think about
using port numbers to identify different
communication channels within a single
TCP connection right so each TCP segment
contains port numbers to both the source
and the destination devices which allows
for multiple concurrent connections to
coexist on the same network interface
and we'll touch on this a bit more later
and so lastly this brings us to UDP or
the user datagramgram protocol
And this is a connectionless
communication protocol, right? So unlike
with TCP, well, UDP does not provide any
reliability or sequencing of data
transmission. Instead, it can offer
things like a lightweight and best
effort delivery mechanism that's more
suitable for applications where speed
and simplicity are prioritized over
reliability. And so when we call it an
unreliable protocol, well, it kind of
carries a negative connotation. But
really, all it means is that there's no
guaranteed delivery or sequencing of the
datagramgrams themselves, right? So
there's no acknowledgement or sequence
numbers and so it's more susceptible to
packet loss or duplication or out of
order delivery. And while it kind of
seems like a drawback, well it it makes
up for itself with higher performance
and lower overhead compared to TCP. And
so we can think of very common use
cases, right? So voice over IP or
anything when we're streaming, right? So
streaming media like videos or audio or
online gaming, you know, any of these
scenarios where the real-time
communication and low latency is more
important than, you know, the
reliability of the connection. And so,
as we've covered at a high level what
each of these protocols do, well, let's
look at the logical makeup and the
standards behind these protocols
specifically through their headers. And
a protocol header is a structured
section at the beginning of each data
packet that contains various metadata
and control information that's necessary
for the transmission and interpretation
of the data being sent. And so, let's
start off by taking a look at the
typical IPv4 header. And as we start
going through this, well, you might be
thinking like, whoa, there's a lot of
sections here. Why is networking so
unnecessarily complicated? Well, let's
quickly go through some of these uh
sections to get a general idea of what
makes up this header. And so, we have
things like the version of the IP. We
have the header length and the type of
service, which is sometimes used for
quality of service parameters, but in in
most cases now, it's kind of just for
packet priority and handling. We also
have the total length, right? So,
including both the header and the data
that's appended to it. We have different
flags that can be used for controlling
or identifying fragments. We have the
time to live which kind of represents
the maximum number of hops or routers
that a packet can traverse before being
discarded. Right? And so there's a lot
here and I went through it kind of
quickly on purpose because yeah, this is
great and all right, but how does a
system actually know where to send a
packet or data? And how does the
receiver know where to send the replies
to? Well, there are two main pieces to
this header that we really only need to
focus on from a practicality standpoint.
Like to be honest, we can pretty much
abstract the majority of this graphic.
So you don't need to memorize this at
all. It's rarely going to come into play
in your day-to-day. So we can tune our
focus to these middle two headers.
Right? So we have the source address
which specifies the IP address of the
packet sender and of course the
destination address which specifies the
IP address on the packet's intended
recipient. Right? So we can think of
mailing an actual letter if if that's
even relevant anymore. So, you would jot
down the recipient or the destination of
your mail on the front of the envelope.
And you would also put a return address
or the source address to say who it's
from. And so with these two headers, the
sender and receiver are identified
within the packet itself. And our
appliances like routers will perform the
magic of examining these addresses to
determine the best path for the packet
to reach its destination. And this is
how the internet works, right? It it
doesn't work through domain names. We
use DNS to translate domain names that
are more friendly and things that we can
remember like google.com into an actual
internet protocol
address. So we can demonstrate this
really quickly, right? So let's say we
wanted to check the availability of
tcmssec.com. Well, we can use the ping
command and simply type in
tcmssec.com. And so if I run that and
immediately stop, well, we can see right
away that the tcms domain was resolved
into this number or this IP address,
right? So through DNS, this friendly
domain name was transformed into this IP
address that can then be used for
routing over the network layer using the
IP protocol. And if we just do an NS
lookup with the type of A, which is the
address record, and it's the type of DNS
record that is used to map a domain to
the corresponding IPv4 address, right?
And if we just put in TCM
sec.com, well, we can get the same IP
address here, right? So in simpler
terms, it translated the human readable
domain into a machine readable IP
address like
190.92.188.190. And yes, that's how DNS
works. And I'm sure I'm sure this isn't
the first time you're seeing this. And
so it's great that we know where to send
packets to and where we'll be receiving
packets from, but we didn't touch on
anything related to ports and protocols
with IP, right? And so let's return to
the TCP protocol again and take a look
at its header. And remember we have the
IP protocol and what can sit on top of
that is TCP and the IP header gives us
that highle indication of the direction
of travel right so it basically says go
to this destination IP address or this
packet came from this source IP address
and so when we get into a more session
layer protocol like TCP well we're
talking about things like making
reliable connections between parties and
doing things like network address
translation or having multiple
connections made on one system and so
obviously a big thing with TCP are ports
And you can see we have 16 bits
separated for the source port and 16
bits for the destination port. And
because of that, that's why we end up
with
65,535 available ports out there. And
that kind of brings us to the topic of
ephemeral or highle ports. Right? And so
on the server side, we typically have
some well-known and established or
standardized recommendations through
various RFC's that dictate which port
numbers should relate to which service,
right? So we can think of FTP on port 21
or HTTPS on port 443. Well, we also have
this concept of dynamic highle ports
that get assigned by operating systems
to facilitate the communication between
client and server. And so when a client
application initiates a connection
request to a server, it will typically
select a random highle port from a range
specified by the operating system. And
this is the port that will serve as the
source port for the connection. And so
when the server receives this packet,
well, the server has already allocated
its own well-known port known as the
destination port that corresponds to the
service that the server is providing
like port 80 for HTTP for example. And
the server will select the client's
highle port or the ephemeral port to be
the destination port in the response.
And so by using these ephemeral ports,
well, it's essential basically for
enabling multi-client server connections
simultaneously and ensuring that each
connection is distinct and identifiable,
right? So you can think about having
multiple browser tabs open. So each
connection to a different website is
using port 443 in most cases, but they
use different highle ports to
differentiate the communication. For
example, google.com might be using port
54321 and amazon.com might be using port
45535, right? It doesn't really matter.
They're highle random ports. And so
within the TCP header, right, we have
the source port and the destination
port. We also have something called the
sequence number. And this is a field
that's used to specify the sequence
number of the first datab in the
segments data. And it helps in ordering
and reassembling segments at the
receivers's end. And so it really comes
into play with this whole idea of
reliable and connectionoriented
delivery. And so when a TCP connection
is established, well, each bite of data
that's sent over the connection is
assigned a sequence number. And because
TCP guarantees the ordered delivery of
data, well, these sequence numbers allow
a receiver to reassemble the received
data in the correct order, right? So if
any segments arrive out of order, well,
TCP can use these sequence numbers to
rebuild and reorder them before
delivering the data to the application.
And we also have an acknowledgement
number. And so if the acknowledgement
flag is set, which we'll get into, well,
this field will contain the value of the
next sequence number that the sender of
the segment is expecting to receive. So
this is kind of how we can get in sync
between client and server. We also have
things like a data offset. We have some
reserved bits for future use. Um as well
as many different flags. And so there
are a number of flags, but the main ones
that we can focus on are like the
acknowledgement. And so when the
acknowledgement flag is set, well, it's
used to acknowledge the receipt of data.
And so every TCP segment after the
initial three-way handshake, which we'll
talk about soon, is going to have this
flag set. We also have things like the
reset flag. So if anything like I said
gets out of sync or out of order or if a
packet arrives unexpectedly well it's
able to sort of reset the process and
the communication. And then as I
mentioned we have that sin flag which is
used during the initial steps of
establishing that TCP connection. And we
also have a fin flag which is used to
indicate that the sender has finished
sending data and so it's part of the
termination process of a connection. And
again there are some more uh bits here
like the window size. So this kind of
specifies the receive window which is
the number of bytes that the sender of
the segment is currently willing to
receive and different operating systems
have different window sizes which you
can look up but ultimately it helps with
that sort of flow control right and
along with flow control we have error
checking which we can do through a check
sum and if these check sums don't match
well we can tell something went wrong we
have an urgent pointer which is kind of
only set if the urgent flag is set which
we don't really need to get into at this
point um and then we also have options
and padding which is kind of more
variable able and optional. And again,
these aren't super important to
understanding the entire concept. And
so, the main things we want to focus on
in this header, well, are the ports,
right? The source port, the destination
port along with the sequence and
acknowledgement numbers as well, and
also any flags that are set, which we
can talk about in a little bit as well.
And so with a UDP header, it's very
different and it's much shorter as you
can tell, right? So, we have the source
port, we have the destination port, we
have a length, and at the end we have a
check sum. And so you can see we don't
have any indications of reliability or
state here, right? There are no
acknowledgements. There are no sequence
numbers. There are no flags. And
ultimately there's no handshake, right?
It's just basically throwing packets and
hoping that they're delivered. It
doesn't care if they made it. There's no
retries. There's no reyncs. It just
throws stuff over the network. And
again, this works great for video and
audio, right? If you drop or miss some
packets, it's not going to be a huge
deal. The reliability and integrity
doesn't need to be onetoone. you know,
we can have a slight glitch or hiccup
without affecting the overall user
experience. And so, let's talk a bit
about TCP. Again, I mentioned this
concept of the three-way handshake. And
so, remember how we said TCP is a
connectionoriented protocol and that
it's reliable? Well, the TCP 3-way
handshake is the underlying process that
establishes a reliable connection
between two devices over a network. And
it's that sort of fundamental part of
how data is exchanged through the TCP
protocol. As the name suggests, there
are three steps to this. And so we can
start with the first step, which is the
SIN or the synchronization. And so
client A in this case is going to
initiate the connection by sending a SIN
segment over to server B. And this
segment contains the initial sequence
number, which is a random value that
client A chooses, right? And so this is
used to start the sequence for data
transmission. But after receiving the
sin segment from client A, well, server
B is going to acknowledge the request by
sending its own sin segment back to
client A. Right? So in addition to the
sin flag that's checked, well, this
segment is also going to contain an act
or an acknowledgement flag to
acknowledge the receipt of the initial
SIN segment. And so the acknowledgement
number that server B sends back in the
segment is going to be set to the
original sequence number that client A
sent incremented by one. And lastly
here, again this is only three steps.
And so client A is going to acknowledge
the SIN act from server B by sending
just an act back to server B. And so
this is once again going to confirm the
receipt of server B's sin segment and
complete the handshake. And the
acknowledgement number in this case is
going to be set to the sequence number
received by server B. And at this point
you can guess incremented by one. And so
now both client A and server B have
synchronized their sequence numbers and
can start exchanging data
reliably. And so enough PowerPoint for a
second. Let's try to demonstrate this at
a very basic level. And if you want you
can follow along. And so I'm just going
to open up the terminal. And what I'm
going to do is just hit control shift
and t twice so I can open up two more
tabs of terminals. Right? So we have
three here. And in this case, I'm going
to use the netcat utility, which is a
computer networking utility that can
read and write from network connections
using both TCP and UDP. And I'm going to
set up a listening server just on my
local host. And so I can do that with
the simple NC command. And I can provide
various options like L here to listen. I
can do tac V here to make it more
verbose. So we can actually get some
output. And with the TAC P, I can
specify the port that I want to listen
on. In this case, I'll just choose 1 2 3
4. And I know there are some people out
there that have used netcap before and
are probably internally yelling at me uh
for not uh combining these arguments
into a single one. Right? So what we can
do is just do attack LVP and that's
going to both listen as well as set the
verbose option and also specify the
port. Right? So we can just run this.
And you can see there that we're
listening on
0.0.0.0 which is our internal local host
address on port 1234. And so on this
second tab here, well, I'm going to act
as if the client in this model, right?
So if we think of this as the server
that's listening for the connection,
well, this will be our client. And in
this case, I'm going to run netcat
again, and I'm going to specify my local
host. And so if we think about DNS
quickly, well, I can just type local
host, right? And that's going to resolve
to this specific local host IP address.
And how does our system know to do that,
right? Well, we can take a look at
what's called the Etsy host file. And
this is a file on Linux. There's also a
version on Windows as well, which kind
of provides a local list of DNS names to
resolve, right? So, if I just do cat
Etsy host, well, we can see that local
host here, we can think of this as a
domain name. This resolves to
127.0.0.1. So, we can use either, right?
We can use local host or the IP address.
It doesn't really matter. And then, if
you remember, the port that we're
listening on is 1 2 3 4. And I'm just
going to provide tac v there to make it
verbose. So we can see the connection
being
made. Right? So you can see immediately
we have a connection over that port. We
can see it was successful. If we hop
back over to our server, well, we can
see that the connection was received.
And look at this. What does that look
like to you? Well, that is an ephemeral
port. It is that highle port that the
operating system randomly chose and
assigns it to that basically ephemeral
high port. And now I can start doing
things like saying hello, right? So I
just sent over a hello message. If I go
back to the client, well, we can see
that right
there. I can reply and we can see that
it's being sent over this connection. So
that's cool and all. Um, let's do this
again. So I'm going to set up my
listener. I'm going to have my
connection or my client ready. But in
this case, I'm going to first set up
what is called TCP
dump. And TCP dump, which we're actually
going to cover pretty shortly, is a
command line network packet analyzer
tool that we can use basically to
analyze the packets that are traversing
through our little network that we're
making up, right? And we can do this by
specifying TAC I here to indicate the
interface we want to use. And I'm just
going to type L for our loop back
address because remember we're all doing
this on our local host. And so if I hit
run here, well, got to type in my
password. You can see we're listening on
this interface now. And so now when I
make the
connection, well, let's hop back over.
We can see some interesting things that
were logged, right? So we can see
another highle port that was specified
on the verbose output here on the
server. Well, if we go over to our TCP
dump output, well, let's take a look at
this first line here. We can see local
host, which matches up. This is our
highle or our ephemeral port that is
making the connection. We can see where
this little arrow is pointing to our
server on port 1 2 3 4. And when we look
at what flags were set, well, we can see
this S here for the SIN. And we can also
see the sequence number, right? So this
is that built-in state within the
connection. And so when we look at the
second line here, well, we can see it's
coming from the server on 1 2 3 4 going
back to localhost on
36838. And we can see in this case in
terms of flags, we had sin and then this
dot here which refers to act. So we have
sin act. This is that second stage in
the handshake. And we have our own
sequence number here. And if we look at
the acknowledgement number, well, does
this look familiar? Kind of. It's the
original sequence number incremented by
one. Right? That's what we covered.
That's what we talked about. That's
expected to happen. And lastly, here we
can see the final act based on the flag
sent from the client to the server. And
if we start sending a bunch more uh
let's go to the client here. If we start
sending a bunch more messages. Whoops.
Hi. Hi. Hi. Hi. Hi. and head back over.
Well, we can see a number of acts,
right? So, we talked about how after
that handshake is established, well,
we're basically just getting axe until
the connection is terminated. And so, we
can see all of these different acts and
we're getting some push flags here as
you can see by the capital P. That's
basically just netcat saying don't fill
up the TCP buffer with these packets,
just send them through. And so, finally,
let's terminate our connection. So, this
is our client here. I'm just going to c
to cancel out or close our connection.
And if we head back over, well, we can
see the connection was closed with these
capital F or the FIN flag. So, it's
pretty interesting how we can see all of
this
happen. I'm just going to set this up
again. And let's think about the ping
command again. And if I just ping myself
on
127.0.0.1. All right. So, I'll send some
pings over and head back over. Well, we
can see that this output looks totally
different. Well, that's because we're
using a completely different protocol
here, right? So, ping uses ICMP or the
internet control message protocol. And
so, in ICMP packets, well, unlike TCP
packets, we don't have flags or options
like we did with TCP. And so, if someone
ever asks you what port ping uses, well,
they just think they're cool and they're
trying to trick you with a trick
question. So, the fact is ping doesn't
use ports at all. ICMP basically sits on
top of the IP address. Speaking of
ports, um, as sock analysts, we're going
to often investigate network captures
that include evidence of interactions
with various ports across the network.
And so understanding the common ports
and protocols is going to be really
useful for us for recognizing and
analyzing network traffic, right? So we
have the concept of well-known ports
like HTTP on port 80 or HTTPS on port
443. Well, the other thing here is that
services can technically run on any
port. So, we can't always make
assumptions based solely on the port
number. And so, you're not expected to
immediately memorize all of the common
ports out there, but over time, it will
become more natural for you to associate
certain port numbers with their typical
protocol. And if you ever come across
something you're unsure of, well, the
answer can be found a quick Google
search away. And so, I'm going to cover
what I think will be the most useful
ports that you'll see come up in the
field. But this, of course, is not going
to be an exhaustive list. As as we
mentioned, there are
65,535 ports out there. And we're
obviously not going to cover each one.
And we also don't have to go into, you
know, great detail on each port and
protocol here. It's more so going to be
a general list because we're going to
get into some specific protocols in more
detail as we actually frame network
traffic analysis within the lens of
incident response. And so to compile our
list here, I'm just referencing the top
ports that NAPAP, which is a popular
network port scanning tool, uses to
prioritize based on how common these
ports are in the wild with some slight
modifications. And so we can start with
port 21 which is FTP or the file
transfer protocol. And FTP is used for
transferring files between a client and
server over the network. And so it works
by establishing a connection between two
devices. And from that established
connection, files can be downloaded and
uploaded as needed. So next we have port
22 or SSH or secure shell. And SSH
provides secure remote access and
management capabilities to servers and
clients and allows users to securely log
into a remote system over the network.
And because it's encrypted, well, it's
very useful and secure from a
confidentiality and integrity point. And
so the protocol itself is often used for
various purposes like most commonly with
shell sessions. But we can also
integrate it within FTP itself, right?
So we can have a secure file transfer
protocol. On port 23, we have TNET,
which you can think of similar to SSH
except it's not secure is I guess the
highle way to put it. And so it's used
typically for remote terminal access and
management of network devices similar to
SSH. But it's considered insecure
because it transmits data like things
like login credentials in plain text. So
if someone's eavesdropping or listening
to the network traffic, well they can
sniff out credentials quite trivially.
On port 25, well we covered this. This
is the simple mail transfer protocol or
SMTP. And it of course handles the
transmission of outgoing mail from email
clients to other email servers. On port
53, well, we talked about DNS or the
domain name system, right? And so DNS
resolves domain names to IP addresses or
in the case of a reverse DNS vice versa.
And it enables users to access resources
on the internet using human readable
names. On port 80 that is HTTP or the
hypertext transfer protocol. And HTTP is
the default protocol for unencrypted
HTTP connections. So web browsers can
communicate with web servers and request
web pages and receive HTML content and
images all without any encryption. And
this was the standard up until about uh
I don't know the mid2010s maybe until
HTTPS really dominated and took over. On
port 110 we have POP 3 or the post
office protocol 3 which again we
covered. And so this is used for
retrieving emails from a mail server to
a client device. On port 135 we have
Microsoft remote procedure call or RPC.
And this is a protocol, as you can tell,
used by Microsoft Windows um for
communication between processes or
interprocess communication. And so it
uses things like the RPC endpoint mapper
service, which dynamically assigns ports
for other RPC services. And so again, it
can do things like interprocess
communication, but also allow for things
like remote administration tasks in
Windows environments. On port 139, we
have net bios session service. And so
net bios or networkbasic input output
system provides services related to the
sharing of resources and communications
between devices on a local area network
or a LAN. And so port 139 is used by net
bios to establish sessions between
devices. And it can enable things like
file and printer sharing and name
resolution within Windowsbased networks.
On port 143, another one we covered
already, IMAP or the internet message
access protocol. And it's used again for
accessing and managing email services
stored on a remote mail server. And if
you remember, IMAP has a little bit more
features than uh something like POP 3 or
the post office protocol 3 and is more
commonly used nowadays. On port 389, we
have LDAP or the lightweight directory
access protocol. And LDAP is a protocol
used for accessing and managing
directory information services such as
user authentication or doing things like
directory lookups. And so often we
associate it with Microsoft's active
directory and is commonly used within AD
environments, but it's also a more just
in general directory service as well. So
on port 443, well that is what you are
on right now to watch this video. And
that is the hypertext transfer protocol
secure. And so it's just like HTTP on
port 80 except it includes TLS
encryption within the connection to
secure data transmission and ensure
things like the confidentiality of
things like user credentials or
financial transactions over the web. On
port 445 we have SMB or server message
block. And it's a network protocol used
for file sharing and printer sharing as
well as other communication between
devices on a network. And again it's
commonly associated with Windows
systems. And it can enable devices on
the network to access shared resources
again like files or printers and perform
various network related tasks like
authentication and also remote
administration as well. Okay, we're
almost there. Port 3389 is the remote
desktop protocol or RDP. And RDP allows
users to remotely access and control a
computer or a server over a network.
Right? So it can actually transmit
desktop graphics and keyboard and mouse
inputs between the client and remote
host all over the network. And so if
you've ever remoted into a system and
had access to a guey or graphical
environment, well, chances are if it was
a Windows system, especially you were
using remote desktop protocol on port
3389. And lastly here we have port 8080,
which again refers to in most cases
hypertext transfer protocol. Again, none
of these ports have to match up with
these protocols, right? We're just going
based off the standards and RFC's. This
is a common alternative to port 80, and
you'll commonly see it used in
development servers, right? So if a
developer is standing up a quick server
to test something or run something or in
the case of proxies where you're
actually proxying traffic without
conflicting with any other services. And
so that was this is a big list, right?
And you don't need to memorize all of
these numbers. But over time as you
start doing more analysis and you start
looking at more evidence and doing your
own research, well you're going to start
slowly associating protocols with their
ports. And we also covered quite a bit
in this lesson as well. And so take a
breath, take a breather, and I'll see
you in the next video where we will
continue. When it comes to network
traffic analysis, there are countless
different approaches and strategies to
determine the best way to collect and
detect and analyze network data. And so
in this lesson, we'll talk about two
highle approaches to capturing and
storing network data and how they're
often opposed to each other, but in
reality, they kind of complement each
other very well and serve their own
purpose in the grand scheme of network
traffic analysis. And these two
approaches are packet- based analysis
and flow-based analysis. So first let's
talk about what is a packet right? So a
network packet is a unit of data that is
transmitted between devices over a
network. And so it contains both the
actual data being transmitted in the
form of a payload and also the control
information or the metadata that's used
for routing and managing the packet as
it traverses the network. Specifically
though, we can think of packets as a
single piece of an entire puzzle that we
want to send over a network. For
example, when retrieving a web page over
the internet, well, the entire web page
can't be sent over in a single piece.
Instead, it's broken down into packets
of data and sent over the network to be
reassembled on the client's end to make
up the full web page. So to put it
another way, packets allow systems to
transmit data efficiently over the wire
by breaking it down into smaller chunks
that can be routed independently and
reassembled at the destination. And
typically a packet is made up of three
main parts. First we have the header.
And if you recall in the last lesson, we
talked about various packet headers in
great detail. And so packet headers are
the important part of network packets
that contain all of the information and
metadata required to direct the packet
during its transmission and its handling
across the network. And if you recall,
we talked about the IP header and how it
will contain a source and destination
address to ensure that the packet can
route between sender and receiver. We
also looked at TCP and UDP headers.
Specifically, the TCP header, we looked
at things like the source and the
destination port along with the sequence
and acknowledgement numbers. So as a TCP
IP packet traverses across the network,
well, it goes under a process of
encapsulation with the TCP header
encapsulated within the IP packet. The
IP header is then added to the front of
the TCP segment. And so upon reaching
the destination device, the IP packet is
received and processed. The destination
device determines the IP header to
determine if the packet is destined for
itself. If so, the IP header is removed
and the encapsulated TCP segment will be
extracted through a process of
de-incapsulation. And this encapsulation
and de-incapsulation will continue as
the data traverses through the different
layers within the TCP IP model. And so
beyond the headers lies the payload and
this is the core content of the network
packet itself. And so the payload
contains the actual data being
transmitted from the source to
destination. And this data can vary
widely depending on the application or
the protocol that generated the packet.
Right? So in the case of web browsing,
well the payload might contain the HTML,
the CSS and the JavaScript or other
content that makes up the web page. If
it's an email communication, well maybe
the payload would include the body of
the email message. In the case of FTP or
the file transfer protocol, well the
payload might encompass the content of
the actual file being transferred. And
also depending on the application and
source of the packet, the data within
the payload could be encrypted, which of
course is a good security practice,
meaning that if the packet is
intercepted by any unauthorized parties,
well, the data within it will remain
secure and confidential. However, for us
as sock analysts, well, this encryption
can also add a bit of overhead and
complexity when it comes to actually
monitoring and analyzing the data within
the payload. And lastly here, following
the payload, some network protocols will
include a trailer or a footer section at
the end of the packet. And while not all
protocols incorporate a trailer, those
that do will typically use it for a
specific purpose like a check sum or
error detection or data integrity. In
some cases, the trailer or footer might
be used for padding purposes where it
will add extra bits of data to the end
of the packet to ensure that it meets a
minimum size requirement specified by
the protocol. An IP packet, for example,
does not contain a trailer, but Ethernet
frames, for example,
do. And so when we think about the
process of performing packet captures,
this is going to involve intercepting
data packets as they traverse across the
network. And once these packets are
captured, well, they can be stored for
further processing and analysis. And
this can become very useful in an
incident response scenario. And there
are many methods and strategies for
capturing network packets. And each of
them have their own advantages and use
cases. So for example, we have the
concept of port mirroring or using span
ports. And this involves configuring a
network switch to copy traffic from one
or more ports or VLANs and send it to
another designated port for analysis.
And so by doing this we can monitor the
network traffic without interrupting the
normal network flow.
We also have solutions in the form of
inline network devices such as IDS or
IPS systems which can capture and
analyze packets as they pass through. So
these devices would be placed directly
within the network path and can take
action on packets based on predefined
rules. And we also have network taps and
these are physical devices that are
connected to network cables that can
passively capture the traffic. And so
these provide more of a non-intrusive
way to monitor the network traffic. And
each of these methods have their own
considerations in terms of cost and
complexity and also scalability. And so
the choice of method will depend on
specific requirements of the network and
the goals of the
organization. We talked about logging
and storing packet captures. Well,
typically this is going to be done
through the use of packet capture or
pcap files that store these packets for
detailed inspection. And so a pcap file
is a binary file format that's used to
store network packet data that's been
captured during network traffic
analysis. Each packet in a pcap file
typically includes the raw binary data
of the packet itself along with any
metadata such as timestamps or packet
lengths and possibly other information
depending on the capture tool that was
used. And when we're going through the
process to collect pcaps that contain
all of this network data, so including
both the packet headers and payloads or
all of the ones and zeros, we typically
refer to this as a full packet
capture. And once we've collected the
pcap files, we can leverage tools like
wireark, which can provide a graphical
interface to analyze the pcap files and
allow us to dissect and filter packets
in more detail to identify anomalies and
malicious activity. We can also use
command line tools like TCP dump to
analyze pcaps much more quickly and at a
larger scale. And we're going to cover
both of these methods in the following
lessons. And so, as mentioned, a full
packet capture is going to be the most
useful method for us as analysts when it
comes to incident response since it
captures every single bit of data and
provides the most detailed record of
network activity. And with this detail,
we can inspect the packet payloads to
understand the specific protocols and
applications being used. We can
potentially look at things like files
being accessed or requests that were
made or authentication attempts and much
more. However, this level of detail is
also part of its drawback. And so this
type of capture is going to be quite
resource inensive in terms of both
network bandwidth and storage space. So
capturing every packet that traverses
the network can quickly generate a large
amount of data requiring a lot of
storage capacity and network bandwidth
for both capturing and analyzing the
traffic. And also this kind of thing can
potentially raise privacy and legal
concerns as it might capture sensitive
information like user credentials or
personal communications and other
proprietary data. So there are often
considerations and potential
restrictions on what can be captured and
how long it can be stored. So it's
important for organizations at a high
level to consider these factors and
ensure that they're compliant. On the
other hand, there is a more macroscopic
or zoomed out approach to capturing
network data using flow records and
specifically we can talk about net flow.
And so net flow is a type of network
protocol developed by Cisco for
collecting IP traffic information and
monitoring network traffic. And it works
by collecting and aggregating metadata
about the network traffic flows such as
the source and destination IP addresses
or the ports and the protocols and
timestamps without capturing the full
packet contents and specifically a flow
record can be identified by the standard
five tpple. So that would contain the
source IP address, the source port, the
destination IP address, the destination
port along with the transport protocol.
For example, net flow specifically
defines a flow that shares seven values.
So it includes a few more than we
mentioned here which we don't really
need to get into at this stage. We can
think of the comparison here almost like
reviewing the transaction logs on a cell
phone bill. Right? So flow records or
net flow will act like a summary on the
phone bill and provide an overview of
you know who called whom, when the call
occurred, what was the timestamp of the
calls and for how long did they last so
the duration and this will give us a
bird's eye view and allow us to grasp
the broad patterns and trends in the
communication. On the other hand, pcaps
or packet captures go much deeper and
capture every packet exchanged during
the conversation. So this would be
similar to not only having a phone bill
with the summary of call transactions,
but also having a full voice recording
of what was said over the phone. Is this
the Krusty Krab? And so flow data is
typically generated by network devices
like routers and switches and firewalls
which can export flow records to a net
flow collector for analysis. And these
flow records can provide us insights
into network traffic patterns and allow
us to identify trends and detect
anomalous behavior. So one of the key
advantages to net flow or flow records
is its efficiency in terms of network
bandwidth and storage requirements.
So unlike full packet captures which can
generate large volumes of data, well net
flow data consists of a compact flow
record that can summarize network
activity and it's much smaller and much
more efficient and much more scalable.
And so it makes it much more suited for
continuous monitoring purposes without
placing a significant burden on network
resources. And because the records are
much smaller, well they can be stored
for much longer as well. I mentioned
earlier that there are other standards
or protocols than just net flow. There
are a number of similar network flow
protocols like JFlow, Sflow, Appflow, IP
fix, and various others that initially
stem from Cisco's efforts. But because
of the desire of other vendors to avoid
relying solely on Cisco technologies,
well, this is why a number of
alternative standards have emerged. And
so we can use a comprehensive tool set
like SILK, which stands for the system
for internet level knowledge, to collect
and process net flow and other types of
flow data. And we can use the silk suite
to filter and aggregate and analyze the
data no matter what proprietary means it
came from or was generated from. But
again on the other hand because net flow
data lacks that payload detail it
doesn't really give you the full picture
compared to pcaps. And so while a lot of
people will frame the conversation as if
you can only have one or the other
within a sock environment. Both
packet-based and flow-based analyses
support each other and play
complimentary roles in maintaining
network security. And so analysts can
typically use flow-based analysis to
monitor highle traffic patterns and
detect anomalies or suspicious
behaviors. And once an anomaly is
identified or detected, well, they can
then capture and examine the full
packets to correspond to the suspicious
activity for a more detailed inspection.
Right? So pcaps might be more suitable
when investigating a known bad system or
a network segment where the depth of the
detail provided by the full packet
capture is necessary for thorough
analysis. On the other hand, flow
records are better suited for continuous
monitoring and should ideally be
deployed more near the edge of the
network to watch for specific activity
on a day-to-day
basis. And so with all of that, we're
now going to jump right into some
hands-on with performing full packet
capture and analysis using various tools
in the following
lessons. Let's take a look at one of the
most widely used and efficient ways to
capture and analyze packets from the
command line, the TCP dump utility. TCP
dump is a powerful command line packet
analyzer that allows us to intercept and
display packets being transmitted over a
network and with TCP dump we can perform
many of the powerful functions that we
can get in a graphical user interface
like wireark but with greater
versatility and advantage of being
easily scriptable. However, both TCP
dump and wireark have their own
strengths and weaknesses which we'll
talk about when we get to the wireark
section. And so while command line tools
can be less userfriendly compared to
GUIs or graphical user interfaces, they
offer more advantages in terms of speed
and scriptability and scalability and
also the ability to run it in a headless
format without needing a GUI. And
there's a similar program on Windows
called Windump, which offers much of the
same functionality, but in this lesson,
we'll focus on the more ubiquitous TCP
dump. And ubiquity is an important part
here because TCP dump is available on
almost all Unix like operating systems
making it a useful tool in our sock
analyst toolkit particularly during
instant response scenarios. And so like
I said it's typically already installed
on your distribution. But for the chance
you need to install it well we can just
run pseudoappget install TCP dump and
just type in your password there. But
you can see we already have it installed
on the lab machine. And so with TCP
dump, which we'll get into, well, we can
capture packets traversing any of the
network interfaces on our system. We can
also apply complex filters to capture
only specified packets based on their
protocols or IP addresses or even ports
and TCP flags. And we can decode packets
and display their content in a more
human readable format as well. And with
this, we can also do what's called
offline analysis as well because we can
save captured packets to a pcap file for
later examination. The pcap files that
we save through TCP dump can also be
analyzed through any other tool that
supports the format like wireark which
provides us again more flexibility in
how we want to approach our packet
analysis and response. And so common use
cases you'll see with TCP dump are
things like spanport monitoring, right?
So we can set up TCB dump to capture
traffic from a span or a switchport
analyzer on a network switch. And this
will allow us to monitor all of the
traffic that passes through the switch
and give us more comprehensive
visibility into our network activity. Or
we can do things like remote packet
captures, right? So we can remote into a
server or workstation. And we can use
the TCP dump utility to capture packets
directly on the server or the
workstation without even needing access
to the GUI. And we can also do things
with scripts, right? So we can easily
integrate scripts to automate packet
capture and analysis. So we might want
to set up some automated captures during
specific times or triggers based on
certain network events. And so let's get
into it here. The first thing I'll
mention here is that TCP dump interacts
directly with network interfaces to
capture its packets. And it does this by
accessing low-level network resources
within the operating system. And so
because of this, these actions are going
to require elevated permissions to
ensure that only authorized users can
interact with the OS at this level and
intercept and analyze network traffic.
And so because of this, TCP dump
typically needs to be run with root
permissions if we're doing things like
capturing packets. And that can be done
quite simply by prepending the pseudo
command or the super user do before the
TCP dump command to execute it as a
super user or root. Right? So if I just
type who am I? Well, I am not the root
user. And so if I just type TCP dump and
try to monitor on my loop back
interface, well you can see we don't
have permission to perform that action.
However, if I run the same command but
prepend the pseudo command in front of
it, well I can run this as pseudo. And
if you haven't typed in your password
already, you'll need to at this point.
But I already have. In fact, I can
demonstrate that in a new
tab. So, you can see it's requiring our
password, but now we're
listening. And so, all of the commands
that we're going to use are going to
involve quite a simple command syntax.
And that's going to be pseudo TCP dump.
And then we can provide any options that
we want. For example, we could specify a
specific interface with TAC I and then
provide the name of the interface. Or we
can specify specific capture filters,
which we're going to get into shortly.
And each option we provide will of
course require an expression or a value
such as the actual interface we're
listening on or an IP address that we're
filtering on. But again, we'll get more
into this shortly. So speaking of
network interfaces, well, let's talk
about them for a second. And so network
interfaces are the points of connection
between your computer and the network.
And they can be physical interfaces,
right? So you might have an Ethernet
port or a Wi-Fi adapter or they can be
virtual like a loop back interface or in
the case of a VM, it's all technically
virtualized. And each of these
interfaces allows us to send or receive
data over a network. And we can view all
of the network interfaces on our system
by running iplink
show. In this case, note that we have a
loop back interface with this hello here
that is used for internal communication
within our system itself. And we also
have an interface here. In my case, it's
P0S3 that we're using to connect to the
internet. And yours might be named
differently, but for now, let's just
make note of them. And so when we're
using TCP dump, we need to specify which
interface we want to capture packets
from. And this is the highest level of
capture filtering that we have because
the network interface determines the
scope of the traffic that we'll be
monitoring and collecting. And if we
don't specify an interface, well, TCP
dump will search through our systems
interface list for the lowest numbered
one that's configured up, and we'll
choose that one for the capture. And so
to list the available network interfaces
for capture within TCP dump, well, we
can just provide the TACD option with no
value. And because we're not monitoring
anything yet, well, we actually don't
need to prepen the pseudo command at
this
time. So if I hit run here, well, we can
see we have all these available
interfaces to choose, right? So we have
that
ENTP031. We have any here which will
capture traffic on all interfaces. We
have our loop back address. And then we
have some additional ones here that we
don't need to worry about. And so in
some cases, you might want to monitor
multiple network interfaces at the same
time. TCP dump does not support
capturing from multiple interfaces in a
single command directly. But you can run
multiple instances of TCP dump each
capturing from a different interface.
And if we do that, well, we can use
tools like Wireshark or Mergecap, which
can merge multiple capture files into
one file for analysis. And assuming your
kernel supports it, in this case we of
course do, well, we can run TCP dump
with the any option for the interface,
which will capture traffic on all
interfaces. But if we do select the any
option, well, we won't be able to
capture traffic in promiscuous mode. And
that's a type of network interface mode
that allows a network device like our
network interface card to intercept and
read all network traffic that passes
through it regardless of whether our
traffic is addressed to that device or
not. And again, that's why it's best
practice to set an interface when we're
configuring TCP dump. And so, we've
listed our interfaces, but how do we
actually specify one? Well, we can run
TCP dump here and provide the TAC I flag
or the I argument followed by the
interface name or the index number,
right? So, you can see these are
numbered. This index one here refers to
entpex 2 here refers to any. So, in the
case that we want to monitor our loop
back address, well, I can either type
hello or I can provide the number three.
In this case, I'll just type hello. And
if I just hit enter, well, we're going
to start monitoring the traffic on our
local loop back interface. And so now
that we're listening for network
connections on our loop back interface,
well, let's start simulating some
traffic. And this will be very similar
to what we did in the network security
theory lesson where we looked at the
individual TCP handshake packets. And so
what I'm going to do is press control,
shift, and t to open up another
terminal. And I'm just going to zoom
this in. And I'm going to open a third
one by again pressing control shift and
t.
And if you recall what we did last time,
well, I'm going to use the netcat
utility, which is a utility that can
read and write to network connections.
And so I'm going to set up a listening
server here. And I'm just going to run
NC for netcat. I'm going to provide the
L flag or the L argument here to listen.
I'm going to provide the V argument to
make it verbose. So we're actually going
to see some output when we get a
connection. And the TAC P flag to
specify the port that we want to listen
on. In this case, I will do 4 3 2 1 for
the port. And again, if you recall from
last time, we can actually combine these
arguments
together. And so I'll just remove the
dashes there and just keep one set of
dashes to provide - LVP to include all
of those
arguments. And so you can see we're
listening on port
4321. I'm going to head over to our
third tab here. And if we think of this
one as the server, well, this third tab
here is going to be our client. And so
now I'm going to type the netcat utility
again. And in this time, I'm not
listening, but I'm connecting to our
local host on
127.0.0.1. Remember, we could also type
local host as well instead, but I'll
just keep the IP address. I'm going to
provide the TAC V flag once again to
make it verbose. And then I just need to
provide the port number
4321. And if I hit run here, well, you
can see we have succeeded and made a
connection to our local host on that
port. If we head back over to our
server, well, we can see the connection
was received. And again, we have our
highle port here or our ephemeral port
that our operating system chose for the
client's
connection. If we head back over to TCP
dump, well, you can see we caught the
entire 3-way handshake. So, if we think
of this as a single line, well, this is
our sin based on the TCP flag with the
capital S. This next line here is going
to be the sin act. And lastly, this
third line here is going to be the final
act. And so this can kind of be a little
difficult to read at first, especially
on this screen when I have it zoomed in.
So let's look at the first line once
again and let's see if we can make out
the different fields that are being
logged in this connection. Right? So at
first here we have what looks like a
timestamp and this indicates the time at
which the packet was captured and this
is the default format of the timestamp
and we'll get into this later but we can
tell TCP dump to display this in a
different format like Unix time if we'd
like. Next here we have the protocol
which we can see is the internet
protocol or IP. And if you remember the
concept of encapsulation well inside
this protocol we would have the TCP
header. This third field here we can see
localhost
54388. So this specifies the source
address and port. So if you recall
localhost refers to that
127.0.0.1 and this is the source port
number making the initial SIN
connection. This arrow here indicates
the direction of the packet from source
to destination. And so obviously
everything on the right of this arrow
here is going to be the destination
address and the destination port
separated by this period. So next we
have the flag section. And we've covered
this quite a bit, right? So this
indicates the TCP flags that were set on
the packet. And of course in this case
the capital S here stands for SIN which
is used to initiate the TCP connection.
Next we have our sequence number. And so
this is the initial sequence number for
the TCP connection which is that
randomly chosen 32-bit number. Next here
we have window size. If you remember
when we broke down a TCP packet, well,
we had a field for window size and this
is the size of the TCP receive window
which indicates the amount of data in
bytes that the sender is willing to
receive. We don't really need to worry
about this at this stage. We also have a
section here listing all of the TCP
header options, which we don't really
need to worry about. And lastly, we have
the length of the actual payload data.
In this case, we were just initiating a
connection. So, we don't actually have a
length specified here because this is a
SIN packet. Well, it doesn't carry any
payload data. So, hopefully that makes
it a bit easier to start going through
these TCP
packets. And so, if I return to our
client
here and just send a hello message,
well, we can see the specific packet of
that message. We can see by the length
of six here. So there was actual payload
data within this packet. And you can see
to send over the message, we had a push
flag set and an acknowledgement flag
set. And when the listening server
received the message, well, they sent
back an act. And so all of the data that
we're sending back and forth here over
netcat is unencrypted, meaning that it's
in plain text format. So let's see if we
can view this payload within our packet
capture. And so let's cancel out our TCB
dump instance by pressing Ctrl and C.
And then let's start up a new one. So
I'm just going to clear the screen and
start it up again. This time let's add
the capital X flag. And so this capital
X argument here is going to tell TCP
dump to print each packet in both
hexadimal and ASKI format. And so
essentially it's going to show the raw
packets in hexadeimal allowing you to
see the individual bytes of the data and
then provides the corresponding ASKI
characters making it easier to interpret
the content of the packet. Right? Right.
So, I'm just going to listen here and
let's send another client hello
message. And so, I'm going to head back
over and this time we get a lot more
information. We can actually see some of
the payload data. So, this looks very
similar. We have our length of six here
from our hello message. We have the push
and the act set, but we have all of this
hexodimal data here. And if we look over
to the ASI of that data, well, we can
make out our hello message right here.
So in this case, we can actually decode
the unencrypted message that we sent
over. And so I'm going to cancel this
again. And instead of the X flag, this
time I'm going to select the capital A.
And this is another common flag or
argument that you'll see. And the
capital A argument tells TCP dump to
just print out the ASKY data. And so in
this case, we're not going to get any
hex output, which is really useful when
it comes to things like looking at HTTP
requests or responses. It makes the
output a lot cleaner for us.
So to demonstrate this, let's start a
listening HTTP server on port 80 on our
local system. So I'm going to close out
our server here with C and our client
with control C. And in this case, I'm
going to go back to our server tab and
I'm going to run the pseudo python 3 tac
m
http.server 80. And this is going to
start a listening HTTP server on port 80
on our local
system. Right? So, you'll need your
password here because it's going to be
using port 80, which is a low-level
port. And so, you can see here that
we're serving HTTP on port 80. And so,
I'm going to head back over to our
client tab. And in this case, we can use
the curl utility to make a get request
on our listening HTTP server for a file
that doesn't exist. So, in this case,
I'm going to put in
http/ localhost or remember
127.0.0.1. And I'm going to ask for the
file. Well, this file doesn't
exist.php. And so, let's run that. And
you can see, as expected, we got an
error code of 404 or the file was not
found. If we return to our TCP dump tab,
well, we get a lot more information
here, right? Let me scroll up a bit and
you can see we get the full ASKI output
or the full payload of the received
packets, allowing us to see the HTML
response that we return from the web
server. If we scroll up a bit more, we
can also see the HTTP response headers.
So, we can see headers like the server
name, so simple HTTP. We can see the
date of the connection or we can see
things like the content length. If we
scroll up even more to the original
request, well, we can see the original
get request to the server on this
specified
URL. We can even see things like the
user agent. In this case, we were using
curl. And so, these examples were fairly
straightforward. And I just wanted to
give a quick introduction to the TCB
dump tool. And so our focus is now going
to shift towards capturing and filtering
network data, which is where the bulk of
this tool's features and arguments come
into play. And so with that, thank you
for sticking along and I will see you in
the next
lesson. In the previous lesson, we
looked at the basics of TCP dump and how
we can select our interfaces and view
captured payload data in a variety of
formats. And a big part of capturing
live traffic is the actual capture
filters we put in place before we begin
monitoring. And so it's important to
understand that typically in network
traffic analysis, we'll have both
capture and display filter capabilities
within our tooling. And so capture
filters are the initial parameters that
we establish before we begin monitoring.
And these allow us to specify the type
of traffic we want to capture, right?
Like the specific protocols or the
source and destination IP addresses or
port numbers. On the other hand, display
filters are applied after capturing the
traffic and are used to selectively
display or analyze specific packets
within the captured data set. And so in
the last lesson, we looked at our loop
back interface. In this case, I'm going
to run TCP dump again with the capital D
option. And notice that in my case on my
machine, this is the interface I have
that's connected to the internet. And
yours might be named differently. You
might need to run an if config or an IP
command to figure out which network
interface you have up and running. I'm
going to run pseudo TCP dump with the
TAC I for the interface flag and specify
ENTP03 as my interface. And if we just
let this run with no filters on a real
network, well, we would very quickly be
flooded with traffic. And so if I open
up a new tab here and if I just curl the
TCM
website, well, you can see all of the
packets that were involved in that one
connection. So, first you'll notice that
TCP dump is converting or resolving IP
addresses into host names. Well, this
isn't so much of a capture filter as
much as a display filter, but just to
make our lives easier and is also good
practice when we want to look at just IP
addresses. Well, we can run this again,
but use the N argument with all our
commands to prevent TCP dump from
converting addresses like the host
addresses or the ports into names.
So if I listen again and we make another
curl
request, well you can see this time
instead of https what we got 443 for the
port. Instead of the DNS name, what
we're just getting the IP address
here and so let's start now with actual
filters or capture filters. And the
first one we have here is called host.
And so we don't need a dash in front of
this. It's just host on its own. And as
the name suggests, the host filter will
only capture packets involving a
specific host within the connection.
Right? So if I put example.com here, and
it can be a host name or an IP address.
In this case, I'll just use example.com
for the domain name. Well, let's start
listening. And in this case, I'm going
to open up Firefox and start opening
some random
websites. If I go to google.com, well,
we get
nothing. If I go to Wikipedia, we also
get nothing. However, if I go to
example.com, well, do you think we're
going to log some TCB connections here?
Well, in fact, we are. And so, you can
see that we weren't capturing any
traffic when we navigated to any other
website or domain. But when we navigated
to example.com, we should be able to see
the original three-way handshake and any
subsequent acts that were being made.
And so, this filter can obviously become
very useful when we want to monitor
traffic from a known malicious domain or
a suspicious site, right? because the
host command is going to look at both
the source or the
destination. And so while the host
filter can filter out traffic that
involves a particular host or IP address
regardless of whether the IP is the
sender or receiver, well, we also have
the source filter or the destination
filter. So that's SRC for source or DST
for destination. And these allow us to
filter specific senders and recipients
of traffic. Right? So the source here is
going to capture packets originating
from a specific source or IP address.
And the destination on the other hand is
going to capture packets that are
destined for a specific host or IP
address. Just for example, if I run the
IP command and look up the address, well
I can see that my IP address is
10.0.2.15. So if I run TCP dump again
and this time I can specify a source of
10.0.2.15. And so this is only going to
capture packets that originated from my
own IP address. Right? So if I start
listening and then just
curlgoole.com, well, we can see we
captured all of those packets. And now
we can't really demonstrate what isn't
being logged since we're just in a lab
environment with one machine. But more
interestingly, we can set a specific
destination address, right? So if I run
the dig command on google.com, well, I
can see in my case, I'm getting this IP
address resolved. So if I copy this IP
address and run TCP dump again, this
time I will specify a destination of
that IP address. And now I can use the
IP address here. But again I could just
put google.com. But just to demonstrate
more use cases here, I will put the IP
address. And so if I curl Google.com
again, well you can see we of course did
capture those
packets. And now along with individual
hosts or IP addresses, we can also
filter TCP dump to only capture traffic
to and from a specific subnet or range
using cider notation. And so we can do
this with the net filter here. And this
is going to capture traffic to and from
a specific network, right? So I could
put
10.0.0.0/8 to capture the entire subnet
there. But we also have the ability to
modify this to be the source net. Right?
Okay, so this is going to capture
packets originating from a specific
network, right? Or I could modify this
once more to destination net. And as
suspected, this is going to capture
packets that are destined for a specific
destination network. And this could be
useful in the case of a C2 server or a
command and control server that might be
talking to different IP addresses within
the same network, right? So we can start
to narrow down the traffic using the net
filter. And so another common filter we
have is port, right? And so port is
going to capture packets based on
specific port numbers. And so we could
capture everything happening on a single
port, right? I can put 3389 here if we
want to just log RDP traffic or port 21
if we want to capture anything related
to FTP. And we can further break this
down once again with source port and
destination port. And so you can see the
syntax here is pretty consistent and
easy to remember. And before we
demonstrate some more specific filters
like ports, well, we should first talk
about the concept of logical operators
within TCP dump. Right? So TCP dump
provides logical operators using words
like and or or not to combine multiple
filter expressions into a more refined
capture. Right? So being able to capture
various things on their own is really
powerful. But the real power of TCP dump
comes from the ability to combine
different options in order to isolate
exactly what we're looking for. Right?
So we can think about some examples
where these logical operators might come
in handy. So let's say we're looking for
any RDP traffic that's originating from
a specific system or IP address, right?
So we could simply put in the source
here for
10.0.2.10, but we could also include and
here to look for the destination port of
3389.
Alternatively, let's say we wanted to
capture traffic on a remote device that
we remoted into using SSH. Well, if we
were to do that and fire off TCP dump,
well, we're going to capture a lot of
packets related to our own SSH session,
which we might not want. And so, we
could modify this to be something like
and not port 22. And so, as we start
building more complex queries, well,
it's going to be best practice that we
start wrapping our filters within
quotes, right? And so this will allow us
to use more complex operators like
brackets without having to manually
escape them and allows us to group
various expressions and have them
evaluate correctly. Right? So let's
think of a complex scenario here. And
I'm going to wrap everything in these
single quotes. And so let's say we were
looking for the source of
10.0.2.15 and the destination of
40.123.123.123.
And we don't want the ports to be
443 or port
22. Right? So assuming I type that
correctly, the brackets in the not
expression as we can see here serve to
group the logical operations together.
Right? So this ensures that the logical
negation applies to both ports 443 and
22. Without brackets, the not operator
would only apply to the first port here.
So altogether this command is going to
capture network traffic on our interface
here originating from this IP address
and destined for this IP address while
excluding traffic on ports 443 and port
22. Right? So we can demonstrate this.
Let me just netcat that
40.123123123 address. And I'm going to
specify port
443. Well, we're obviously not going to
get a response back from the server. So
I can cancel that. But you can see we
log nothing over on TCP dump. So let me
try that again. Maybe it was a fluke.
Let me try port 22 or
SSH again. We're not going to be able to
connect here. But we should still see
the packets being logged. And again,
nothing. So what if we try a port that
we didn't specify, right? Let's try 1 2
4. And if we hop back over, well, we can
see some sin flags that were sent over.
So in this case, our filter was pretty
specific.
Cool. And so finally, TCP dump allows us
to filter packets based on their
protocol, right? So to filter packets
based on protocol, well, let me just get
rid of all this mess, we can simply use
the protocol's name as the filter
expression, right? So some common ones
you might see obviously TCP if we just
want to look at TCP packets or of course
UDP. We can look at ICMP. Remember
that's a completely different protocol.
So if we just want to see those echo
requests and replies well we can specify
ICMP here or we can supply ARP right the
address resolution protocol which is
used for mapping IP addresses to MAC
addresses on local networks. So these
are the most common ones you'll see and
of course we could even exclude any of
these protocols using the not operator.
And so obviously we don't have time to
cover every single combination of useful
capture filters out there. But I will
add that the man page or the manual page
for TCP dump is very well written and
can give you an entire deep dive on any
useful flag and argument out there.
Right. So to view the man page, well, we
can simply use the man command, give it
the name TCP dump, and we can pipe this
to the less command so we can see an
easier
output, right? So we can get the usage
information. We can get a description of
the utility. We can get all of the
different options that we have available
to us. And we're going to cover some
more of these shortly.
And if we scroll down to examples, well,
we can see all of these very useful
examples or use cases of TCP dump.
Right? So if we wanted to get as deep as
to print the TCP packets with the reset
and acknowledgement flag both set, well,
we can use something like this, right?
If we wanted to print the IP packets
longer than 576 bytes and sent through a
specific gateway, well, we can use this
command. And obviously, we can change
any of these parameters here. This is
just a sort of list here to get you
started. And so to quit this, by the
way, you can just press Q. And so again,
I'll stress that the most important
skill to pick up here is the ability to
combine various options and logical
operators in order to isolate exactly
what you're looking for in a given
scenario. And so this is going to
require a lot of logical thinking and a
lot of trial and error and also a lot of
practice. And so, like I did with the
fishing analysis section of this course,
well, at the end of this section, I'll
compile some useful resources for you to
get your hands on and also do additional
practice on dissecting and analyzing
real pcaps. But before we can obtain
pcaps, well, we need to learn how to
save them to a file. And then in the
next lesson, we're going to actually
analyze them. And so, thankfully, TCP
dump makes this incredibly simple to do.
And so the ability to save and write the
network traffic that we capture into a
file is obviously very useful when it
comes to future analysis. Right? So it
gives us the ability to do things like
offline analysis or process pcaps in
other tools like wireark or an IDS
system or even back into TCB dump itself
which we're going to do in the next
lesson. And so to save any of our output
into a pcap file, we just need to
provide the W option here followed by
the name of the file where we want to
save the capture. So in this case, I'm
going to send it over to the desktop
under the network security TCP dump
folder. And then I'm going to call it
capture.pcap. And in this case, it
doesn't really matter what filters
you're using or anything or what
interface. We're just going to practice
saving a
file. And so I'm going to run this now.
And then I'm just going to ping
google.com. And if we hop back over,
well, we can see nothing was captured in
standard output. But if I cancel this
now, we can see that 10 packets were
received by the filter and they were
saved into this capture.pcap
file. Right? So if I run the file
command and specify the
location, well, we can see that it's a
pcap capture file. And we can even see
the length here indicating that we did
in fact save those packets. And if we
want to verify this further, well, we're
skipping ahead a bit here. But in this
case, instead of the W flag to write,
well, I'm going to change this to an R
to read from this file. And if I just
hit run, well, we can see all of those
ICMP echo requests. And so we can apply
any of the filters we just covered onto
this pre-existing data or this
pre-existing packet capture, right? So
if I just specify the protocol of ICMP,
well, we should still get everything
returned, right? But if I change this to
TCP, well, we get
nothing. And so I think this was a good
adventure into the various live capture
filters that we have available to us
within TCP dump. And as I mentioned, in
the next lesson, we're going to look at
some real pcap files and start building
up a very strong strategy and
methodology and different commands that
we can use to parse and make sense of
network traffic in the command line. And
so I look forward to seeing you in the
next
lesson. Okay, now that we know how to
capture and filter traffic with DCB
dump, it's time to do some practical
command line network traffic analysis
using real pcap files from infected
machines that were involved in malware
campaigns in the wild. And so if you
recall in the last lesson, we saved a
packet capture into a capture.pcap file.
And if I just ls my directory here,
well, we can see that capture.pcap file.
We can simply view this packet capture
within TCP dump by using the -ash r
argument to read in the pcap. So if I
just run tcp dump with r and then I'm
just going to provide
capture.pcap. And you can see just like
in the end of the last lesson, well we
can read in this file that just
contained ICMP echo requests and
replies. Before we dive into the real
examples, there are a few more display
commands that will come in handy as we
investigate packet captures. The first
one is the count. So if I just clear
this and run it again, I'm going to
provide two dashes here and then the
word count. And the count option is used
to display the number or the count of
packets that are currently matched by
our filter expressions. So if we don't
provide any filters, well, we're going
to get the total amount of packets
within our entire pcap. And so you can
see here we have 10 total packets. And
so this is obviously useful in quickly
determining how many packets match a
certain criteria without needing to
display all of the packet details. The
next option here is just -ash c. And
this option specifies the total number
of packets that we want to capture when
we're writing to a file or the number of
packets that we want to return when
we're reading from a file. And so this
is useful if you only need to see or
save a subset of packets in a larger
pcap file. For example, to only return
the first two packets in this pcap,
well, I can provide the number two here.
And you can see we're just getting those
two lines. Lastly, here we have some
commands related to timestamps. So, you
can see the very first field we have
here is the timestamp. And that is in
our local relative time. We have a few
options depending on how many t's we
provide in the t argument. So what I
mean by that is if we just provide one t
in this dash t well we're going to
completely remove the time stamp
altogether from printing. So it
basically suppresses any time stamp.
However, if I put two t's this is going
to convert the time stamp into the
standard Unix epoch time. And this can
be very useful in documentation purposes
because it's sometimes better to have a
UTC time stamp versus a relative one.
Well, we also have the tac ttt or the
3T's which is going to print the
timestamp in milliseconds since the
previous packet. So essentially if we
run this, we're only going to get the
deltas between each packet. Right? And
lastly here the four T's is going to
print the time stamp in the standard
date and time format. So that year,
month, date, hours, minutes, seconds.
And so we can see how this is also a
useful modifier if we want to display
the timestamp in an easyto- read format.
And so with that, let's jump into our
first pcap example. So head over to the
pcaps folder within the TCP dump
directory. And let's start with the
2021-09-14.pcap
file. And this contains a capture of a
host infected with lockbit, a popular
and known info stealer and remote access
trojan piece of malware. And so how
should we first approach this? Well,
there are many different ways and
methodologies, but I like to obviously
start from a wide 50,000 foot view and
then narrow down the search once I've
identified any interesting conversations
or IP addresses. And then I'll do some
more detailed analysis. And with any
various IoC's or suspicious IP addresses
I find, I might need to zoom back out
and look at the bigger picture again to
determine the scope. And so I'll also
say that we'll be slightly limited in
the amount of detailed analysis that we
can perform just through the command
line. And so while I say TCB dump is a
fantastic tool for capturing packets and
it offers many speed and scalability
advantages over something like
Wireshark, well Wireshark is arguably
better at performing individual packet
analysis due to its statistical and
advanced filter features, but we will
get to Wireshark in due time. And
they're both very important tools to
grasp. So let's start out with the most
simple command to just read the file and
see what we're dealing with. So, if you
recall, I'm just going to run TCP dump,
provide the R flag here, and then just
provide the name of the file. In this
case, that
2021-09-14.pcap
file. And we're getting a lot of
packets. So, what we can do, if you
remember, we have the count command, so
we can identify how many packets we're
dealing with. In this case, we have
around 3,600 packets. And as good
practice, like I said, I'm going to
display the timestamps in Unix epoch
time. And so to do that, I'm just going
to prepend the -ashtt there in front of
all of our commands just so we can get
the timestamps in that format. And so
let's start by going through some of
this at a very high level. And in this
case, I don't want to provide the N
argument yet because I might be
interested in some of the domain names
that we identify. And as I scroll up
here, I'm seeing quite a bit of traffic
between this
10.0.0.168 address and this 103.23255.14
232.55.148
address. And this also appears to be
port 80 or HTTP traffic, which is going
to be useful for us since it's
unencrypted. And so for my first filter,
I'm just going to specify that we only
want to look at port 80 traffic as
either the source or destination port.
And so to do that, I can just provide
the port
argument and just put 80. In this case,
I'll narrow down the count here so we
can see how many we've cut down. In this
case, about over a thousand packets,
which is nice. And again, I was noticing
some conversations between those two IPs
that I identified. And during real
traffic analysis, we'd probably know the
affected endpoint source IP address,
likely from the ticket or the incident
details. However, in this case, I can
make the assumption since it's the only
internal IP I've seen so far, that this
is probably the source IP of the
endpoint. In which case, I'll add this
IP to our filter as the
host. And I'll just modify our command a
bit to include
and with the host of
10.0.068. And since we're dealing with
HTTP, I also want to search for any get
or post requests, which we can actually
do by leveraging the ever useful GP
command. And so we can pipe our output
here into
GP. And we can then search for any
instances with get or post that show up
in the HTTP headers.
And a get request in HTTP would be like
a web request to retrieve information
like fetch me this web page. And a post
request on the other hand would be a
request to a web page where we're
sending in data in what we would call
post parameters within the HTTP body.
And this could be things like
credentials or information in a form and
many other possibilities. And so it can
be quite useful to narrow down web
requests like these especially when the
connection is unencrypted. And so to
specify our parameters within GP here,
I'm going to give it the capital E
option. So we can specify an expression.
And in this case, I'm going to wrap it
in double quotes. And I apologize as
it's gone to a second line, but I'm just
going to provide and then pipe that to
post, meaning that we're going to match
any words that are get or post. And so
if I run this, so we can see a number of
different URLs or endpoints that we
could perhaps cross reference with our
web proxy or firewall logs if we had
them. However, there's one URL or path
listed here that makes me very curious
and suspicious. And can you see
it? Well, it's this one right here,
which is very interesting. And it
suggests that the endpoint downloaded an
executable file called audiodg.exe.
And any.exe extension should get our
ears perking up. And the dot in front of
the file name here is also quite
suspicious, right? So in file systems, a
dot at the beginning of a file name
often signifies a hidden file. However,
this is more common in Unix like
operating systems and is not something
we typically see in Windows
environments. So this might be an
unusual naming convention or an attempt
to mask a malicious file with a false
extension. And so I'm just going to copy
the name of this executable here. And if
we perform some very basic OSINT by
Google searching the name of the file in
quotes. Well, we can see that it might
relate to the Windows audio device
graph. However, the curious thing here
is that in our pcap, this file doesn't
seem to have been downloaded through an
official Microsoft channel. And the dot
at the beginning of the file name is now
even more suspicious.
And so let's return to our original
methodology that we built through the
fishing analysis section of this course.
And so we've identified a suspicious
file name here that came from an
identified indicator of compromise or
IOC. In this case, we have the IP
address of
103.232.55.148. And I'd say a good call
here is to do a lookup of this IP
address to confirm whether or not this
really is affiliated with Microsoft in
any way.
And so I'll just head over to the domain
tools website and paste in this IP. And
we can see that it's affiliated with a
server technology company located in
Vietnam. And it's in no way related to
Microsoft. So we've identified two IoC's
hinting at a malware infection in the
form of a file name and an IP address.
And so let's step back in our filters
and perform a more generic search using
GP for any packet that contains the
audiodg.exe file. And so I'll just clear
this out and I'm going to remove all of
these filters and just search for
audiodg.exe. And it shouldn't matter
that we don't have the dot at the
beginning. And so it looks like we have
two results. The first one here seems to
be including a URL within the query
parameters of this API. And the URL
within these parameters, well points to
the same IP address that we just
identified. And so let's start opening
these packets up to the best of our
limited ability within TCP dump. And so
I'll modify our command a bit here. And
so because I want to open the ASKI
output of the payloads contained within
these packets, well I will apply the
capital A argument to TCP
dump. Additionally, I'm going to modify
our GP command slightly to also append a
capital A. Now this is a different one.
With GP, we can append the capital A to
retrieve a number of trailing lines
after we match our GP results. And so,
because we're opening up the payloads
that are going to be multi-lined, well,
we can tell GP that we want to also
display the trailing 500 lines or so
after we match the
audiodg.exe string. So, this is not the
cleanest way to do this, but we are
limited to command line tools here. And
so, before I run this, I'm going to pipe
it once again to the less command. And
this will make the output a lot easier
for us to scroll
through. And so immediately we can see
this first result here. So we're opening
up that first packet that was pointing
to this endpoint here, this API. And if
we look in the HTTP host header, well,
we can see it's pointing to
api.bing.com. And we can also see the
destination address here is 13.107.5.80.
And if we do a lookup of this IP
address, well, we can see that it is in
fact associated with Microsoft and
likely Bing. And so based on this
oddlook URL, it seems to be designed to
interact with Bing search's API to
either query information or abuse it in
some way to redirect to the provided
URL, which we discovered is hosting that
executable file. And so I'm going to
copy the entire URL within this query
parameter and head over to Cybershere to
see if we can decode the URL. And so I'm
just going to search for the URL decode
and drag it over to the recipe. And we
can see the full URL. And while we're
here, we should probably defang it as
well as it's good practice for our
documentation. And now this definitely
looks like a potentially malicious URL
to me. Partly due to the IP address
instead of a domain name. the HTTP
protocol and also the fact that it's
serving an executable file. And so I'm
just going to copy this URL quickly and
head over to virus
total. And I did mention earlier we
would be using a lot of these tools all
throughout our different
investigations. And if I go under the
URL section and paste in that
URL, well, we can see that it was
flagged by six vendors as malicious,
which supports our investigation.
And if we head back over to our output
here and scroll to the second packet,
well, we can see the beginning packets
that contain the actual download of the
executable file. And specifically, we
will find this string here of this
program cannot be run in DOSS mode. And
this is a string that's often found at
the beginning of a Windows executable
file and is part of the DOSS header. And
so, we've successfully found the main
malicious IOC within this pcap file, all
through using TCB dump filters and GP.
If we wanted to take this any further
and actually extract the executable file
or obtain its hashes for further
analysis, well, we would typically have
to use something like Wireark to do
that. And so, I hope this example wasn't
too complex. But you can see how it can
sort of get a little difficult to do
things solely from the command line,
which is why we have other tools and
options available to us. But it is still
important to know how to do some of this
stuff, like using GP and doing different
filtering options to find what we're
looking for. And so since this video got
a bit longer than I thought, I'm going
to save the second analysis for the next
video. So I will see you in the next
video. All right, so let's go through
another example. And this time, we'll
get to chain some more useful command
line utilities together to parse through
some more packets. And in this scenario,
we have a packet capture from a Cobalt
Strike Beacon after a user fell victim
to a malicious macro enabled Word
document. And in this case, we're going
to be looking at the 2024-04-18.pcap
pcap file. And so let's start off by
seeing how many packets we have to deal
with. So I'm going to read in that file
and then I'm going to provide the d-
count argument. You can see we have
almost 10,000 packets here. So a bit
more than the last time. And so let's
start out by doing something that is
incredibly easy to do in something like
Wireshark, but is a little more
complicated when viewing a packet
capture in TCP dump. And that involves
looking at statistics of conversations
and IPs and ports. And so first, let's
look at the top source IP addresses. And
so to do that, I'm going to run TCP
dump. I'm going to provide two T's here
to convert the timestamp into Unix time.
I'm going to read in the file. Once
again, since I'm just dealing with IPs
right now, I'm going to provide the N
argument so we don't resolve any IP
addresses to names. And the only filter
I'm going to use right now is TCP. This
is because at this point I'm not
concerned with any ICMP or ARP or any
UDP
packets. And I'm just going to run this
so we can see what the output looks
like. Okay, excellent. I'm going to give
us a bit of space here. And I'm going to
rerun the command again. This time I'm
going to pipe it to a very useful
command called cut. And we're going to
cover cut in a lot more detail during
the log analysis and sim section because
it's really one of those Swiss Army
knife tools that every sock analyst
should master because it really helps
you parse through logs very quickly. And
in this case, the cut command allows us
to specify a delimiter with the tac d
option. And in this case, I'm going to
put the delimiter in quotes. And for the
delimiter itself, I'm just going to
press the space bar to add in a space.
Because if you look at some of these
outputs here, we have a field and then
we have a delimiter of a space and then
we have another field for the protocol
and then another space and then the IP
address. And so this is the field that I
want to extract. And so in this case, I
can provide the -f option to specify the
field that we're cutting. And in this
case, if we count, we have one field,
two fields, and three fields. And so
I'll just provide the number
three. And if I run this, well, you can
see we're just cutting the IP addresses.
However, due to the way that TCP dump
organizes things, we're also getting the
port numbers appended at the end. So in
this case, we can pipe this to yet
another cut command. And in this case,
we can specify the delimiter of the
period. And if we think about the
periods in these outputs, well, we have
one field, two fields, three fields,
four and five. So in this case, we want
to grab fields one to four, but exclude
five. And so for the fields option, I
can just provide 1 to four. So we can
provide that range there with the dash.
And so I'll run this one more time. And
you can see we're just getting the IP
addresses now. And so this is great, but
we have a lot of IP addresses here.
We're not doing any kind of filtering or
sorting. And so that's where the sort
command comes in, which is another very
useful command that again we're going to
cover in some more detail later on. But
let this be a introduction to it if you
haven't used it
already. And so I'm going to pipe this
output once again into the sort command.
And let's see how that changes things.
Well, we can see that all the IP
addresses have been sorted in descending
order. And so that's useful, but how do
we cut down on the duplicate entries?
Well, that is where we can pipe this
into the unique command.
And that's going to cut down all of the
entries that are duplicates on the same
line. Right? So you can see we had a
bunch of 85s here. This IP address
duplicated on the same line. And so
unique is going to cut down on all of
these. So it aggregates into a single
line. And a modifier that we can add to
the unique command is the C option or
the C argument which will display a nice
count for us. And so this is the amount
of unique aggregated entries of that
single IP address. And so this is great.
We're almost there. However, we can do
one more sort command here with the -ash
nr with the n being a numeric sort to
compare the string against the numerical
data of the count values here. NR to do
it in reverse. And so if we run this, we
will finally get a nice and sorted list
with all of the source IP addresses
within this pcap file. And if we scroll
up, well, we can see that the top IP
address here is this
10.4.18.169. And in second place, we
have this 85.23.
239.53.219. We also have some other
interesting IPs as well. And so
similarly we can run the same command
but we just need to change the first
value here from sorting on the third
field to the fifth. And in this case we
will get the top destination IP
addresses. Right? So if I run that and
we scroll back to the top well we're
getting the same results basically
because the source and destination seem
to be talking to each other the most.
And so we again we have this 10.4 4 and
this
85.239. And so from these initial
statistics, it looks like this private
IP address might be the affected
endpoint. And this one right here is a
potentially interesting IP to look into.
And so I'm going to get rid of all these
cut commands here. And I'm going to
specify that we want the source of
10.418.169 and the destination IP of
85.23953.29.
And if we just run a count on these,
well, we can see that we've narrowed
this down to about a thousand packets,
which is nice. And so now let's
aggregate and get some statistics on the
top ports that these two IP addresses
are using in their communications. And
so to do this, let me just clear this
all out. I'm going to remove the count
here. And I'm going to pipe the output
of, you know, these filters here with
the source and destination. And I'm
going to cut based on the space again.
And this time I want the third field
again because remember we're getting the
IP and the port. And so we want to pipe
this to another cut
command for any periods. And in this
case we only want the fifth field. And
that's just going to return the ports.
And so now it's just a matter of sorting
and grabbing the unique and then sorting
once
more. And you can see we're now getting
the top source port numbers. And if we
just modify this slightly and in this
case I'm just going to change source
here to destination and then I'll change
destination to source to basically
reverse this
filter. And you can see we're only
returning port 80 as the destination
port. And so we can see that the
majority of traffic is on port 80 or
HTTP and what looks like a number of
ephemeral or highle ports from the
client's end which of course makes
sense. And so now that we know that
we're just dealing with port 80 traffic,
well, let's look a bit deeper. And if
you recall what we did with our previous
pcap, well, we can pull back things like
the HTTP get or post headers from the
packets themselves using GP. And so I'll
just search on that source and
destination IP. And then I'll type this
to GP where we'll provide the capital E
to do an expression. And then we want to
look for get or post.
If we run this, well, we can see a
number of post requests to this API
endpoint. And this endpoint has a
seemingly unique identifier here, which
is very
curious. And so, let's try opening up
some of these packets. And so, I'm going
to clear this out. And this time, I'm
going to provide the - C argument to TCP
dump to only pull back the first five
packets here. And in this case, I'm
going to provide the capital A argument
to open up the packet in that ASI
format.
And so when we do that, well, we get a
very interesting content type here of
Los Angeles and a user agent of SS load
1.1. And I've never seen this user agent
string before. And so I'm going to copy
SS load and once again do some more
OSINT and just Google to see if I can
find any
information. And when I search for SS
load, well, I can immediately see this
Malpedia article here specifying that
it's part of a malware family.
And we can see that SSL load is a
rustbased downloader that is used to
deliver secondary payloads. And we can
see that the first stage of the malware
connects to a telegram channel named SS
load to retrieve another URL. We can see
that it downloads a compressed PE file
or an executable file using a hard-coded
user agent of SS load 1.x. And this is
the user agent that we saw in our HTTP
headers. If I go back to Google here and
search SS
load, well, I can see this GitHub URL.
And in this case, we can see a number of
additional IOC's that we can perhaps
look out for in our pcap file. For
example, this appears to be the Telegram
link because I know from experience that
t.m me is a domain owned and operated by
Telegram. We can see this IP address
which we actually already discovered.
So, this is that 85.239 IP address. We
can see that it downloads an encrypted
payload on this URL. So let's see if we
can find the domain name associated with
that IP address. And so in this case,
I'm just going to provide the filter of
host. And I'm going to provide that
85.23953.29. And if I run this, well, we
can see a very interesting domain name
here.
And it appears based on this first
subdomain, it's using some sort of
dynamic DNS to have a random value for
this
subdomain. And so with that, I will take
the base domain here of first
opportunity.online and head back to
Virus Total to see if I can find any
information about this domain name. If I
search under the URL tab for that domain
name, well, we can see that two security
vendors here flagged the URL or the
domain as malicious.
And so since we were seeing a large
number of post requests, well, let's try
opening up some of the packets to see if
any passwords or credentials were
submitted. And we can actually do that
through some clever expressions within
Grep. And so I'll run the command again.
In this case, I'll append the capital A
so we can see the ASKY output of the
payload. And I'll pipe this over to Grep
where I'll use -ash I to make sure it's
case insensitive. Within our search
here, I will look for any results that
contain the word
user or pass for password or login. And
if we run this, well, we're actually
getting all of the user agent strings,
which isn't very useful. So, what I can
do is pipe this to yet another GP
command. And this time, I'll use -ashv
to exclude the word user
agent. Now, if I run this, we should get
any other outputs. And in this case, we
get a very interesting object here. So
we can actually see some key value pairs
that might relate to the beacon or
information related to the affected
endpoint that was being sent over to the
attacker. So we can see things like an
IP address here. We can see the domain
that the affected endpoint was likely
on. We can see the host name of the
affected system. We can see the
architecture and operating system
version. We can even see the user that
was logged in. And we're getting all
this information just from the keep
alive object inside this packet.
And so let's also use GP to see if we
can find any files that were downloaded.
And so sometimes HTTP packets will
contain a file name header to specify
the name of a file being downloaded. And
in this case, I'm just going to search
for the string of file name. And if we
run this, well, we can see some
interesting results. We are seeing this
crypted_dll.bin file. And so this is
definitely something we want to open up
in Wireshark now to get more details on
the payload that was downloaded. But we
will save this for another lesson. And
so while we're here, let's see if we can
hunt down the remaining IoC's. And so if
you recall, we actually had reference to
a TM me domain here, which actually
relates to the Telegram messaging
service, which is sometimes used as a C2
or command and control channel for
attackers. And so let's do a search
across our entire pcap file for anything
related to T.M. me. And so I will search
the entire file and just g for TM me.
Interesting. So we can see some related
DNS queries to that
domain. And so in this case we have
certain values like this which is the
identifier for the DNS query. And this
is a randomly generated number. In this
case we have a with a question mark
here. This indicates the type of DNS
query that is being performed. In this
case it's an A query which is used to
translate a domain name to an IPv4
address. And lastly we have t.m me which
is the actual domain name being queried.
And so to put this all together, these
packets represent DNS queries from our
source
endpoint asking for the IPv4 address
correspondent to the domain name t.m me.
And so if we change our filter here to
search for the host of t.m
me. Well, it looks like all of the
traffic is HTTPS traffic on port 443,
meaning that we can't really dig into
the payloads without having the TLS
certificate, which we typically don't
have.
And so lastly, the IoC's we found also
mentioned a malicious DLL file that is
used for the second stage of the
malware. And so let's see if we perform
a basic search here if we can pull back
anything related to a DLL. And in this
case, we actually did. We can see that
the endpoint here made a get request for
this 8080.dll file.
And if I attempt to open this packet up
with the capital A and then also append
capital A with GP so I can pull back 50
lines and then pipe it over to
less. Well, we can start to see the
contents of the
crypted_dll.bin
file. But at this point, we really need
to open this up in Wireshark as we can't
do detailed analysis like this with TCP
dump alone.
And so these were two somewhat elaborate
command line investigations to cap off
our TCP dump lessons, but hopefully they
showed you a bit of the general process
and methodology on how we can use
various display filters to zoom in and
isolate what we're looking for and how
we can use various IoC's we find to
enhance our search. And so to conclude,
TCP dump is a fantastic tool for quickly
and efficiently capturing network
traffic and aggregating network packets.
However, in the next lessons that
follow, we're going to take a look at
Wireshark, which is a graphical packet
analyzer, which will give us a lot more
power in various features like
statistics aggregation or conversation
following that can make our
investigations much easier. And so, at
the end of the day, it's important that
we cover and know both as you never know
what you'll have access to in the field
with certain incidents or scenarios. And
so, with that, I will see you in the
next lesson for the challenge and then
see you over in the Wireshark section.
Welcome to the Wireshark section of this
course. As I've mentioned a few times
already, Wireshark is another essential
tool for anyone involved in either
network troubleshooting and in our case,
network traffic analysis. And as sock
analysts, we need to know how to use it
to both create and carve through and
analyze pcaps when responding to
malicious activity over the network. So
there might be scenarios where we're
handed a pcap file that contains
suspicious traffic and we need to
analyze it to identify various
indicators of compromise or live
incident response scenarios where we
might need to actually remote in and
capture packets directly from a
compromised server or workstation. And
so Wireshark is a free and open- source
GUI based utility. So a graphical user
interfacebased utility and is the most
widely used network protocol analyzer in
the world. And like with TCP dump, we
can use Wireshark to do live capture and
offline analysis of network traffic. So
we can capture live network traffic
through any of our network interfaces or
analyze previously captured packets
through pcap or other file formats. And
because Wireshark is a graphic based
tool, it offers several analysis
advantages over TCP dump. And it allows
us to do more of a deep inspection of
various networking protocols and use
things like powerful display filters to
narrow down interesting traffic and even
follow stateful conversations like TCP
and HTTP data streams. And we can look
at highle statistics which really helps
the initial analysis process. And so
when it comes to network packet
analysis, many folks like to put
Wireshark and TCP dump headto-head and
have strong opinions on which is the
better tool. And well, the truth is,
like I said before, both Wireshark and
TCP dump have their own strengths and
weaknesses and are suitable for
different purposes rather than one being
categorically better than one another.
And so TCP dump being a command
linebased tool is known for its speed
and efficiency. And it's especially
useful in environments with high network
throughput and data rates and large
volumes of traffic. And like we said
before, TCP dump is available on almost
every Unixbased system, making it a
powerful and ubiquitous tool and also
doesn't require a graphical user
interface. So it's ideal for headless
servers and remote sessions. Wireshark
on the other hand is really good at
detailed packet analysis, right? So it
makes navigating and filtering and
analyzing network traffic much easier
and it offers way more visualizations
and statistics. But of course the
drawbacks are it can be very resource
inensive and often struggles with very
high data rates and large capture files.
And so if you have a very large pcap
file, well, you might need to first
carve it down with relevant filters with
TCP dump or something like T-shark first
and then load it into Wireshark once
it's a lot smaller. And so in general,
for real-time traffic capture on
high-speed networks, TCP dump is more
suitable due to its efficiency and
scalability. But for in-depth analysis
and visualization, Wireshark is the
better choice. And so unlike TCP dump,
Wireshark typically does not come
bundled in to most default Linux
distributions or with Windows. So, let's
quickly cover the installation process
for each. And so, on Linux, the easiest
way uh is typically through your
built-in package manager. And in our
case, we're running Ubuntu. So, we
really just need to run pseudoapp
install Wireshark and say yes to the
prompt
there. And so, we will be met with this
screen here when we're installing
Wireshark. And this is basically asking
us if non-root users should be able to
capture packets. And if you remember
with TCP dump, well, we couldn't
actually start a capture without
prepending it with pseudo because we
need to be a root user or a super user
in order to capture packets and interact
with the network interface at that
level. And so I'm just going to go with
the default option here and say
no. Excellent. So we have it installed
now. And you'll notice if I just run
Wireshark and don't worry about the
interface yet. We'll get to this in due
time. But if I just start a capture,
well, you can see I'm getting this
error. And this is because I did not
start Wireark as pseudo. And so just
remember if you select that default
option there to prevent non-super users
from capturing packets, well, you're
going to run into this issue unless you
start Wireshark as a super user or
someone in the Wireshark group. And so
to fix this this time I'm just going to
run pseudo
wireark and I should be able to capture
packets with no
problem. Now there is a way to get the
latest and greatest release of wireark.
And to do that we would need to run a
couple of extra commands. And so I'll
list the commands below if you want to
install the latest release yourself. But
just know we won't need it for this
section. And so to do it, we would need
to add the Wireshark dev repository to
our package
manager. And after doing so, we would
just need to run a pseudo apt
update and then pseudoapp install
wireark. To download Wireshark on
Windows, we can go to wireshark.org and
click on get started. From here, you can
select the installer applicable to your
systems architecture. In this case, I
will choose the Windows 64-bit
installer. And once the download is
complete, we can run the
installer. And we can now go through
this wizard to guide us through the
installation process. Accept the license
agreement.
And here we can choose various
components that we want to include or
install with Wireshark. In this case,
you can see T-Shark is already selected.
And T-shark is a command line interface
version of Wireshark and is more
powerful than TCP dump or wind dump. We
won't get into covering it in this
section, but we can keep the defaults
here and just click on next. Choose
where you want to save the program. And
if you don't already have it installed,
it's going to install NPC for you as
well. This is required in order for
Wireshark to run.
Once this is finished, we can click next
and then
finish. And now we can just search for
Wireshark and run the
application. And I'm going to hop back
over to Linux now. But basically
everything we cover here is going to be
applicable to both the Windows and Linux
version of
Wireshark. So let's open up Wireshark
and take a quick tour. And I'll mention
that there are several options for us to
start Wireshark directly from the
command line. And there are several
options that we can provide as we do
that like specifying capture interfaces
or opening up specific pcap files. For
example, if I run pseudo wireshark with
the -ash i here and select the03
interface with the k
argument. Well, this will directly start
a capture on that emp3 interface.
However, I will just run pseudo
Wireshark to open up the welcome screen.
And so when you open Wireshark without
starting a capture or opening a capture
file, well, it will display this welcome
screen which lists any recent open
captured files if we had any. In this
case, we don't. And also the available
capture interfaces for capturing network
traffic. And so just at a high level in
terms of our user interface, you can see
we have the menu bar at the top here.
And this obviously contains various
menus for file operations, right? So, we
can open PECAP files. It's currently
grayed out, but we could save captures
as we start capturing packets. And we're
going to return to a lot of these
options here as we start capturing
packets. We also have the main toolbar
here, which is going to provide us quick
access to common actions, right? So,
like starting packet captures or
stopping them. We could restart our
packet capture. We can even open files
this way as well. We also have a section
here for capture filters, which we're
going to get into in more detail in a
future lesson. But the main area here is
our list of interfaces. And you'll
notice this is pretty similar to when we
ran TCP dump with the capital D argument
to list our
interfaces. You'll also notice this
little spark line here or this graph
indicating if a current interface has
packets going through it. And so this
can be helpful if you're trying to
figure out which interface you actually
want to capture packets from. Right? If
I just open Firefox and go to
google.com, well, we're going to start
to see a lot of traffic coming from our
various interfaces as we interact with
the internet.
And so we can select any of these
interfaces to capture from and we can
also select multiple. Right? So we have
the any option here to capture from all
interfaces or we can click and hold
control and select various other
interfaces to collect both at the same
time. Or I can hold shift and select
everything. And if we hover over any of
these interfaces, for example, this one
here, well, we can see its IP address
and any capture filters that are
applied.
So for example, let's start monitoring
on our local loop back interface. So in
this case, I'm going to select the loop
back interface here. And let's recreate
the same scenario that we've done a
couple times already with netcat. And in
doing so, we can get some simple and
easy to read packets to start to dissect
and understand the layout and feature
set of wire. And once we go through this
activity, well, we'll start loading in
some real pcaps containing malware like
we did with TCP dump. And so in this tab
here, I'm just going to start up netcat
and listen on port 1 2 3 4. And I'm
going to return to Wireshark and double
click the loop back interface here to
immediately start our
capture. So now that we're capturing
packets, I'm going to open up another
tab
here with control shift and t. And then
I'm going to connect with netcat on my
local host on port 1 2 3
4. and we should see the three-way
handshake taking place. And at this
point, I'm going to stop the capture.
And I'll just zoom in a little bit here.
We're now looking at what is referred to
as the main window. And Wireshark
further breaks down this main window
into three distinct sections. So, I'm
going to click on a packet here. And you
can kind of only see two here. This is
because of my screen size. So, if this
is happening to you, just go over to the
right here. And you should see this
little window here or this pane that got
cut off. So we can drag this into view
so we can see it more clearly. And so in
the top here we're going to see this
packet list pane. And this essentially
provides a summary of each packet. So we
can see we have different columns here
like the source and destination IP
addresses, the protocol, the length,
even a timestamp. And so once we click
on or select any of these packets, well,
we can see the details in the other
panes here are going to update. And I'm
just going to drag this more into view.
And so by default, we're going to see
this list of columns here. So we have
number here and this actually refers to
the number of the packet within the
capture file and this number is not
going to change even if we use any of
our display filters. This is something
that Wireark adds to make navigating
through packets easier. Next we have
time here and so this refers to a
timestamp of the packet and we can
actually change the presentation format
of the time stamp which we'll get into
shortly. Under source here we obviously
have the source address of where the
packet is coming from and of course
destination is where the packet is going
to. We have the protocol here which is
the abbreviation of whatever protocol is
being used in this case transmission
control protocol. We have the length of
each packet as well as the info column
here which shows additional information
about the packet content itself. In this
case we can see various things like the
flags and the window size and sequence
numbers very similar to what we were
looking at in TCP dump. And so I
mentioned this timestamp presentation.
Well we can change the format here and
the precision using this view menu at
the top. And so if we click on view and
then go to time display format. Well, by
default, Wireshark is going to display
the packets in seconds since the first
captured packet. The most common format
and typically best practice is to use
the UTC date and time of day or we can
also use the Unix timestamp with seconds
since
19701. In this case, I will switch it to
UTC date and time of day. And so next,
you can see we have the packet details
pane over here on the bottom left. And
this will contain a detailed protocol
breakdown of the packet that we select.
And any lines you see with this arrow to
the left, well, we can click on them to
expand and find out more information. In
this case, under transmission control
protocol, well, we can open up the
conversation completeness to see the
flags that were set. And on the right
here, we have the packet bytes pane
because what we're seeing here is the
hex output as well as the decoded asy
content of the packet itself.
And as we click on different areas in
the packet details pane, well, it's
going to highlight the related sections
within the packet bytes pane as well.
And so we can start going through some
of these layers, right? So we have the
frame here, and this will show us what
frame we're looking at and details
specific to the physical layer of the
OSI model. Next, you can see we have the
source and destination MAC addresses
from the data link layer. Additionally,
we have internet protocol version 4
here, which of course relates to the
network layer and we can identify the
source and destination address. So
again, this is the entire IP packet that
we're looking at. And lastly, of course,
in this case, we have the transmission
control protocol. And as we start
looking at some more packets, well,
we're going to see some more application
protocols and application data within
this packet details
pane. We can see at the top here, we
have the option to apply a display
filter. So, this is the filter toolbar,
and it allows us to quickly edit and
apply display filters. We're going to
cover display filters in much more
detail in the next
lesson. And at the very bottom here, we
can see we have the name of the pcap
file that we have open. In this case,
it's set to a temporary value because we
haven't actually saved this packet
capture yet. But this status bar here
can be very useful for us. For example,
if I start hovering over different
sections in the packet bytes pane here,
well, we can see that the status bar
here is going to update to the relevant
column names that we can then filter off
of once we start looking at display
filters. Another very useful option
available in Wireshark is packet
colorization. And so we can set up
Wireark so that it will colorize
different packets according to a
specific display filter that we set. And
so we could potentially use this to
emphasize various packets that we're
interested in. And so there are two
types of coloring rules in Wireshark. We
have temporary rules that are only in
effect until we quit the program. And we
also have permanent rules that are saved
in a preference file that are always
available and will always be applied to
whatever pcap we're looking at. And so
temporary rules can be added by
selecting a particular packet. And once
we have a packet selected, we can press
the control key along with one of the
number keys to start automatically
applying different colors to the
conversation. And so to permanently
colorize packets, we can click on the
view option here and go down to coloring
rules. If we click on this, well, we can
see a number of the default coloring
rules that Wireshark ships with. For
example, if we have a TCP reset packet,
well, it's going to be colored with this
red background and yellow text. If we
click on the green plus icon here, well,
we can create our own coloring rule
according to a specific display filter.
And we don't have to worry about this
yet. But let's see one of these default
rules in action. And so I'm just going
to start a new
capture. And in this case, I'm simply
going to
curl localhost and fetch just a random
file. And if we look back here, well, we
can see some more colors. In this case,
the port 80 traffic or the HTTP was in
green. In this case, because we had a
reset packet, well, that was in that red
background with yellow text. And so I
think this was a good start to
installing and introducing the general
UI of Wireshark. If it seems
overwhelming now, don't worry too much
because we're going to get into some
more practical analysis and everything's
going to start making sense once we
start actually looking at pcap files.
And so in the next video, we're going to
look at how we can use the power of both
capture and display filters to focus on
and narrow down specific network
traffic. And then we'll start analyzing
some real
pcaps. All right, welcome back to
Wireshark. And Wireshark allows us to
specify or limit the packet capture only
to packets that match a particular
capture filter. And Wireshark capture
filters are written in the lib pcap
filter language. And lucky for us, we
use this very same filter language when
we cover TCB dumps filtering options. So
we should be well accustomed to the
general syntax. And like with TCP dump,
we won't be able to cover every single
capture filter out there. But I'll cover
the basic syntax with common examples
and provide a reference to the
documentation for more examples below.
And so I'm just going to start up
Wireshark once
again. And capture filters should not be
confused with display filters, which
we're going to cover shortly. And so
capture filters are much more limited
and allow us to reduce the size of a raw
packet capture. The latter or the
display filters are used to hide some
packets from an already established or
captured packet list and offer a lot
more functionality with specific columns
and field names. And so obviously
capture filters are set before we start
a packet capture and cannot be modified
during the capture. Display filters on
the other hand, well, we don't have that
limitation and we can just change them
on the fly whenever we want. And so once
we're back in this welcome screen here,
well, we can find the capture filter
itself just above the list of
interfaces. And this is where we can
actually specify and type in our capture
filter. And if you remember, a lot of
this is going to be mostly review from
the TCB dump section. And so we have the
primitive elements, right? So these
include qualifiers like the host, right?
If we want to specify a particular host.
And you can see wire sharkark is giving
us some useful indicators here on how we
can complete the filter. And we also
have things like port, right? If we want
to specify a particular
port, we can also prepend this with like
source for source
port. We also have various operators,
right? So these include things like and
or or not. And we can combine these or
negate primitives that we covered to
create complex filter expressions. So
for example, if we only wanted to
capture traffic to or from 8.8.8 8.8.
Well, we can just type in host
8.8.8.8. If we wanted to capture traffic
to or from a range of IP addresses,
well, we can use the net qualifier here
and we can specify that range or that
cider
notation. If we wanted to be more
specific, we can specify the source net,
right? So, only coming from a range of
IP
addresses. If we wanted to capture only
DNS traffic, well, we could just use
port 53. If we wanted to capture all
Telnet traffic not from
10.0.0.5, well, we could specify port 23
for TNET and not source of the host of
10.0.0.5. If we wanted to capture any
non-HTTP and non-SMTP traffic on a
particular host, well, we could specify
the host, in this case, example.com and
not, and remember, we can wrap these in
parenthesis here to specify port 80 or
port 25. And I spelled and wrong.
And the not in this case is used to make
sure the negation applies to both port
80 and port 25. We can also get pretty
in-depth and specify lengths in bytes
and various payload signatures. And some
of these examples will be found in the
documentation link below. But the main
takeaway here is that capture filters in
Wireshark are used to limit the amount
of traffic captured by specifying our
criteria of the packets of interest. And
we can also take a look at some more
default examples by clicking the green
bookmark option here.
And if we have any filters that we use
frequently, well, we can add them to
this section as well. And so let's use
that example.com example. So if I
specify the host of example.com and not
port 80 or port 25, well, I'm going to
start capturing on
ENSP03. And remember, your interface
here connected to the internet might be
different. So if I open up the terminal,
I'm going to run netcat for
www.agample.com.
example.com and I'm going to try port
80. Well, we can see nothing was logged.
In this case, I'll try port 25. I'll
also add the verbose option
here. No, we're still getting nothing.
But what if I try a port that we didn't
specify, like 1 2 3 4. Well, we can see
in this case we did capture those
packets. And so, let's quickly talk
about saving a pecap file. So once we're
happy with the packets that we captured,
in this case let's say we are, we can go
ahead and click on file save as, which
allows us to save the current capture to
a file on disk. And the most common
formats that we can save the captures
are is of course this.pcap file, which
of course we're used to seeing through
TCP dump. And we also have this pcapng
file. And this is a more technically
flexible and extensible successor to the
default.pcap pcap file and is used as
the default file format in Wireshark
after version 1.8. But in this case,
I'll just choose a pcap file. You can
see we can name it as test.pcap and I'll
just click on
save. Okay, so once we have a pcap file,
but we can simply load it into Wireshark
for us as analysts to perform deeper
analysis. And I'll mention again,
Wireshark is not the best at handling
very large pcap files. And sometimes it
might actually be impossible due to the
system freezing up and crashing on you.
And so because of this, it's often a
good technique to carve through a very
large pcap file like a multi- gigabyte
file with something like TCP dump using
our lib pcap filters or just by making
sure you have good capture filters in
place initially to ensure we're not
flooding our file with unnecessary
noise. And so to open a pcap file in
Wireshark, we can head over to the file
menu here and click on open.
In this case, I'm going to head to the
pcaps folder within the wire directory
and then click on this
2021-09-14.pcap file. And this is the
file that we covered in the TCP dump
analysis section of the course. And so
I'll just double click on this file to
open it up. And notice if we go back to
the file tab here, we can also merge
multiple pcaps together. And so with
this option, we can actually merge
multiple pcaps into a single file. And
we can maintain the chronological order
of each packet. And this could be really
useful in situations where we've
captured traffic from different sources
or at different times, but we want to
analyze them more cohesively. But in
this case, we don't need to merge
anything. I just wanted to showcase that
option. And so now that we have a real
pcap loaded in, let's talk about display
filters. And so, as I mentioned before,
display filters can be applied in the
Wireshark interface after we've started
capturing packets or after the packets
have been captured. and they're used to
only pull back or return specific
subsets of packets that match our
criteria. And while it's similar to the
lib pcap language for capture filters,
well, wireark provides a display filter
language that lets us precisely control
which packets are being displayed using
multiple different columns and field
names. And so we can check for things
like the presence of a protocol or field
or the value of a specific field or even
compare two fields together. And so the
simplest display filter is one that just
displays a single protocol. And so to
only display packets containing a
specific protocol, well, we can type the
name of the protocol into Wireshark's
display filter toolbar. So to only
display TCP packets, well, I can just
type in TCP and hit enter. Similarly, to
only display packets containing a
particular field, well, we can type in
the name of that field into the toolbar.
For example, to only display HTTP
requests, well, we can type in HTTP
request. We can see it sort of has this
object and value
notation and so we can do things like
comparisons as well. So we can build
display filters to compare values using
a number of different comparison
operators. Right? So we have the
equality or the equal filter and this is
a very common filter where we can
specify if a specific field equals a
given value. For example, I can search
for the IP address field or add and I
can set if it equals a specific IP
address, right? like 1
192.168.0.1. In this case, we won't
return anything. But if I go back and
choose one of these IP addresses here,
like
103.232.55.148, well, we can see we're
only pulling back conversations where
that IP address is either the source or
destination. We also have different
operators like the greater than and less
than or greater than and equal to or
less than and equal to. And we're going
to cover some of these as we start
diving into more packets. We also have
some really useful operators as well
like the contains field. So in this case
we can filter packets where the
specified field contains a given value.
Right? So for example I can do HTTP
contains the word login. In this case
it's going to filter packets where the
HTTP payload contains that word. In this
case we don't have any matches but in
this case we can see this specific
packet is making a get request to the
service endpoint. So if I do HTTP
contains service, well, we should pull
back that exact packet along with any
others that mention the name service. If
you remember this specific packet
capture, well, we identified the audiodg
executable as an indicator of
compromise. In this case, I can do a
search for
audiodg.exe. And you can see we're
pulling back some relevant packets. And
like with capture filters, we also have
logical operators as well. So we have
things like and or or not. And we're
going to cover these in more detail as
we start going through the
analysis. And so these specific fields
that we use are going to be dependent on
what we're actually looking for, right?
And there's an extremely large variety
of fields and column names that we can
use. And we're going to pick up on the
most common and useful fields as we
start to analyze pcaps. And so now that
we covered the basic syntax in
components, I think it's probably best
to go through some examples. Right? So
we kind of covered this already, right?
If we wanted to only show HTTP traffic,
well, we can just type in the name of
the protocol. If we wanted to get more
specific, well, we can specify if the
request and the method of the request is
equal to post and we can pull back any
post requests. Similarly, we can change
this to get to pull back any get
requests. Instead of the method, I can
also search based off of the URI. In
this case, we can do
contains audio DG. And again, in this
case, we're pulling back any packets
where if we dig into the HTTP or the
hypertext transfer protocol, and if we
look at the actual URI within the
payload, well, we're going to match
audiodg.exe. If we only wanted to pull
back DNS traffic from a specific domain
name like example.com, well, we can
change this to DNS.query or
qry.name equalsample.com.
If we wanted to only pull back traffic
from a specific port like port 80, well,
we could run
TCP.port equals
80. Another extremely useful and
important option here is the ability to
both prepare and apply filters within
Wireshark. And so essentially any piece
of data that we're looking at within
Wireshark, whether it be any of the
columns here or any of the fields and
columns that we can extract from the
packet details itself. For example, let
me open up an HTTP request here. Well,
we can right click on the specific entry
or value or the column and from here we
can either select apply as filter or
prepare as filter. And if we choose
prepare as filter and click selected,
well, you can see it's going to add the
relevant matching syntax to the display
filter but not actually run the filter
yet. If I rightclick this again and
click on apply as filter, well, this is
going to immediately filter the packets
to what we
selected. Right? Right. So in this case,
we're pulling back the specific packet
where the URI contained
/service. And in my opinion, this is the
best way to learn how to create and edit
display filters in Wireshark. So feel
free to play around with some of these
filters and conditions and field names.
In the next lesson, I want to talk about
statistics within Wireshark, which are
another absolutely invaluable way for us
to break down and make sense of a
daunting and large pcap file. And then
we're going to finally walk through and
highlight some additional analysis
strategies. And so I'll see you in the
next
video. In addition to display filters
that can help us isolate interesting
traffic that we're looking for, well,
wireark offers a robust set of
statistical features to analyze captured
network traffic from a high level and is
one of the most important features we
have available to us when it comes to
making sense of a large pcap file. And
in my methodology, the statistics in
Wireshark is the best way to start our
analysis because it will provide us with
all the highle guidance and overview
that we need to start drilling into
things like interesting conversations
and top talkers and protocols of
interest, which we'll get into. And we
can find all of these statistics, of
course, under the statistics tab in the
top menu bar. And you can see there are
a lot here, and we're not going to cover
every single one, but we'll cover the
most important and useful statistics
that are going to help us for quick
wins. And so let's start out with the
first one here or the capture file
properties. And so if we click on this,
you can see we're going to be brought to
this window pane here. And this is going
to open the capture file properties
pane, which is going to cover a lot of
useful information and metadata about
the packet capture itself. Right? So the
file tab here, right? So under file
here, we can see things like the name
and the Shaw 256 hash of the actual pcap
itself. Under time here, we can see the
time stamp of when the first packet and
last packet was delivered. as well as
the elapse time between the first and
last packet. In this case, we have about
9 minutes. And this is going to be very
useful for us because we can use this
section to confirm that the pcap we're
looking at contains the actual traffic
that we're looking for. Right? So, if
we're handed a pcap file in an alert,
well, we need a way to confirm with the
client or the stakeholders that the file
we're about to investigate and spend
time analyzing actually contains the
traffic from the time frame of the
incident. And so we can avoid a lot of
wasted time and resources by checking
the time of the first and last packet.
We also get various well statistics as
well. Right? So we can see the total
amount of packets that were captured in
this file. And if we had a particular
display filter set, well, we can see the
amount of display packets as well. For
example, if I close this and just run
HTTP as our display filter and head back
to the capture file properties, in this
case, we only have 86 packets or 2.3% of
the packets that match with the HTTP
protocol. And so, next, let's look at
resolved
addresses. And in this case, we can see
wherever a DNS lookup was performed and
an IP address was mapped to a domain.
And so as we start scrolling down here,
well, we're going to start to see some
IP addresses on the left here and the
associated or resolved names over on the
right. And the hosts that are populated
here are typically taken from the DNS
answers within the capture
file. And so this saves us a lot of
manual work by looking through different
DNS queries and
responses. And so next here we have the
protocol hierarchy. And as the name
suggests, well, this window pane here
presents a hierarchical view of the
different protocols encountered within
the captured traffic. And it displays
statistics and calculations like the
number of packets and the bytes and the
percentage of bytes as well. And so
using this, we can easily identify which
protocols are predominant within the
traffic and figure out some quick wins
on if we can see any high volumes of
traffic on a suspicious protocol or
identify any protocols that might have
unencrypted connections that could
benefit us as we dig into the payloads
more
easily. And one important thing to note
is that it's going to use the current
display filter to aggregate this data.
In this case, we're returning a 100% of
the packets as HTTP, which isn't the
case for this pcap file. So, if I remove
the display filter and run this
again, well, you can see we're starting
to see some more protocols here. In this
case, we do have some HTTP traffic, but
we also have a lot of TLS or HTTPS
traffic as well.
So next let's look at
conversations and the conversation
statistics feature will organize traffic
based on the communication between
endpoints like IP addresses and ports
and it provides details like the number
of packets and bytes and the packet rate
for each conversation. And so by using
this well we can analyze communication
patterns and identify things like the
top talkers or the most predominant
talkers on the network. And for example,
this can be really useful as we can
potentially see if an internal IP is
reaching out predominantly to an IP we
don't recognize or perhaps one IP
address is making a large number of
requests to a number of different IPs
and maybe we're dealing with a port
scan. And so if we click on the IPv4 tab
here, well, we're going to get all the
IPv4 statistics. And in this case, we
can click on bytes two times so we can
sort it in descending order. And this
gives us a general breakdown on who was
talking or communicating with what
system the most. In this case, we can
see this internal address of
10.0.0.168 communicating with
103.23255.148. And we can see the amount
of packets that were delivered from A,
so address A to address B or the packets
that were delivered from address B to
address A. And if we notice an
interesting conversation here that we
want to dive into in more detail. So for
example, this top one here. Well, we can
right click on the conversation and what
do you know? We can prepare or apply it
as a filter. Well, we can choose which
direction we want to specify for the
traffic, right? Do we want to look at
either A going to B or B going to A or
only A going to B? So this gives us a
lot of easy options to filter off of.
For example, if I click on both A and
B, well, you can see the display filter
that it immediately applied.
And so I'll just clear that out. And
next, if we look at the endpoints tab
here, well, this is going to give us
insights on the individual host network
activities like the network traffic sent
and received and the packet count and
data size. And if I click on IPv4 again,
well, we can get a list of all of the
different endpoints that are included
within this pcap file. And this is kind
of similar to what we were painstakingly
doing manually with TCP dump when we
were piping things to cut and sort and
unique to pull back and aggregate the
top talkers. In this case, I can just
click on bytes here to sort the amount
of bytes or the amount of packets in
descending
order. Lastly, here we can also go down
to HTTP and look at any of the requests
that were made. And so with this option,
we can see all of the different HTTP
requests that were made to various
servers and URIs all in a very nice and
easy to understand
chart. Right? So if we scroll down here,
well, we can see this
103.232.55.148 address. And we can
immediately see the audiodg.exe endpoint
that was accessed. And so this can be a
very quick win for you if the pcap file
you're analyzing contains a lot of
unencrypted HTTP traffic.
And so moving on, we'll touch on this
some more later, but Wireshark allows us
to aggregate and rebuild an entire
stream of protocol specific packets like
TCP or HTTP. And in doing this, we can
understand the whole picture a lot
better. And this is something we tried
our darnest to do with TCP dump alone.
But Wireshark just makes this so simple
for us and is such a powerful option
when we want to see the entire
conversation. For example, I'm just
going to filter on HTTP traffic. And in
this case, I'm going to choose this
packet here, packet
1186. And if I right click on the packet
and go down to follow, well, I can
follow either the TCP stream or the HTTP
stream. And since the HTTP stream is
going to contain more details about the
HTTP payload, well, I'm going to click
on this, and we're going to be brought
to this amazing pane here that is going
to show us the entire conversation
between the two endpoints. And so we can
see that all of the requests here are in
that red color and all of the responses
from the web server are in blue. And so
we can see all of the headers as well as
any of the body content. Right? So we
can actually reconstruct this web page
if we really wanted to. And again, this
can be very useful in investigations
when you're dealing with an unencrypted
payload. We can also either select the
entire conversation or only the requests
here or only the responses, right? So we
can filter this more if we wanted
to. And so I mentioned packet numbers
earlier. Well, each packet captured in
Wireshark is going to be assigned a
unique sequential number. And this
packet number serves as an identifier
and is displayed in the packet list pane
as you can see here. And these can be
really important for us in terms of
referencing and analysis, right? So we
can actually track and log and reference
specific packets during analysis and
document them accordingly because these
packet numbers are chronological and
sequential and so they're not going to
change if we start applying things like
display filters. We also have some
useful navigation options around the
packet numbers themselves. For example,
I can click on the go option here in the
main toolbar and click go to
packet. In this case, I can type in a
packet number. For example, I'll type in
1,250. And if I click go to packet,
well, it's going to immediately
highlight this packet number for me. And
this can obviously be very useful when
we want to pinpoint and find a
particular packet by its number. We can
also mark specific packets as well. So
if I right click on any of these
packets, I can click on mark packet.
Alternatively, with a packet selected, I
can press CtrlM and it's going to mark
that packet for me.
And after doing so, I can go up to the
display filter and type in
frame.mmarked and set that to equal to 1
to only display marked packets. And so
obviously this can be very useful for
tagging a packet for later
review. And so lastly here we can export
various objects that are found within
our packet capture directly out of
Wireshark. And this is another extremely
useful feature here because you can
think of the scenario where a user
suspectedly downloaded malware like an
executable or a malicious PDF or a word
document. Well, if the connection was
over an insecure protocol like HTTP or
an unencrypted FTP server or an SMB
session or if we were doing some sort of
TLS inspection and had our own trusted
CA or encryption key log file, well, we
could potentially decrypt the data over
HTTPS as well. And by extracting these
files, we can do analysis that we're
already quite familiar with. So we could
extract the hashes of these files and
compare them against malware databases
like virus total. Or we could actually
submit these files for dynamic malware
analysis. Or in the case of a PDF or
office document, we could carve into
them and extract any malicious scripts
or embedded objects. And to do this,
it's honestly quite simple. I click on
file here and I can go down to export
objects. And you can see various
protocols here that we can search off
of. In this case, since we have a lot of
HTTP traffic, well, I'm going to click
on HTTP and we can see all of the
different files that were sent over the
wire. Particularly, we're aware of the
audg.exe file. And if we scroll down,
well, we can find the actual file
itself. And so, in this case, with it
highlighted, I'm going to click on the
save option. And you can see I can
actually save and extract the file from
the pcap file itself.
And so if I click on save here and back
in the terminal, I can run an ls with
the tac a flag because remember it was
saved with a dot at the beginning of the
file name. Well, we can see the
audiodg.exe file. And of course, I can
run a file on that file and we can see
it's a PE32
executable. And I of course can run the
Shaw 256 sum of the file as well.
And if I copy this file
hash, I can search for it on virus
total. And we can see 52 out of 72
security vendors and four sandboxes flag
the file as malicious. And so in doing
this exercise, we can really see how
useful Wireshark is for performing more
detailed inspection. This is just
something we could not really have done
with TCP dump.
And so now the past few lessons did
really contain a lot of information and
syntax and options. So let's take a step
back and put all of what we learned
together and run through a sample PCAP
in the next lesson. And so I will see
you in the next
video. Now that we've taken in quite a
bit of information, let's walk through
the general process for effectively
analyzing a pcap in Wireshark. And the
methodology we cover here can easily be
applied to any packet analyzing solution
or tool. But in our case, Wireark makes
all of this very easy for us with its
visualizations and statistics. And so,
let's get right into it and open up
Wireshark. And in this case, I'm going
to click on file and open. And I'm going
to select the
2023-2-3.pcap
file. And this is a public pcap exercise
that was provided by malwareanalysis.net
net and Palo Alto Network's unit 42
which is a fantastic resource for PCAP
samples that I'll cover in the
additional practice lesson and so all
credit goes to them for this sample and
so first once we have the sample open
the first thing I typically do in an
investigation is to set up the timestamp
so I can document consistently with a
common reference format and so to do
this we've already technically done it
in the previous lesson but I'll click on
view here under time display format and
make sure that I have UTC date and time
of day selected and we could choose a
Unix time stamp as well or that epoch
time. But for readability, I'll choose
this option. And depending on what time
stamps we have available to us, either
through the alert or a ticket, we might
need to modify or shift the time format
slightly to correlate things correctly.
But in this case, the default UTC will
work nicely for us. And so next, let's
follow our methodology, right? So we can
start from a high level or a zoomed out
overview and then highlight any
interesting conversations or end points
to focus on as we go through the pcap
file. And so to do this, what we can and
we should leverage Wireshark's
statistics. And so first I will go to
capture file properties. And we can see
that we have over 50,000 packets
captured within this file, which is
quite a lot. And so this is why it's so
important that we start from the top and
drill down as needed. If we look under
the time here, well, we can see that the
elapsed time between the first and last
packet was almost 3 hours, between
around 12:00 p.m. to 2:45ish.
And so again, this can be very useful
information to confirm before we start
diving in and investing resources and
time into analyzing a file that doesn't
contain the relevant
data. And so next, let's go down to
conversations. And from here, if I click
on the IPv4 tab and click on packets A
to B and filter this on the most amount
of packets, well, we can see that
10.0.0.149 communicated the most with
10.0.0.6. And so we can make note of
this 149 address as our likely culprit
for the victim because all of the
traffic originated from this IP address.
And we can see that it's communicating
the most with this 6 address which is
another internal IP address on the same
subnet as the victim with most of the
traffic heading in one direction. So
we'll make note of that for
now. And we can also note some of the
other top talkers. Right? So we have
208.187.122.74. We have
78.3167.7. We also have
5.75.25.43. And so next, let's take a
look at the protocol hierarchy and look
at the most common protocols and see if
we can identify any lowhanging fruit or
quick wins to base some more detailed
analysis off of. And usually what I like
to do is close all these arrows here to
make it more easy to look at. And
interestingly, we can see we have a lot
of net bios and SMB and LDAP and RPC,
even SMTP and ARP communication as well
with a small number of HTTP traffic with
only four packets. And since it's
unencrypted, we only have four packets.
So, let's start looking through the
small amount of HTTP traffic to see if
we can find where any potential
malicious traffic originated
from. And so first let's set up some
additional columns to show the source
and destination ports which are not
enabled by default within Wireshark. And
so we can do this by clicking on edit
and then go down to preferences. From
here we can click on columns. And so to
add a column we can click on the green
plus icon here. And in this case we can
set a title. And so I'll just call it
source port. And for the type here well
we have this drop down menu. In this
case, I can go down to source and find
source port
unresolved. Next, I can add a second
column for destination port. In this
case, I'll just call it desk
port. And under the type here, again,
very similarly, we can click on desk
port here, unresolved. And just to make
this easier to look at in the columns
view, I'm going to drag this up right
under
source. So, we have the source IP
address and then the source port.
Similarly, I will drag the destination
port here, right under destination. And
feel free to name these whatever you
like. Once we click okay, well, we can
see our screen refreshed here. And we
now have the source port and destination
port. And so we wanted to look at HTTP
traffic. So let's add a display filter
to just select that
protocol. And in doing this, we can
immediately identify those four packets.
And so let's open up the HTTP packet
details for this first packet here.
We can see an interesting result here.
The host value in the HTTP request
header is an IP address and not a domain
name, which is immediately suspicious to
me. If we go up to the get request here,
well, we can see it's making a request
to
86607.dat. And so, it's making a get
request to a DAT file, which is also
very suspicious. It almost feels like
that Mr. Robot episode where Elliot
finds the DAT file. And so, let's open
up this stream. So, I'm going to right
click on the packet and click on follow
and then HTTP
stream. And in this case, we're going to
start rebuilding the
conversation. And in the actual header
of this request, we see some even more
suspicious information. Under the user
agent, we have curl, the curl utility.
And typically, an end user would never
have curl as their user agent unless
they've executed some sort of script
either knowingly or unknowingly. So
again, this is very suspicious. And if
we look at the actual response from the
server where it's sending over this
attachment or this downloadable file,
well, we are seeing that common string
here of this program cannot be run in
DOSS mode. Additionally, we have MZ here
as the magic bytes or the file signature
at the very beginning of the file. And
if I go to Google here and just search
for list of file
signatures, well, we can get a list from
Wikipedia here of all the common file
signatures and what they mean. And these
file signatures are also known as magic
numbers or magic bytes. And they
typically tell operating systems what
kind of file to present. For example, if
I search for a JPEG, well, this is the
magic bite or the magic file signature
you'll find at the start of a JPEG file.
And this is what it looks like in
hex. So if I do a search for MZ here,
well, we're immediately seeing this is a
DOSS MZ executable. And if we click on
this, we can see the actual MZ stands
for the creator of the DOSS program. I
think it says it here. Yes, we can see
this hexadimal string here or this MZ
are the initials of Mark Zikowski, one
of the leading developers of MS
DOSS. So in this case, the endpoint here
or the victim downloaded an executable
file from this web server using the curl
utility. And if you remember, we could
have actually found this using the HTTP
statistics here under requests. You can
see immediately we are finding this
86607.dat
file. And so let's continue gathering
IoC's. So specifically we have the name
of the file and its URL and the IP
address that is associated with hosting
it. But let's also extract the file
itself so we can gather its hashes. And
so of course if you remember to do that
we can go under file export objects and
click on
HTTP. And in this case we can see there
is a certificate here which we don't
really need to worry about. But we do
have this file. And if I highlight it
and click on save, well, we can save it
to our folder here. And so now that
we've extracted it, I'm going to back
out of this directory where I saved it.
I'm just going to run a file on
8667.dat. And we can see, of course, it
is a p32 executable. In this case, a
Windows DL file. And I can simply run
Shaw 256 sum to get the hash of the
file. And of course, we want to make
note of this in our documentation and in
our ticketing software. And so now it's
just a matter of doing file reputation
checks that we're very used to doing
already from the fishing section, right?
So we can check virus total and paste in
the
hash. And of course it's being
flagged. We can check the malware
bizarre database in this case under
search syntax here. We can see that we
can specify a SHA 256 hash using this
syntax
here. And if we run that, we can see we
have a match in this case to Quackbot.
And so it looks like this file hash is
associated with the Quackbot malware
family. And so we've successfully
identified a number of IoC's that
resulted in the infection of the victim
machine here. We've also determined
through our analysis and research that
the specific type of malware is
Quackbot. And so let's do some more
research into Quackbot and see if we can
discover any post compromised IoC's or
tactics that we might be able to
additionally identify in our PCAP
sample. And in this Sofos article here,
they discovered an infected host
performing an ARP scan on the internal
network to discover if there are any
other active IP addresses that they
could maybe pivot
to. Very similar activity here in this
Canadian Center for Cyber Security
alert in which they've identified CACbot
performing an ARP scan in order to
discover other endpoints on the network.
Specifically, they're mapping it to
MITER
T1016. And we're going to get into the
MITER attack framework in a lot more
detail in the threat intelligence
section. But if we look at the actual
software categorization of CACbot
itself, well, we can see associated
techniques used particularly under the
technique of
T1016. Well, we can see another
reference to using
ARP. In this article here, we can see
that it was using SMB protocol to spread
across a network.
And in this scroll article here, we can
see that it was also discovered
exfiltrating emails in an email thread
hijacking
attack. And so if you recall, along with
IP and TCP traffic, we did actually see
a large amount of ARP traffic in our
protocol hierarchy. And so with that in
mind, we can check our PECAP for any
indicators of an attacker performing an
ARP scan from the compromised victim
device. And an ARP scan or an address
resolution protocol scan is a technique
that attackers commonly use to identify
active IP addresses within a compromised
network. And so these scans operate at
the MAC address layer where a device
will send ARP queries to the broadcast
MAC address. And the purpose of these
queries is to discover which IP
addresses respond and are currently in
use or active within the network
segment. And so an ARP scan will
typically involve a client sending ARP
requests to sequential IP addresses
within a network. And so if we start
seeing some sequential queries, this
will be a telltale sign of an ARP scan
and suggest that an attacker might be
attempting to map out the network by
identifying which IP addresses respond.
And so to find this traffic, well, we
can use the following Wireshark
filter. In this case, we can filter on
the ARP protocol. And additionally, we
can look at the Ethernet destination of
that broadcast address. And the
broadcast address is two Fs with a colon
six times.
And so if we run this, well, we can
immediately see all of these broadcast
queries, right? So if we look under
destination, it it is to the broadcast
address. And if we look under the info
column here, well, this is basically the
query that is being asked through the
address resolution protocol, right? So
who has
10.0.0.248? And they're asking tell me
as the host address here. And as we
scroll down, well, we can see the IP
addresses are descending. And this is a
clear indication of an ARP scan. And at
this point, we can infer that the
attacker who compromised the machine was
attempting to find any other active
machines within the network to
potentially probe or move laterally to.
And so, if an attacker manages to
identify any active IP addresses within
the network, well, they'll likely
attempt to ping these systems to see if
they're alive and if they can get a
response before performing additional
port or service scans. In this case, we
can use the ICMP
filter to see if we can find any ICMP
echo requests or replies.
And in this case, we have four packets,
two requests and two replies.
Interestingly enough, it looks like the
attacker managed to identify
10.0.0.6 as well as
10.0.0.1. And so we can also check if
the attacker performed any kind of port
scanning on these identified IP
addresses to see if there were any
lateral movement or post compromise
actions that they might have performed
on them. In this case, I'll change the
display filter to IP.ADR for address and
set that to equal to 10.0.0.1.
0.1. And if I run this, well, we can
identify a number of ports that the
attacker tried probing on the 10.0.0.1
endpoint. By the looks of it, we can see
a number of incomplete TCP handshake
attempts and a number of reset flags
that were set as well. Specifically for
port 445, 139, and port 80 as
well. And so when we were looking at the
protocol hierarchy, we also saw some
SMTP traffic. And considering this is
unencrypted traffic, we can also take a
look to see if we can uncover anything
interesting. So in this case for the
display filter, I'll choose SMTP in
which we get a number of packets
returned. And if I scroll to the top
under info, I can see an authentication
login packet. So this is interesting. So
I'm going to right click on this and
click on follow TCP stream. And in this
case, we can get an entire conversation
view of what was received in blue and
what was sent in red.
Particularly we can see under the off
login here some B 64 encoded
data and so what I'm going to do is copy
this entire conversation here of B 64
data for this authentication
login and I'll head over to the ever
useful cyersh I'm going to paste in that
conversation here and just clean it up a
bit by removing these
numbers and now I'm just going to drag
over from base
64 and we can immediately see the
username that was entered with this
email address as well as the password
that the attacker tried as
well. And in this case, it looks like
the authentication failed. However, we
might have identified some potentially
compromised user credentials. And
obviously, we don't have the
organizational context here, but this
kind of thing is of course worth noting
as well and might expand the scope of
the investigation. And so a very common
goal for attackers once they gain access
is to perform actions on objectives and
excfiltrate data from a compromised
system or abuse services in some way to
escalate privileges and gain access to
an active directory domain controller.
In both cases, this can typically be
done through SMB or the server message
block protocol which enables file
transfers between Windows hosts. And in
an AD environment, Windows hosts and
servers will commonly communicate with
the domain controller as part of normal
system operations. However, certain
types of activity like file transfers
over SMB can be
suspicious. And fortunately, Wireshark
makes it very easy for us to view
objects transferred over SMB. And like
we did with HTTP, well, I'm going to
head over to file under export objects.
In this case, instead of HTTP, I'm going
to select SMB for server message
block. And so at the top here, we can
see a number of files related to group
policy objects or GPOS as specified by
GPT.in. ini or gpt
tempmplate.inf. And these files are
actually quite common to see in an
active directory environment and they
allow administrators to manage settings
and configuration centrally for users
and computers within the domain. But
Windows executable or DL files within
SMB traffic can be very suspicious. It
could also be benign, for example, in
the case of Windows Server Update
Service. But randomly named DLL files
like these are pretty suspicious and
warrant further investigation. And it
looks like we have six potentially
suspicious DLL or DL.cfg files and they
were all transferred to the 10.0.0.6
host. And in the case of this PECAP
file, well, I'll pull the curtain a bit
here and say the 10.0.0.6 is the domain
controller of this network. And
typically when investigating a file like
this, well, we would know the IP address
of the domain controller as well. And so
what I'll do is go up to text filter
here, and I will just search for DLL.
And this will list just the six files
here. And I will just save each of these
files one by
one. And I'll just make a directory for
them called
SMB. Then I will move every file with a
DLL into the SMB
folder. And from here I'm going to run a
file on all of these files. And we can
see that half of them here are in fact
Windows DLS. And all of the CFG files
here appear to just be data binaries.
And so if I run Shaw 256 sum on all of
the files as well, well, we can see that
all of the DLL files all have the same
hash. And if you did note this in your
documentation, well, this is the exact
same hash of the initial CACbot DLL file
that we discovered over HTTP at the
beginning of the infection. And so in a
real world scenario, we would typically
want to direct our focus now to the
system or the host that received this
malware. In our case, the 10.0.0.6 or
the domain controller.
And we would do this either through our
SIM system and correlate logs that way
or through various EDR logs or
additional PECAPS from this host itself
as it seems very likely that the
attacker attempted to move laterally and
continue compromising the network.
And so to sum up our analysis, we were
able to start from a highle view and
look through our statistics and
conversations and protocols in order to
carve through the pcap and focus on
interesting packet streams and
lowhanging fruit to discover the initial
vector of malware infection and
compromise. And as we started to
identify the specific type of malware
infection that we were dealing with, we
were able to identify several post
compromise artifacts and indications of
host discovery and lateral movement
within the network. There were also a
number of other indicators associated
with CACbot within this pcap file itself
related to things like TLS certificates
and VNC activity. However, those
investigations are a bit out of scope
for this section, but I will include the
write up from unit 42 if you'd like to
investigate them further. And
admittedly, this was quite an involved
walkthrough and I wanted to cover all of
the important methodology steps and
features that we have available to us as
analysts within Wireshark. And obviously
we can't cover every single scenario and
indicator that you might come across in
the field. Which is why it's more
important to build up a methodology of
approaching pecaps from a high level
first and leveraging things like
statistics and aggregations to identify
interesting conversations and top
talkers or IP addresses. From there we
can zoom in and do more in-depth
analysis on these conversations, right?
Like what protocols are they speaking?
What ports are they talking to? Can we
follow any of the TCP or HCP streams? Or
what objects can we extract? Right. And
so as we identify more information and
start putting the puzzle pieces
together, we can zoom back out and
identify other hosts or conversations of
interest and repeat the process. And so
in the challenge following, you'll be
put to the test to see if you can
complete a network traffic analysis
investigation on your own. But don't
worry, I will be here the whole way if
you need a walk through. And so with
that, I will see you in the next video.
Now that we've gone through network
traffic analysis, let's shift our focus
over to network intrusions and how we
can detect and prevent network threats
both proactively and reactively. As I've
mentioned earlier in the course,
intrusion detection systems or IDS and
intrusion prevention systems or IPS are
important components in network security
that SOCKS use to proactively monitor
and actively prevent network intrusions
and attacks. And so at a high level, an
IDS or an intrusion detection system is
a device or a software application that
monitors the network or system
activities for malicious traffic or
actions or policy violations based on
predefined rules or known malware
signatures or through things like
anomaly and behavior-based detection.
And IDS's are primarily designed to
alert and identify and report any of
these policy violations. And they can do
this through monitoring and analysis.
Right? Right. So, an IDS is going to
continuously monitor network traffic and
actually do things like open up and
analyze data packets and log files to
detect abnormal patterns that might
indicate a potential attack. And when
suspicious activity is detected, well,
these IDS's can generate alerts and
notify the sock of potential threats.
And these alerts can be configured to
provide detailed information about the
nature and the source of the threat or
the network or the endpoint and could
potentially conduct some automated IoC
extraction. And typically all of these
alerts will be forwarded to the SIM
system. And the information that will be
forwarded will be through logs. So an
IDS is going to log all of its monitored
events which can be very useful in
investigations or incident response
scenarios and will assist us with things
like correlation and compliance
reporting and also provide future threat
detection capabilities with the IoC's
and signatures that it detects. And
typically an IDS is going to be deployed
out of band. So essentially not in line
with the network traffic. This is
because it doesn't need to sit in
between and actually intercept and drop
specific packets. It can do all of its
monitoring passively. And since they
operate passively, well, they're a lot
easier to scale and less of a burden on
the network performance and throughput
since there isn't that single choke
point of having an ID system in between
traffic. On the other hand, an intrusion
prevention system or an IPS is more of a
proactive security solution that's
designed to detect and prevent
identified threats in real time. And so
unlike an IDS, which is primarily a
monitoring and alerting tool, well, an
IPS can take a step further and actually
take immediate action to block or
mitigate malicious activity as it's
occurring. And so it does this through
traffic inspection. So an IPS is going
to inspect all of the network traffic at
a deeper level and actually analyze
packet contents as it sits in between
the traffic and intercepts them. And
when it detects suspicious activity or
anything that violates its predefined
rules, well, an IPS can block the
offending packets and actually drop them
from the network and prevent them from
reaching their intended destination. And
similarly, they can terminate
connections that are deemed harmful or
anything that goes against its rules,
which can stop any ongoing
attacks. And similar to an IDS, well, an
IPS can also generate alerts and log
events for any analysis and
recordkeeping purposes.
And so an IPS is typically going to need
to be deployed inline because it needs
to actively inspect and control the
traffic flow. And so a consideration
here is that it can actually introduce
some latency since it needs to actively
process and filter traffic in real time.
And so diving even deeper, well there
are two main types of IDS or IPS
systems. And the first here is a
network-based IDS or IPS. And these
systems will operate of course on the
network level. And so they can inspect
and analyze all of the traffic flowing
through the
network. On the other hand, we have
hostbased ids and IPS systems as well.
And these operate as the name suggests
at the host level and they can focus on
individual systems or endpoints rather
than the entire network. And so these
appliances can monitor activities on the
actual host. So things like file system
changes or login or application
behavior. It can look into processes
being spawned or files being accessed or
any registry changes. And of course, in
these cases, well, it can alert and log
and actually block malicious host
actions from taking place. And so with
all of these network and hostbased IDS
and IPS appliances, well, we often have
various means for detecting and
preventing
threats. For example, we have
signaturebased detection. And this
involves comparing network traffic or
host activities against a database of
known attack patterns or what we call
signatures. And when a match is found,
an alert can be triggered indicating a
potential threat. And so signature-based
detection is really effective at
identifying known threats, but it can
struggle with detecting things like zero
days or variance of known exploits
because it's comparing all of its data
against a
database. On the other hand, we have
behavior-based detection. And
behavior-based detection focuses on
identifying abnormal or suspicious
behavior within a network or a host. And
rather than relying on predefined rules,
these systems analyze deviations from a
normal pattern of activity or a
baseline. And so because it's not
focused on hard-coded signatures or
rules, well, it has a better chance of
detecting previously unseen threats
because it's looking at the actual
behavior on the endpoint or the network
itself.
But the key here is that you need to
have an effective baseline in place.
Otherwise, these systems are prone to
generating a lot of false positives if
the normal behavior is not accurately
defined. We also have rule-based
detection. And so rule-based detection,
as we've talked about earlier, involves
the creation and enforcement of specific
rules or policies that can govern
acceptable network or host behavior. And
so rulebased detection is highly
customizable, right? So we can tailor it
specific to the security requirements of
our organization. The downside here is
that it requires a lot of upkeep and
maintenance to remain effective against
ongoing
threats. And so when we look into Snort
in the next lessons, we're typically
going to focus here on rulebased
detection. And the last thing I'll cover
here on the slide is the diagram on the
right. And this is what's referred to as
the known unknown matrix, also known as
the Johari window. And this is a
framework that's used to understand the
knowledge about information and how we
actually categorize it. And so in the
context of a sock, it can help us
categorize and understand different
types of threats and detection methods.
Right? So this matrix is obviously
divided into four quadrants. And in the
top left, we have the known known. And
these can be thought of as threats or
vulnerabilities that are both known to
the organization and attackers. And so
information in this quadrant is well
understood and documented. And our
defenses can be specifically tailored to
address these threats. And in the top
right, we have the known unknowns. And
these are threats or vulnerabilities
that are known to the organization but
not necessarily to the public or to the
attackers. And this can include things
like internal vulnerabilities that the
organization is aware of but have not
been exploited yet. In the bottom left
we have the unknown known and these are
threats or vulnerabilities that are
known to the attackers but not the
organization. And obviously this is a
critical area to focus on as it
represents blind spots in our
organization defenses. And lastly, we
have the unknown unknowns. And these are
threats that are unknown to both the
organization and attackers. So these can
be new emerging threats or zero-day
vulnerabilities that have not been
discovered yet. And so to completely
generalize this nuanced concept that
probably shouldn't be generalized, well,
we can think of signaturebased detection
as highly effective against known
threats. So the known known, but it kind
of fails against unknown threats. On the
other hand, behavior-based detection is
really good at identifying anomalies.
And so, it's really good at detecting
known unknowns and some unknown knowns,
but it can also generate a lot of false
positives. And lastly, rulebased
detection can balance known and unknown
threats, but struggles on completely new
threats because it relies on predefined
rules. Okay, let's shift our focus and
talk a little bit about Snort. And so
Snort is an open-source network-based
IDS and IPS system managed by Cisco and
it's a pretty popular choice in the
industry and is also integrated into a
number of security solutions as well
primarily due to its effectiveness in
real-time traffic analysis and packet
logging
capabilities. And so Snort is really
versatile and is capable of detecting a
wide range of network attacks and
probes. And we also have the power to
ingest a wide range of community curated
rules and also create our own custom
rules. And so the list is basically
endless when it comes to what we can
detect with Snort. And so Snort was
originally created back in 1998. And
since then, it's evolved into one of the
most widely deployed IDs and IPS
solutions globally. And over the years,
Snort has undergone more and more
development and has gained a large
community of developers that are
maintaining the rules to keep Snort's
detections up to date with the latest
and greatest attacks out there. And so,
the two major versions of Snort in use
today are the more common Snort 2, but
also Snort 3.0. And there are some
notable differences between the two like
multi-threaded support and scalability
improvements and also different
configuration systems using Lua and
Snort 3. But in these lessons, we'll
focus on Snort 2 due to its widespread
use and accessibility of rule sets and
also detailed documentation and also the
likelihood that you'll encounter it in
professional environments because not
every organization or security solution
has begun migrating to Snort 3. And so
having a familiarity with Snort 2 is
very useful to have and will give you a
great foundation to migrate if needed.
And so Snort can operate in three
primary modes. The first is the sniffer
mode. And so in this mode, Snort is
going to read network packets and
display them on the console. And so this
is very similar to TCP dump with a bit
more functionality. So something like
T-Shark or Wireshark in the command line
as well. The second mode is the packet
logger mode. And so again like with TCP
dump, Snort can log the packets into
files on a disk. And so of course this
is obviously useful for us if we want to
do offline analysis later on. And so the
third mode is the most advanced mode and
the mode that we'll focus on in this
course is the network intrusion
detection and prevention mode. And so
this is where Snort actively monitors
the network traffic against defined
rules and can take actions like generate
alerts or block or drop traffic to
prevent potential intrusions. And these
predefined rules can be ingested through
community rule sets or through threat
intelligence capabilities or developed
in-house with custom rules which we're
going to take a look at. And so rules
really are the main core of how Snort
operates. And similar to firewall rules,
Snort rules allow the system to inspect
network traffic and then make decisions
or take actions based on the
criteria. And so let's go ahead and
install Snort for the first time. And so
I've just opened up the terminal. And in
this case, I'm just going to run
pseudoapp install snort and then hit
enter. You might need to enter your
password here if you haven't done so
already. And when we're prompted here,
we can just hit capital Y and hit
enter. So when we're installing Snort,
you're going to see this configuration
screen pop up. And so in this case, it's
asking us for the address range of our
local network. And so this is going to
depend on your current VM setup. And so
to find out this information, I'm going
to press control shift and t to open up
a new terminal tab.
And in this case, I'm just going to run
the if config
command. You can also use the newer IP
command to figure out the same
information, but I guess I just have old
habits here. And if I look under my
ENP03 interface, again, yours might be
named differently, but I can see this
inet of
192.168.1.4 and this is my IP address.
Additionally, I can see the net mask
here or the subnet mask of 255.255.25.
255.0. And so this means I am on the
192.168.1.0/24 network. And we could
also run the IP command and give it the
A and the S argument. And in this case,
if we look under
ENTP0S3, well, we will see
192.168.1.4, which is my IP address, as
well as the slash notation or the cider
notation of the network that I'm on. So,
in this case, we can copy this, but make
sure if you're on a /24 that you change
this to a zero. And so, I'm going to
head back over to my screen here with
the configuring snort
window and just type in the address
range for my local network. And from
here, I can just hit
okay. All right, it's successfully
installed. So if I clear this and then
run snort with the tactac version, well
you can see I'm pulling back version
2.9.20. And we can also see that along
with the installation, it made sure we
had the following dependencies. So we
have lib pcap here. And we're actually
used to seeing this dependency because
this is the interface for user level
packet capture and it gives Snort the
capability to capture network packets
which of course Snort needs to inspect
and analyze the traffic. And we're
already used to this library from using
TCP dump and
wireshark. We also have PCRE here and
this stands for Pearl compatible regular
expressions. And so this library or
package gives us the ability to use
things like pattern matching and regular
expressions within our snort rules. And
lastly here we have zib and this is just
a compression library used for data
compression and decompression.
So before we jump into the configuration
files, in a typical organizational
deployment, well, Snort's listening
network interface will operate in
promiscuous mode. So it can effectively
monitor and analyze all of the network
traffic. Promiscuous mode is a network
interface configuration where the
network card captures all of the packets
on the network regardless of their
destination address. Right? So normally
a network interface card or a nick is
only going to process packets addressed
to it. If we turn on promiscuous mode,
well, we can actually process and
intercept and log all of the network
packets traveling through the network,
even if they're not destined for our IP
address. But we don't really need to
worry about this configuration at the
moment because for this lab exercise,
we're going to keep everything local to
simplify the setup and avoid us needing
to spin up multiple VMs. Okay, so I'm
just going to clear this out. And so the
main configuration files that we need to
know about to use and operate and well
configure Snort are typically found in
the Etsy/Snort directory after we
install it. So if I just CD over to that
directory, it's under Etsy and then
Snort. And if I run an ls with an al,
well, we can see a number of files and a
directory here for
rules. And so this snort.com file, this
is the primary configuration file for
Snort. and it's going to define all of
our main settings and components and
variables for Snort's operation. And we
also have this rules directory here. And
so this directory contains all of the
predefined rule files that Snort is
going to use to detect specific patterns
of malicious activity. So if I run ls
with attack a under the rules directory
here, well, we can see a large list of
default rules that come shipped with
Snort. For example, if I just cat out
one of these
files, for example, I'll pick the
backdoor.ules rules
file. Well, we can see a number of rules
that have been defined. And this might
look like gibberish at the moment, but
we will go through the structure of a
rule. And we're going to look into
writing our own rules as well. And so
before we do anything, it's going to be
best practice for us to make a copy of
the configuration file in case we make
any mistakes or if we want to revert
back to the default configuration in
case we run into issues.
And so if you remember snort.com is the
main configuration file. We can also see
that only root can read and write to it
and only members in the snort group can
read this
file. And so if we want to make a copy,
we're going to need to run pseudo. And
then I'm just going to provide the copy
command. In this case, I'm going to copy
the snort.com file and I'm just going to
name it
snort.com.back or bak, which is a common
syntax for backup files.
So you can see here we have this
configuration backup file
now. So now let's open up the
configuration file and take a look
around. And to do this I'm going to run
pseudo and then nano
snort.com. And we're now taking a look
at the configuration file. And if we
scroll down we can see all of the
different things that we can set and
configure within this file. So we can
set things like the network variables or
the decoder information or base
detection engines or pre-processors or
output plugins. Under seven here we can
customize our rule set which we're going
to do in a
second. First here I'm going to scroll
down to set the network variable section
or step one
here. And so this is where we can
specify the subnet that Snort is going
to monitor. And if you remember we
actually did this and we configured our
home network while we were installing
Snort. So in my case that /24 network
that I provided is set to the home net
variable. And this any statement here
means that the variable will include all
of the IP addresses in the network
range. And so we could just leave this
as is. But if we wanted to change this
value or hardcode it, well I can just
delete the variable here and put
192.168.1.0/24. Similarly, we have the
external net variable as well. And as
the comment says here, we can just leave
this as any. And the reason being is
that we ideally don't want to confine
the external or internetf facing network
space to a particular subnet as of
course attacks can come from anywhere.
And so we don't want to tell Snort to
only consider a specific network range
as
external. And we could leave all of
these remaining variables just as they
are. But essentially, if we wanted to,
we could list specific hosts or IPs that
relate to critical or important servers
or resources on the network, right? like
HTTP or web servers or email servers or
DNS
servers. And at the bottom here, we can
see this rule path variable which
currently points to
etsy/snort/rules. And this was the rules
folder that we were quickly taking a
look at. And so we can just leave this
as is because this is where we're going
to place all of our custom rules. And so
I'm going to scroll all the way down now
to section
7. And in section 7, this is where we
can customize our rule set.
And this first specification here, you
can see we're including our rule path
and then the local rrules file. And so
this is a specific file name to contain
and write all of our custom rules in.
And as we scroll down, we can see a
number of rules in white here that have
not been commented out. And so these are
active rules. And anything in blue here
or with the pound sign at the beginning
of the line, well, these rules have been
commented out or deactivated. And so
Snort is not going to look at any of
these rules, but it will parse through
and look at these rules. And so because
we want to start writing custom rules
and learn how we can write custom rules,
well, we don't want these default ones
getting in the way. And so let's go
ahead and comment out all of these
default rules. So to do this, let's find
the first line of a custom rule. In this
case, it's this
attack-responses.ruules file. And I'm
just going to hold the shift key and
then arrow down to start highlighting
all of these lines.
And while still holding shift and the
down arrow key, I'm going to go all the
way to the
bottom. Then with all of these lines
selected, I'm going to let go of the
shift key and then I'm going to press
the escape key and the number three at
the same time to add a pound sign or the
comment symbol to the beginning of each
line. And in this case, you can see that
we've commented out all of these rules.
And so now all we need to do is just
press controll and x to escape. And then
when we're prompted to save the modified
buffer, we're just going to hit yes or
the y
key. And so now we can test our
configuration changes. And as always,
it's best practice that if we make any
changes to a configuration file, well,
we should test the changes to check if
we've broken anything. And so to test
our configuration file, we can just run
pseudo snort with the capital T option
to test and then the C argument to
specify the location of our
configuration file. In this case, it's
under Etsy snort
snort.com. And if we run this, we should
get the test output. And we can see here
that Snort successfully validated the
configuration and there were no issues.
If I scroll up here, we should be able
to find the amount of rules that were
detected. And you can see under
initializing rule chains, well,
currently we have zero snort rules read.
This is because we commented out all of
those rules, which is
perfect. All right, so now that we're
all set up here, let's take a very quick
look at the three main modes that Snore
offers. And if you recall those modes
are the sniffer mode, so much like TCP
dump or the packet logger mode where we
can actually save packets to a file and
also the IDS IPS mode which we're going
to focus on in the later
lessons. And so to run snort in the
sniffer mode, we just need to run pseudo
snort and then just simply provide the
name of the interface much like TCP
dump. In this case, ENP03 for
myself. And now that it's running, well,
we can make some network requests. So,
in another tab here, I'm just going to
curl
google.com. And if I hop back over,
well, we can see all of the packets that
were logged. And we can see basically
the packet header here. And so, I'll
just cancel out of that. And so, to
cancel out of this, I press C. And you
might run into this bug where it just
seems to be hanging after you tried to
cancel it. In this case, I'm going to
send over some more packets to
google.com basically by curling the
google.com URL again. And for some
reason, doing that seems to stop
whatever is hanging.
And so this time I'm going to run snort
again in packet sniffer mode. And in
this case I'm going to provide the tac e
argument to allow us to see the protocol
headers like the IP or the TCP headers.
And so if I run this again, I'm going to
curl google.com once again and hop back
over. Well, we can start to see things
like the TCP header with the time to
live, the type of
service, even things like the sequence
number and acknowledgement number and
the window size.
So, I'm going to cancel this out once
again. And of course, it's hanging. I'm
going to curl google.com, send some more
packets over, and apparently
everything's fine. The last mode here
I'll show you is TACD. And much like
with TCB dump, this is going to allow us
to get the payload output in hex and
ASI. And this time, I'll curl
example.com with the HTTP
protocol. And if we scroll up, we can
see the actual packet. In this case, we
have the response or the HTML response
from the example.com website. If we
scroll up to the first response packet,
well, we can even see things like the
HTTP
headers. And for example, here is our
actual request, our get request that we
made with the curl utility as a user
agent. All right. So that was much like
when we passed the capital X argument to
TCP dump. And in fact, we can actually
provide this capital X argument to Snort
itself. And this will dump the full
packet details including the hex and
ASI. So it's pretty much the same
command. And so let's quickly cover the
packet logger mode with Snort as well.
And so once again, this is quite similar
to TCP dump where we can capture packets
using Snort and then output them to a
file for later offline
analysis. And so to use the packet
logger mode, well, I'm just going to run
the same command but provide the TAC L
argument.
And the default output folder here is
going to be under var log snort. But we
can also configure the default output
directory in the snort.config file as
well. Or in this case, we can specify a
location within the command line itself.
And in this case, I'm just going to hop
over to the home directory and make a
sample directory here called logs. And
I'll just hop inside that
directory. And this time I'm going to
provide the tac l argument to snort and
just provide a period to specify the
current working directory.
And so now that we're sniffing, I'm
going to make another curl
request. And in this case, we can't
actually see the packets logged to the
console because they're being logged to
this file. And so I'm going to cancel
out now. And again, I'm going to have to
curl so we can quit properly. And then
if I run an ls, well, we can see this
snort log here with the Unix timestamp
as part of the file
name. And since we run snort with
pseudo, well, this log file is also
going to be owned by
root. And so we can read in this file
using snort just by running pseudo snort
with the tac r flag. And in this case I
will just provide the name of the log
file. And if we scroll up we can start
to see some of these packets. And there
is also going to be a number of details
at the bottom
here. Similarly we can also run pseudo
tcp dump with the same tac r flag and
provide the same log file. And so you
can see here that we can open up
everything that we captured in Snort
well into something like TCP dump or
WireArk. And so this was a great start
into the introduction and installation
configuration and overview of the basic
Snort features. And so in the next
lesson, we're going to spend all our
time with the IDS and IPS features and
understanding and building out rules and
catching some real attacks.
In this lesson and the remaining Snort
lessons, we're going to focus on its
bread and butter, the IDS and IPS mode.
And so with this mode, we're going to
leverage predefined rules to process an
action network traffic. And so to be
able to write effective Snort rules, we
first need to understand the generic
rule syntax and its components. And
fortunately, the structure in Snort
version 2 is pretty
straightforward. And so here's an
example of a Snort rule. And snore rules
are divided into two logical sections.
On the left here we have the rule header
and on the right we have the rule
options. And so all of the text up to
the first parenthesis there is the rule
header. And the section enclosed within
parenthesis is the rule
options. And the rule header contains
things like the rules action, the
protocol, the source and destination IP
addresses and ports as well. And the
rule option section contains things like
the alert message. So what's going to be
logged when this alert is fired and also
which parts of the packet should be
inspected to determine if the rule
action should take place. And we can get
pretty granular here with the details or
conditions that trigger the rule. We can
do things like content matching or look
at the packet size or specific flags
within the protocol headers. And so to
break down the components of this rule
here, you can see we first have the word
alert. And this is what is known as the
rule action. And so this specifies the
action to be taken when the rule is
matched. In this case, alert means that
well, an alert is going to be generated.
But we also have different actions,
right? We have log where we just log the
traffic. And if we're running sore in
that IPS mode, well, we can drop the
packet which will block the packet from
reaching its destination as well as log
the traffic as well. And with reject, we
can also terminate the packet session as
well.
So next we have the specific protocol
and this obviously specifies the
protocol that the rule applies to and in
this case it's ICMP since we want to
detect pings in this
example. But we also have other options.
So we can look at the IP protocol or TCP
or UDP as well. Under the source IP we
have any any and this basically means
any IP address and any port. And so this
rule is going to apply from any packets
from any source IP address or any port.
And since we're looking at ICMP traffic
here, well obviously port numbers are
not relevant. So that's why we just say
any. In this case, we have the direction
of travel. And so this indicates the
actual direction of the packet's
traffic. So in this case, it's
specifying from source to destination
because we have this arrow pointing to
the
right. And so we have two options for
the direction here. we have from source
to destination or this birectional data
flow and obviously on the other side of
this arrow here we have the destination
IP address so 8.8.8.8 8 as well as the
port. Now when we start looking into the
rule options, we have things like
message here and in this case this
provides the message that will be
included within the alert. And so in
this case, we can put in a description
of what the rule is detecting. We have
an SID here and this is the snort ID and
it's a unique identifier for the rule.
And this is helpful for managing and
referencing rules within the snort
configuration. And so as best practice,
we want to start our custom rules after
the number 1 million. This is because
that any SID lower than this is
typically reserved for rules that are
shipped by default with Snort. And as a
general rule, SID should not overlap and
should be unique for each rule. And
lastly here, in the case of this rule,
we have Rev 1, and this is the revision
number. And this can be used to track
changes to the rule over time, right? So
if we make a change to this rule, for
example, change the IP address here,
well, we might want to increment the
revision number as two so we can track
changes accordingly. So we have more of
a version control over our rule. And so
to summarize, this rule is going to
generate an alert for any MP traffic
from any source to the IP address of
8.8.8.8. And I think once we start to
break down the different components
here, this rule becomes a lot more easy
to digest.
So now that we've defined our first
rule, let's go ahead and add it to our
rule configuration and test it out. And
so to do this, let's head over to our
local.rules file. If you remember, this
is the default file within our Snort
configuration that we can use to place
our rules in. And so to alter this file,
I'm going to run pseudo nano and then
within the snort directory, I'm going to
go under the rules folder and then into
that local rules
file. And you can see in this case this
file is intentionally blank and does not
come with any signatures. And we can put
our local additions within this file.
And so let's go ahead and put the rule
that we just covered on this first line
here. And so to follow along here, the
action is going to be alert. The
protocol is going to be ICMP. For the
source IP address, we'll have any and
port as well since it's ICMP traffic.
For the direction, I'm going to use the
dash and then the right arrow sign to
specify it's going from source to
destination. For the destination IP
address, we'll just use
8.8.8.8, which is one of Google's DNS
servers. For the port, of course, any as
well. And now we get into the rule
options. And so I'm going to put the
parenthesis here and put the rule
options inside this parenthesis. And in
this case, we have that key value pair.
And so for the key here, I'm going to
have the message component or the
message object and make sure to put a
colon after each name. And I'm going to
wrap the value here in quotes. And so
for each option that we include, we have
to finish it or end it off with a
semicolon. So for the next option here,
I'm going to specify the snort ID or the
SID.
And in this case, because it's not a
string, we don't have to wrap it in
these quotes here. Because for the SID,
I'm just going to put 1 million1. And
make sure to close that with a
semicolon. And lastly here, I'll include
the revision number with rev for rev.
And again, this is not a string, so we
can just put the number one. And make
sure to close that off with another
semicolon. And so in this case, our rule
is looking pretty good. And so I'm going
to save this by pressing Crl and X. and
then save the modified buffer with the
capital Y and then hit
enter. And so I'll mention that in a
typical deployment, Snort is going to
run as a service which allows it to
operate in the background and provide
that real-time network intrusion
detection and prevention. But since
we're just learning and testing here,
we're not going to configure that kind
of deployment and rather we can start
Snort manually from the command line to
run and test it. And so when we run
snort, the primary argument that we're
going to need to remember and make note
of is the capital A. And the capital A
specifies the alert mode that we want to
use. And so if I just run man snort
here and scroll down a bit, we can see
for capital A, we have alert mode. And
we have different values that we can
use. For example, full as the alert mode
is going to provide all of the possible
information about the alert. And this is
also the default alert mode. If we use
fast as the alert mode, well, this is
going to show alerts in a more condensed
format. And so it's going to show the
alert message and timestamp, source and
destination IP, and port numbers kind of
in a more SIS log style. If we use none,
well, we're not going to get any alerts.
It's basically going to turn off
alerting. And what's not mentioned here
is we can also use console. And this is
going to allow us to see alerts in that
fast mode, but directly within our
console when we run snort. And so I'm
going to press Q to quit here. And let's
go ahead and set up snort. So I'm going
to provide tac a here. And in this case
I'm going to use console because I want
to see the alerts in the console as they
appear. We can also use the tac l ar ar
ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar
ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar ar
argument to specify the log directory of
where the alerts will be logged. In this
case we can use the default of var log
snort. And we also need to provide our
interface for capture. In this case I
will use03.
And lastly, if you remember, we need to
specify our configuration file with the
C argument. In this case, it's under
Etsy snort and then
snort.com. And I will quickly sneak in
the Q argument here to make sure that we
run in quiet mode because if we don't,
it's going to display an annoying banner
and initialization information that we
don't actually need in this
instance. So once we run this, it's
going to be pretty uneventful because we
don't actually have any output yet.
However, in a new
tab, I'm going to test out our rule by
pinging
8.8.8.8. Well, actually, first, let's
try pinging a different IP address. For
example, if I ping
8.8.4.4, well, you can see we're getting
replies. But if I hop back over to our
snort output, well, we still have
nothing. So, what if I try pinging
8.8.8.8?
And assuming we set up our rule
correctly, well, we're going to get a
match and get alerts for every
ping. If I hop back over, well, we can
start to see all of this traffic has
been
detected. And in this case, we're
getting a timestamp of the alert. We're
getting the SID or the SID of the alert
as well. We're getting the message that
we specified or the description. We're
also seeing things like the traffic
direction. So, we have the source IP
address of our IP going to 8.8.8.8. And
so you can see this fast option mode or
in this case the console option mode is
really useful for us to get a quick
output. Okay, so let's do another
example here. And first I'm going to
quit snort. And if it's hanging up like
this again, I'm just going to issue some
more ping commands. It might just be my
machine and the demo gods raining down
on me. All right, so let's do another
example here. This time let's work with
the TCP protocol, which is a much more
common protocol for these rules as the
attack surface is much larger than say
something like ICMP. And so I'm going to
open up our local rules file again. And
that's under rules, local.ruules. And so
I'm going to delete our first rule here
just by pressing control and K. And in
this case, let's alert on any traffic
that is going to a destination port of
4444. In this case, the IP addresses
don't matter. We just want to monitor
any outgoing quad 4 port traffic. And so
to do this well, we want to specify an
alert under the TCP
protocol, any source IP address, and
also any source port. For the direction,
we want to specify any outgoing IP
address going to port
444. For the options here, well, I just
want to put a message of connection to
remote IP on port 444. You can basically
put whatever you want here. For the SID,
I'm just going to increment our last one
by one, even though we deleted it. And
the revision number is going to be one
as well. And so I'm going to save these
changes. And so to test out that our
rule is working, we can use the hping 3
command to send a specifically crafted
packet over to example.com on port 4444.
And so you can imagine that instead of
example.com, well, this can be an
attacker's controlled server listening
for any incoming connections on that
port. And if you don't have hping 3
installed, well, we can just run
pseudoapp install hping
3. All right, perfect. So, I'm going to
get our command ready. And so, I'm going
to run pseudo hping
3. For the count, I'm just going to put
one. We just need to make one request.
Under port here, it's going to be
444. I'm going to put s just for a sin
flag. And then specify
example.com. All right. All right. And
back over with Snort, I'm just going to
run the exact same
command. All right. So, now that we're
listening and monitoring, I'm just going
to run this hping 3 command to send a
SIN flag over to port 444 on
example.com. All right. We can see it
was transmitted. And back over on Snort,
you can see that we logged this one
alert here. And just to showcase that it
is working well, I can change this to
basically any other port. And we're
still not going to get any results. It's
only going to be on quad 4 here. All
right. So, I'm going to cancel that out
and send another ping just so we can
close it out. I don't know why that's
not working. And so, this wasn't a
particularly complex example, but for
instance, the metas-ploit framework is a
popular penetration testing tool, and
the default Metas-ploit payloads will
typically use port 444 by default when
attempting to establish reverse shells
on a target system. And also, various
malware intro have historically used
this port for command and control
communications. And so you can see how
we can start to monitor lowhanging fruit
like this. And typically this type of
thing will already be caught in the
default and community rules, but I just
wanted to show at the most basic level
how we can create something similar. And
so with this rule, we're basically
trying to see from the perspective of
the sock, what does the network activity
look like and can we write any rules to
log it or mitigate it and prevent it
from occurring. And this is basically
the essence of network security
monitoring and network traffic analysis
coming
together. Before we move on to some more
rule creation examples, let's briefly
talk about community rules. And so
community rules refer to all the rules
that have been submitted by members of
the open source community or the Snort
integrators or developers. And these
rules are freely available to use for
all Snort users and are governed by the
general public license. And so on
snort.org here, we can go under
downloads and then scroll down to the
rules section here. And I'm not going to
actually ingest all of these community
rules, but just to show the general
process, I'll make a quick directory to
store them in, and then we can take a
look at a couple. And so for version 2.9
here, I'm going to rightclick and copy
the link to the community
rules.tar.gz file. And so typically,
we'd want to download and extract this
file within the etsy snort rules folder.
But for this quick example, I'll just
make a sample
directory and then run wget with
pseudo and paste in that link so we can
download
it. If I run an ls, you can see that we
downloaded this tar zip file. And so to
extract it, I'll just run pseudo tar
with the x, z, v, and f arguments and
then provide the name of the file. And
if I go into the community rules
directory and run ls, well, we can see
this community.ruules file, which we can
then move over into our base
directory. And if I just cut out this
file to view it and pipe it over to
less, well, we can start taking a look
at some of these rules. And you can see
that all of these rules are really well
documented. So, we have things like
reference URLs that we can return to. We
have different things like class types
and different metadata about the rule
itself. And some of this metadata might
include things like CVE numbers or MITER
ids. And so if there was something in
particular that we wanted to find or
test, well, we could locate the rule
within this file and understand how it's
detected. You can see that a lot of
these rules are looking at the actual
content contained within the packets
themselves. So you can see specific
values in bytes or hex or different
regular expressions as well. And these
are specific patterns and signatures
that can be found within the packets to
alert on. And this is really how Snort's
rulebased detection works in the sock.
So next, let's take a look at logs
specifically in the
var/log/ snort
directory. And you can see here we have
files created from when we were doing
testing. In this case, we have the alert
fast file which includes all of the
alerts from when we specified the fast
alert mode. We also have the snore log
files with these specific timestamps
appended to the end of them. And these
include the actual raw traffic or the
captured pcaps from when a rule fired.
And so specifically, let's find the most
recent one here, which should refer to
our quad 4 port rule. And what I can
actually do here is just run pseudo
wire and then paste in the name of this
file. And you can see that wireark is
going to open up here. And in this case,
it's going to show us the captured
packet. In this case, we had a single
packet that fired off this rule. But we
can see that the destination port here
is quad 4.
And so obviously this is not the best
example, but you can see how absolutely
useful this can be during
investigations. If we can get an alert
and then get the actual raw data and
packets that were captured to fire off
the alert, well, this incredibly
expedites our analysis and response
capabilities. And so I'm just going to
remove all of the files within this
directory. And then I'm going to run
snort again, but this time I'm going to
log some alerts.
And so in order to log alerts, we can
run snort again just like we did before.
But in this case, I'm going to change
the alert mode to either full or fast.
And if you recall, full here is going to
provide the full decoded header and the
alert message. If I just run fast here,
it's going to show the alert message and
timestamp and source and destination in
that SIS log style. And fast is the
preferred method here if we want to
actually log these alerts and then
forward them to a SIM, for example, for
correlation. And so I'm going to run
this and then I'm going to head back
over to our other tab here and I'm going
to send a number of SIN flags over to
example.com. And each time I do this, it
should be triggering and generating an
alert. And if I hop back over here,
well, you can see we're not getting any
output this time. But if I cancel this,
and I'm going to need to send one more
packet because Snort is being weird for
me. And if I run an ls, well, we can see
we have the captured raw packets. We
also have this alert file that's been
populated. And so if I cat out the alert
file, well, we can see all of these
alerts that were logged. And so once
we're generating these alerts, well, we
can have these logs dynamically
forwarded into our SIM and create alerts
on our dashboard. And this is what us as
sock analysts will typically investigate
and respond to when they come in.
And because Snore is also capturing the
raw pecaps themselves, well, we can then
use what we learned from the network
traffic analysis section to dive into
these files and understand what happened
and gather IoC's. So, you can really
start to see how network traffic
analysis and network security monitoring
tie together, right? So, by setting up
rules and capturing alerts, we can then
forward them to our SIM. And so, lastly
here, let's see Snort in action as an
intrusion prevention system. So, so far
we've been monitoring and alerting, but
we can actually block or drop packets
that match our rules as well. And so, to
configure Snort as an IPS, we need to
use the drop action within our rules
instead of alert. And this will actively
block the traffic that matches our rule.
And so, to do this, I'm going to head
back over to Etsy Snort and I'm going to
run pseudo nano and locate our local
rules
file. And so, in this example, I'm going
to kill this one here. Let's create a
very simple rule that will drop FTP
traffic after it's been detected on port
21. And also, let's get real here for a
second. We don't have to be experts and
memorize every single field and header
when we're creating snort rules. And
although the syntax is pretty consistent
and easy to grasp, well, a tool like
Snorpy here can be really useful for us
when making complex rules. And Snorpy is
a web-based snort rule creator which
makes it very simple and easy for us to
create custom Snort rules. And I'll
include a link to the hosted instance of
Snorpie here along with its GitHub
repository because you can run and host
this yourself. And so you can see how
simple it is. It's just a very simple
point-and-click GUI based tool that
allows us to generate rules on the fly.
And so under action here, remember we
want to drop the packet. So I'm going to
click on drop. Under the protocol here,
we're dealing with FTP. So I'm going to
choose
TCP. Under the source IP address, well,
we want to monitor any IP on our home
network. So I'm going to put any for the
source port. Remember this can be an
ephemeral port as well. So we want to
put any. But for the destination, we
want to make sure the port is 21 and
also any for the destination IP address
because we want to monitor any external
FTP communication. Under the snort ID,
well I can just put 1 million and one
again. And the revision number, I'll
just put one as well. For the rule
message, I'm just going to put a brief
description of what we're doing here.
And with that, our rule is ready to go.
So, I'm going to click on this to copy
it to the clipboard and head back over
to our rules file. And I'm going to
paste it in
here. And when we do paste this in, it
included a couple extra spaces. So, I'm
going to make sure to remove those. And
one quirk with Snorpy is that we weren't
able to change the birectional flow of
traffic. And in this case, I want to
change the direction here from source to
destination to
birectional because I want to detect and
drop any traffic flowing to or from an
FTP server. And so we'll just save that.
And so now that we've created a rule to
drop traffic, we can now run Snort in
inline mode. And again, typically within
a production deployment where we're
going to be running Snort as more of a
service, we can actually configure this
by default in the snort.com file rather
than do it through the command line. And
so to run it in inline mode, we can just
run pseudo snort with the quiet option.
Here I'm going to provide console for
the alert
output. I'm going to specify our
interface here. So
emp3 as well as our configuration
file. And in this case, the capital Q
argument here is going to tell Snort to
run in inline mode. And inline mode is
required for IPS functionality and is
going to allow Snort to drop or modify
packets in real time. And so if I run
this, well, we're going to get an error
message. And you can see here, pcap daq
does not support inline. And this means
that the data acquisition model that
we're using by default or the libid pcap
module does not support inline mode. And
so to resolve this issue, we need to use
a DAQ that supports inline mode like AF
packet. Additionally, we need at least
two network interfaces for Snort IPS to
work as the AF packet module creates a
bridge between them. And so the steps to
do this are going to be dependent on
your hypervisor. And you don't have to
follow along if you don't want to, but
I'm going to quickly set this up to
demonstrate. And so in my case, I'm
running Virtual Box. And so I'm going to
rightclick and stop my machine here
because it has to be powered off. And
I'm going to open up the settings
here and head down to the network
settings. And in this case, I'm just
going to go over to the adapter 2 tab
and check off enable network adapter.
And I'm going to go down to NAT network
and make sure it's on the same one as my
first adapter
here. And so I'm going to press okay and
restart my
VM. Now I can run if config again. And
in this case you can see I have an
additional interface. So I have ENTP03
which is my default one but I also have
ENTP08 now. So now I can run snort once
again. And now what I need to modify
here is the data acquisition unit that
we're
using. In this case, I'll do two dashes
here with DAQ and specify the AF packet
utility. And now for our interface,
well, I actually need to bridge the two
that I just set up. And so I will leave
ENP0S3 here, but with a colon, I will
bridge it over to
ENTP0S8. And if you don't already have
it, make sure to include the capital Q
argument to run Snort in inline mode. If
I just hit enter here, well, you can see
we have nothing on the screen right
away. But if I try to connect to a
public FTP server, well, I can just run
FTP
test.rebex.net and try to connect to
it. You can see that apparently we were
connected, but now it's just hanging. It
should be prompting me for username and
password. If I head back over to Snort
here, you can see we did get an alert.
In this case, a drop action took place
to drop the FTP traffic based on port
21. And if we hop back over, well, you
can see the connection was
terminated. And just to prove that this
is working, I can press Ctrl + C here to
cancel out Snort and try to connect
normally. And in this case, we are being
prompted for our
username. And we can connect just fine.
However, if I turn Snort back
on, suddenly we can no longer connect
and we are logging that drop
packet. And so you can see by setting
Snort to drop or reject traffic, well,
we can actually prevent malicious
connections and protect the network in
real time. And so that was a lot of
information and a very long video. And
so feel free to review your notes or the
rule syntax. And in the next video,
we'll use what we learned to detect some
real threats. So, I will see you in the
next
video. All right, and welcome back. And
in this video, we're going to take a
look at some more intrusion detection
and prevention techniques within Snort
and actually feed in some real malicious
traffic and write custom detection rules
to alert on them. And so, first here,
I'm going to undo what I did in the last
video. I'm just going to head over to
the network settings here and uncheck
adapter 2 because we're not going to
need it for this lesson.
And in this lesson, let's go through
creating some custom detection rules for
a variety of real malicious
pcaps. And so to simulate us detecting
traffic for our rules, we don't have to
set up a lab environment and simulate
live traffic. We can simply use Snort's
option for reading in pre-established
PCAP files. And as we read in these
packet captures, we can leverage Snort's
alerting and detection functionalities
to evaluate our custom rules and make
sure that we can catch the malicious
traffic. And in this lab, we'll focus on
detection rules since it's easier to
showcase and we can pipe the alerts
right into our console. And obviously,
we won't be able to cover every single
scenario here, but hopefully by covering
some initial examples, you'll start to
get a feel for writing simple rules
which can be paired with the resources
I'll include at the end of this section
for further
practice. And so, let's head over to the
desktop and over to the network security
folder. In this case, let's head to the
snort directory and then under pcaps.
And this is where we're going to find
all of the example pcaps for this
lesson. And so I'm going to open a
terminal here. And in this case, to
start off, let's open up 1.pcap in
[Applause]
Wireshark. And if you remember this pcap
file, well maybe you don't just by first
glance here, but this is the same one
that we used to both learn TCP dump and
wire sharkark. So this is the pcap from
that system that was infected with
Lokibot that made the HTTP request to
download the malicious audiodg.exe
Trojan. And if I just run HTTP contains
audiod, we should be able to pull back
that request. Yeah, there we
go. Alternatively, I can go under
statistics under HTTP under requests and
we can also find the same audiodg.exe
executable download. And so in this
case, let's see if we can use this as an
example to create a snort rule that can
alert us on any.exe files that were
downloaded over
HTTP. And to do this, let's use the same
Snorpie tool that I'll link down
below. So let's set the action to alert.
Under protocol, it's going to be TCP
because we're dealing with HTTP traffic.
For the source port and IP, well, this
can basically be anything because we
want to monitor our entire home network
and any ephemeral port that these
connections originate from. For the
destination, well, we will have any once
again an 80 for the port. Here, as best
practice, I will put in an
SID and a revision
number. For the message, I will just
include http URI contains.exe.
exe. All right. So, at this stage, our
rule is not going to match anything
specific to executables, right? In this
case, we're just going to match anything
on port 80, which isn't ideal. So, this
is where content matches come into play.
So, I'm going to press the green plus
button here to add a content match. And
in this case, we need to choose what
field we're matching the content off of.
Because we want to match any.exe
extensions within the URL, I'm going to
click on the URI option here.
I'm also going to click on no case here.
And this is going to make sure the rule
is case insensitive because attackers
might try something like .exe with a
capital X or two capital E's for
example. And for the actual content to
match, I'm just going to type
in.exe. And to confirm this, I'm going
to press the green check icon. And so we
have our rule written here. And you can
see that it automatically converted the
dot here to this hex value of 2E, which
refers to the dot. We didn't actually
need to do this, but it's good practice.
And you're going to see a lot of hex
values within these content signatures.
And so this rule in theory is going to
alert when it detects any HTTP traffic
where the URI contains the
string.exe. And so if I copy this to our
clipboard, we can close out Wireshark
here. I'm going to edit our local rules
file which is located in Etsy snort
rules and then
local.ru. And I'm going to delete our
previous example here for FTP and paste
in this new rule that we created. And
I'll remove any white space as
well. Great. So if I save this, we
should be good now to run snort and test
out our rule. So to do this, we can run
pseudo
snort and specify the name of our
configuration
file. We want to run in quiet mode as
well. And in this case, we want to read
in the pcap.
In this case, it's going to be
1.pcap. And for the alert mode, we want
to specify console so we get all of the
alerts in our console output. So we
don't have to go around digging for
them. And if I run this, well, we get
two results. So our rule matched two
packets from this pcap file. And if I ls
in the var log snort
directory, well, we can see a number of
alerts from our previous testing. In
this case, I'm going to remove
everything currently in varlog
snort. And then I'm going to run snort
once again and we should get these same
two alerts. Now if I ls that log
directory, we should get this snort.log
file with our specified Unix timestamp.
And from here we can dump or decode the
packets that we matched. So I can run
pseudo snort and read in that log
file provide the quiet option and then
tacd here to decode the packets. And we
can see the raw packets as well as their
ASI and hex output and start to
understand how they matched. And if you
remember from our initial analysis, we
had this Bing API endpoint that made a
request to that audiod.exe
executable. And our second packet here
is the actual download of
audiodg.exe. All right. Nice. So we were
able to create a custom rule to catch
the request or download of any
executable files based on the file
extension. And so before we run the next
example, I'm just going to once again
clear out our varlog snort
directory. Okay, so in our first
example, we were able to detect the
downloaded files due to the.exe
extension included in the request URI.
But what if the file extension is not
included in the URI or it's obscured by
other means? Well, we might need to rely
on different detection methods to
identify potentially malicious
downloads. And one approach is to
inspect the content type headers in the
HTTP
responses. So for example, many
executable files are transmitted with
the following content type of
application XMS download. And we can use
this string to trigger alerts. So I'm
going to open up 1.pcap again in
Wireshark. And if I find the same
audgent type of
application/x-m
download and as mentioned earlier this
mime type is commonly associated with
the.exe file extension and is used by
web servers to tell browsers and other
client applications that the file being
transmitted is a Windows executable so
it can be handled correctly. So, let's
create a snort rule that can detect HTTP
responses containing the application XMS
download mime type. So, I'm going to
open up our local rules file again and
make some changes to our initial rule.
In this case, I'm going to remove all of
our options here and I'm going to change
the value of our message slightly.
And if you think about the direction of
travel here, in the initial example, we
were looking at any destination IP
addresses of port 80 because we were
looking for when the client made a
request to the web server. In this case,
we're looking at a response header. So,
we kind of want to reverse this, right?
So, we want to put any for the
destination port because that can be
referring to a client's ephemeral port
and from the source of the traffic,
well, we want that to be the web server
on port 80. So for the options here, we
want to specify the content that we're
matching. And we can do that with the
content object. And within the quotes
here, we want to paste in the string
containing the exact header that we want
to match. In this case, it's going to be
content- type with the colon of
application/x-ms download. And now we
need to specify what field we're
searching for to match this header. In
this case, we can use the
http header field. and make sure to end
that with a
semicolon. All right, so I'm going to
save this rule
here. And now we can try running snort
again on the same 1.pcap file and see
what
happens. All right, so I'm going to hit
enter here. And it looks like I might
have messed something
up. Ah, I forgot the semicolon after the
message. So again, if you miss one of
these semicolons, you're going to get a
syntax error. And let me just make sure.
Yep, I missed one here as well. Okay, so
don't be like me and make sure you have
all your semicolons. I think this looks
good
now. So if I run this again, but we can
see we actually did manage to make an
alert here. And in this case, the packet
direction was from the web server going
over to our client and stemming from
port
80. And from here once again we can
decode the raw packets that were
[Applause]
captured. Awesome. So we were able to
create a second rule to match on a
different part of the
packet. So let's go through a third
example here. And before we do this, I'm
going to clear out the varlog snort
directory once
again. So for a third example, it's
still possible for attackers to spoof
the file extension and the content type
header. And these are common techniques
that attackers use to bypass checks or
rules like these, especially in web
server file uploads and in our case over
network traffic.
And so for this example, let's focus on
detecting the file signature or the
magic bytes of a Windows executable
within the body or payload of an HTTP
packet. Specifically, we want to
identify that hex signature or that MZ
marker which is indicative of the start
of a Windows executable file. If you
remember this Wikipedia article listing
all the file signatures and magic bytes,
if I do a search for MZ, well, we can
see the actual hex value that makes up
this file signature.
We can also see the file types that it's
associated with. For example, the ones
that we saw are an executable file along
with a Windows DL. And so to create a
snort rule that can detect the MZ marker
in the payload, we need to look for the
hexadimal pattern of 4D
5A. And so to write this rule, well, we
can base this basically off of our
previous one. We can specify an alert
for TCP packets on any destination IP
with the port 80. Because remember in
this case we're matching any responses
from the web server. And so for the
direction we're going to specify the
destination of any any. And in the
options here I'm just going to include a
relevant
description. And in this case we want to
specify that we're matching file
data. And this keyword is going to tell
Snort to inspect the contents of the
files transmitted over the network.
Additionally, we want to specify the
actual content that we're
matching. And so within our string here,
I'm going to specify that we're putting
in hex values. And so to do this, I'm
going to enclose everything within these
pipe
characters. And within these pipes, I'm
going to paste in the 45A, which refers
to MZ in hex. Lastly, here we can take
advantage of the depth feature within
our options. And when I type this, it's
probably going to move over to the left.
Okay, so hopefully you can still see
that. And the depth option here is going
to specify how far into the packet snort
should look to match the specified
content. In this case, we can just put
two here to specify that we only want
Snort to look in the first two bytes of
the payload. In this case, matching the
MZ in hex. And so we can really start to
see the power of Snort here and its
different pattern matching capabilities.
And so as best practice here, I'm going
to close this out with a
SID and a revision of
one. And so this looks good to me. So
I'm going to save this. And to test out
that our rule is going to work, well,
I'm just going to run Snort once again
on this 1.pcap file and see what
happens. And you can see we did in fact
get a hit. And if we open up the log
file in
Wireshark, we can see all of the
relevant packets that stem from this
capture. If I follow the TCP stream,
well, we do in fact see the MZ file
signature at the start of this
file. Excellent. So that was three
different ways and three different
custom rules that we wrote to match a
malicious file transfer over
HTTP. And so before we move on here, I'm
just going to clear out my varlog snort
directory and let's take a look at the
next
example. And so for this example, let's
open up the 2.pcap file within
Wireshark. And if you recall, this is
the pcap that we analyzed with TCP dump
earlier that contained the cobalt strike
activity. And during our analysis, well,
we identified a malicious SS load DLL
that was using a unique user agent
string. To demonstrate this, we can
search for the user
[Applause]
agent that contains SS
load. And if I open up the packet here,
we can see the user agent of SS load
version
1.1. So this time, let's create a rule
for this string that can detect an alert
on this type of activity.
And we already created some rules based
on HTTP traffic before. So this should
be quite simple. I'm going to open up
our local rules file, comment our
previous rule out, and start a new one
here. This time I'm going to keep it
very open and just alert
anything under the content
here. This is going to be the same
process as matching the content type
earlier. In this case, I'm going to
paste in the user agent. And under the
field that we're matching, I'm just
going to specify
HTTP header. And by using HTTP header
here, Snort is going to inspect the
traffic to determine if it is HTTP
traffic regardless of the port that it's
on. And so this allows us to catch HTTP
traffic on any non-standard ports as
well, which is sometimes common for
attackers and command and control
servers. I'm going to add the no case
option as well, just in case we run
across this user agent in a lowercase
format. And then I'll just close it out
with a SID and a revision number. So I'm
good with that. I'm going to save and
let's try running snort again this time
under the 2.pcap file and see what
happens. All right, so we detected a
number of alerts here. In fact, we
detected nine different
alerts. And if I head back over to
Wireshark and put in that same display
filter of HTTP user agent contains SS
load.
Well, in this case, we also get nine
packets, meaning that we successfully
match the user agent via the
headers. All right, before our last
example here, I'm going to once again
clear out our Snort log
directory. And then for this example,
let's move away from the HTTP protocol
and look at
SSH. And so 3.pcap here is a packet
capture containing an SSH brute
force. So I can open this up in
Wireshark.
And if we look at the statistics under
the protocol hierarchy, well, we can see
we have a large number of SSH traffic.
And if we look at the capture file
properties, well, all of this traffic
was contained in 25 seconds, which is
already suspicious of a brute force
attack. But of course, like we've been
doing, let's create a custom snort rule
that can detect on potential SSH brute
force attempts. And so, let's use Snorpy
for this rule. Under action, I'm going
to choose alert obviously and the
protocol is going to be
TCP. For the source here, I'm going to
put any
any. And the destination is going to be
any destination IP with port 22
specifying SSH traffic. I'll put in a
SID and a revision number as well as a
rule message indicating a potential SSH
brute force
attack. When we go under the TCP options
here, I'm going to click on direction
and click on to server. And this can
specify the actual flow direction that
the rule will apply to. And so if we
click to server here and under TCP
state, I'm going to also select
established. And this means that the
rule is only going to trigger on traffic
going to the server side of an
established connection. And lastly here,
we can choose the threshold tracking
type. And you can see we have a number
of different options to choose from. And
the threshold option is going to
generate an alert every single time our
network traffic matches our threshold.
So for example, if we set our count to
five and our time period is 60 seconds,
well, it will give us an alert on the
fifth event and then the 10th event and
so on as long as it's within that
60-second
period. If we were to choose both here,
well, this is only going to generate one
alert within our set threshold period.
For example, if we exceeded our
threshold within that 60-second period,
well, we're only going to get a single
alert within that 60-second
period. And so, to cut down on the
number of duplicate alerts that we're
generating, well, I'm going to select
both here. And this is because we're
going to set up some options that can
detect if we've had more than five SSH
connection attempts within 30 seconds.
Under track by here, we can choose the
actual field that we're tracking the
threshold off of. So in this case I can
choose by source to specify the source
IP address of the
connection. Under count here we can set
a count of five. And under seconds well
we can specify something like 30 for 30
seconds. And I also just realized I
messed up the SID here. So I'm going to
add a couple more zeros to make sure
we're past that 1 million mark for best
practice. And so how this rule is going
to work is well snort is going to
inspect the TCP SIN packets going
towards port 22 or SSH. It's then going
to track the number of connection
attempts from a single source IP
address. And if there are more than five
connection attempts from the same source
IP within 30 seconds, it's going to
generate an alert. So, I'm going to copy
this rule over to our terminal here and
paste it into our local rule file. I'll
comment out our previous one and paste
this rule
in. And now I'm just going to run snort
on the 3.pcap file. and we should get
some alerts from brute force
attempts. And you can see because we set
that 30- secondond period, we're only
getting one alert. If I were to change
this and actually edit the
threshold instead of both here to
threshold and run the same rule again,
well, this time we're going to get an
alert for every single attempt within
that 30 secondond period. Or to put it
another way, anytime a single source IP
address exceeded five SSH connections
within 30
seconds. And so this was a very
simplified example. And in a real world
scenario, you might want to fine-tune
the threshold values like the count and
the seconds based on your baseline
traffic patterns so you can reduce false
positives. And also there are built-in
brute force detection methods like fail
to ban. But I just wanted to showcase
how it could be done with snort rules as
well. And so that was a great exercise I
think into various rules and
methodologies around creating and tuning
rules with Snort. And any other IDS or
IPS system that you interact with like
Siraata or Zeke is going to have very
similar syntax and approaches. And if
you want to dive into more complex rules
and look into things like
pre-processors, well definitely look
into the community rules and the default
rules that we looked at earlier. And you
could learn a lot about thresholds and
counts and various fields that you can
define as well through these rules. And
so now I think it's time that we use
what we learned to go through a quick
challenge and combine what we learned
through PACAP analysis to then go ahead
and create custom detection rules and
improve our team's detection
capabilities. And so with that, I will
see you in the next video. Now that
we've wrapped up the network security
section, let's take a look at some
additional resources that you can use to
continue practicing network traffic
analysis and custom rule writing for
network security monitoring and
prevention. And I will have all these
links down below, but I'll quickly walk
through some of them as
well. And so the first one here is
malwareanalysis.net. And this is a
fantastic blog and resource by Brad of
Unit 42 of Palo Alto Networks that
focuses on well network traffic related
to malware infections. And if we go to
the archive here, it contains hundreds
of realistic pecaps from actual malware
infections in the wild. and it's an
amazing resource if you want to continue
practicing your network traffic analysis
and detection engineering skills. I will
list a disclaimer here to be careful
with these samples because they do in
fact contain real malware samples. So,
as best practice, keep everything
contained within your lab VM. And I
fully credit this resource here for
providing some of the pecaps that we use
during the wire shark section because
they really are just that good.
Another great resource here is from
Chris Sanders who is a master of packet
analysis and an author of some fantastic
books like practical packet analysis and
applied network security monitoring. And
he's also provided a list or a
repository here of packet captures from
over the years and you can download them
here from
GitHub within the Wireark wiki. Well,
they also have a list of sample capture
files as
well. Additionally, this resource here
from netresc has compiled a list of
publicly available pcap files which is
all freely
available. We can also take a look at
the zeke repository which is another
type of network security monitoring tool
as they also list some sample packet
captures and traces as well. And these
are the trace files that are used by the
zeke test suite.
And lastly here, Security Onion has
compiled a list of public pcaps for
their Security Onion test tool. And
these are some that we already covered
here, but also another great list of new
resources as
well. And so there's definitely no
shortage of PECAP files for you to get
your hands on and start dissecting and
analyzing and creating detection rules
for. And so I hope these lists are
useful to you and that you were able to
learn quite a bit about everything from
the structure of packets to how
computers talk to each other all the way
to network traffic analysis and security
monitoring. And so as a foreoding
sentiment to the next section of this
course, well, no matter how
comprehensive our packet captures are
and where our capture tools are
positioned, they can't provide a
complete picture of the actions and
behaviors and modifications occurring on
the endpoint alone. And so while they
can reveal remotely issued commands that
were not encrypted if an attacker
utilizes encrypted protocols or encrypts
its transmissions in some way while our
pecaps become ineffective and also any
changes on our actual system or
workstation. So things like spawn
processes or events and registry
modifications all remain undetected. And
so because of this it's often beneficial
during investigations to pair our
network analysis and endpoint security
capabilities to get a full picture of
what's going on at the endpoint level.
And so with that, I will see you in the
next domain of this
course. All righty, everyone. Good job
for getting through that network
security section. I know that one can be
quite long. Uh there's a lot of sort of
stuff thrown at you, uh you know, all
throughout the different tools that we
touch on and cover. Uh but again, very
important aspects for any sock analyst
to know. Um and so with that, we are
sort of going to move things over to the
endpoint now, which is my favorite
domain and my favorite section of the
sock 101 course. Uh we're going to talk
all about um not only how we can
simulate malware, right? So we're
actually going to be creating malware
and uh simulating different attacks at
the endpoint level, but of course we're
going to learn uh and understand
different techniques and methodologies
and tools that we have uh to analyze
those artifacts as they're being
generated on the system in real time.
And so I really think the endpoint
security section really picks the course
up uh sort of turns it up a notch and
really uh deep dives into you know
performing live incident response but
also just learning all those different
operating system and operating system
level components as it relates to
Windows and Linux uh and also working
with an enterprisegrade EDR solution
which I'm very excited to do. Um
unfortunately we are going to have to
cap off this section pretty early. Uh if
you take a look at the time, we are
getting close to the end here
unfortunately, but I just wanted to sort
of uh remind you all once again to check
out the full uh sock 101 course on TCM
uh to get, you know, your hands on all
these different exciting domains. And so
again, we'll have the link down in the
description below for you to register uh
and take the full course because uh if
you made it this far, you're clearly
enjoying it at least to some degree. So
again, I highly encourage you to check
out the full course and get all of those
offerings.
Welcome to the endpoint security section
of this course. And in this section,
we're going to expand the surface of our
monitoring and analysis capabilities and
well include endpoint devices as well.
And so, as a sock analyst, understanding
endpoint security is going to be an
important focus for us because we're
almost always going to be dealing with
endpoints in incident response
scenarios. And as we discussed back in
the fishing analysis section, whether
you agree with it or not, humans are
often seen as the weakest link by
attackers. and as such are often
specifically targeted by attackers for
their initial access or foothold into an
organization. And we can think about
endpoints as simply an extension of
users. Right? So whether it be
workstations in the form of desktops or
laptops or mobile devices or even
endpoints in the form of servers like
web servers or database servers or FTP
servers, all of these systems or
endpoints need to be hardened and
monitored as these are the targets that
often serve as these entry points for
attackers into the network.
And by truly understanding the endpoint,
we're going to be much more effective at
identifying what's normal or abnormal on
workstations and servers, or being able
to correlate network traffic activities,
or being able to map an attacker's
tactics and techniques, and ultimately
respond to incidents more
effectively. And so, this section will
provide you with the knowledge and
hands-on skills needed to effectively
monitor and analyze endpoint security
events. And we're also going to cover
endpoint events and logs in much more
detail during the SIM or the security
information and event management domain
as well as the processes and
methodologies for responding to
incidents in the incident response
section. And so there's going to be some
natural overlap here, but understanding
the fundamentals and components of
operating systems and endpoints and how
we can enhance their security is going
to be very helpful before we dive into
these topics. And so with that, let's
jump into our domain objectives for this
section.
And so first we of course want to
understand the fundamentals of endpoint
security
monitoring. And so we want to explore
different things like endpoint types and
controls and detection strategies. So we
want to answer questions like what types
of endpoints exist in our environment
and what security controls can we
implement at the host level and how do
sock analysts detect malicious endpoint
activity. And to do this we want to
understand the core operating system
components as well as their functions.
And so we want to dive into what normal
looks like in regards to processes and
events and logs or network activity and
the Windows
registry. We want to develop practical
skills in extracting insights from
system internals. So we're going to
actually take a look at the CIS internal
suite and use it to analyze systems and
extract valuable data and improve our
endpoint logging capabilities.
And all of our learning in this section
is going to converge into a practical
project to deploy and configure a
unified endpoint detection solution. And
so this section is going to be a lot of
fun to cover and go through and it's
really going to set us up for success
during the rest of the course. And so
with this introduction out of the way, I
will see you in the next
video. I suppose we should first define
and answer the question of what even is
an endpoint? And so in simple terms, an
endpoint is any physical hardware or
device that connects to our
organization's network. And in the
context of security operations, while
endpoints are great tools that we can
use for business productivity or
communications or use them to stand up
and configure servers, well, they can
also serve as a potential point of entry
for security threats. And endpoints can
include a wide range of different
devices. So, we might have various
desktops or laptops that employees use
for their day-to-day business
operations, or maybe laptops that
external stakeholders or third party
contractors bring in and connect to our
network. And workstations are common
targets for attackers due to their
widespread use and often direct access
to sensitive information. So, we can
think about attacks like fishing that
often attempt to install malicious
software or remote access Trojans onto
an employes workstation.
And so of course along with workstations
there's been an increasing rise of
mobile devices and tablets within the
workplace. And these are additional
endpoints that the sock also needs to
track and secure within the organization
as they can also be subject to fishing
and malware attacks. And due to their
portability they're also susceptible to
physical threats like being lost or
stolen which can lead to unauthorized
access. And so we also have servers,
right? And when we think of servers,
well, these are endpoints that host
various resources and business functions
like applications or data or services
that are essential to the organization's
operation, right? So we might have
internal or external email servers or
web servers, database servers or file
servers. And all of these additional
endpoints require hardening measures and
security controls to prevent things like
breaches and data exfiltration and
unauthorized access into the network.
We also have things like IoT devices,
right? So, these can include our smart
devices like sensors and cameras and
printers and any other appliance that's
often overlooked as part of the
organization's attack surface, but are
becoming more and more common due to
their smart features and ease of use
within the workplace. And often, it can
be hard to get long-term support for
these devices, meaning that they can
quickly lose access to security updates
with no way of patching or remediating
vulnerabilities. And while not IoT
devices themselves, we can also think of
some other categories of endpoints like
OT or operational technology which are
endpoints that are used to manage
industrial operations or IC or
industrial control systems and also
SCADA equipment which all come with
their own attack surface and hardening
challenges. We also need to think about
all of our networking appliances like
routers and switches and firewalls that
form the backbone of the organization's
network infrastructure. And since these
endpoints often run custom or
proprietary operating systems, it can
sometimes be difficult to install
endpoint agents or monitor things
effectively. But we will talk about this
later on in the
course. And so with this abundance of
endpoints growing throughout an
organization's environment, well, we
need a way to implement security
controls to monitor and alert on
malicious activity or behavior occurring
on the host or operating system level.
And over the years, a lot of research
and development has gone into evolving
endpoint security monitoring
capabilities. and vendors have invented
many exciting acronyms to sell the
latest and greatest hostbased security
solutions. And so let's quickly go
through the most prominent controls or
solutions that you might see out there.
And as we think about the concept of
defense in depth, some of these
capabilities pair handinand quite well
together or have a lot of overlap with
each other. And so the goal for an
organization is to assess which controls
align to their specific threat model and
environment and prioritize their
implementation based on that relevance
along with available resources. And I'll
also mention that the area of endpoint
security can get messy in terms of, you
know, where do you draw the line between
what an EDR can do and a hostbased
intrusion detection or prevention
system, for example, or how EDR can
integrate with UBA. Yeah, I told you
there would be a lot of acronyms here.
Or some vendors might have their own
standalone products. So, it's always
been very hard to compare specific
vendor offerings between each other
because they can all do different things
and are always evolving to include more
capabilities. Which is why I always like
to say it's not ever about the specific
tool or solution, but what the tool or
solution aims to accomplish and what
security controls it's aimed to
enforce. And so first here we have anti
virus or anti-malware. And this refers
to software designed to detect, prevent,
and remove malicious software or malware
from computers and networks. An anti
virus software typically works by
scanning files and programs on your
computer for various patterns or
signatures that match known malware. And
the traditional concept of antivirus has
evolved into newer solutions, which
we'll talk about soon, that move beyond
the reliance of constant hard-coded
signature updates. And these newer
solutions can employ advanced detection
methods like behavior analysis or
huristics and machine learning
algorithms to detect threats more
effectively. Which kind of brings us
into endpoint detection and response or
EDR. And this is a technology focused on
monitoring and responding to threats on
endpoints in real time. And EDR
solutions provide visibility into our
different endpoint activities and can
detect suspicious behavior and
facilitate a more rapid incident
response. And so EDR implementations
will typically require the deployment of
an agent on each endpoint. And this
agent is what collects and transmits the
telemetry data to a centralized EDR
server or console where it can then be
analyzed. And this agent monitors
various aspects of the endpoint
behavior. So things like process
execution or file system changes or
registry modifications and even network
connections. And so while antivirus or
anti-malware software focuses on
preventing and removing known types of
malware, EDR extends the capabilities to
detect and respond to a broader range of
security threats by analyzing the
actions and behavior within endpoint
devices
themselves. And so this kind of brings
us to XDR or extended detection and
response. And to be honest, it's a bit
of a marketing buzzword because it can
mean a ton of different things. And so
to generalize, XDR is really about the
integration of multiple data points and
other security solutions to have a more
autonomous and quicker response to
routine threats. And in some cases can
even take automated action like blocking
signins on compromised users or
isolating endpoints from the network or
forcing password changes or blocking web
traffic or policy enforcement. And so
XDR can expand the capabilities of an
EDR and include other layers of
operation like looking at the broader
network traffic or email or cloud
environments. We also have data loss
prevention or DLP. And this is a
strategy and set of technologies that
aim to protect sensitive data from
unauthorized access or use and
transmission. Right? So DLP solutions
can monitor and control data while it's
in motion or at rest and even in use to
prevent data breaches and ensure
compliance with regulations.
And so these solutions can detect
sensitive data in different forms like
text or files or images and emails all
across different locations like
endpoints and servers. And they can
implement holistic access controls
around sensitive data or do things like
dynamic data masking on things like
social security numbers or credit card
numbers. And most of all monitoring the
data transfer activities. So, for
example, if an employee attempts to send
an email containing credit card numbers
or tries to upload sensitive financial
reports to a personal cloud storage
service, well, a data loss prevention
solution can kick in and intervene based
on predefined
policies. We also have user and entity
behavior analytics or UBA. Or you might
see this as UEBA, which is slightly
different, but we can generalize here.
And this involves monitoring and
analyzing user behavior patterns to
detect anomalous or suspicious
activities that can indicate things like
insider threats or compromised accounts.
And the big thing about UBA here is its
ability to use machine learning and
statistical analysis to identify
deviations from normal behavior or a
predefined baseline. And so it can build
a profile and context on normal user
behavior based on historical data and
real-time observations. And so it can
track things like a user or endpoint's
typical login times or access patterns
or how much data is typically
transferred from that endpoint. And it
can also consider the context around the
user, right? So the user roles or access
privileges or the actual geographic
location that the user is accessing
from. And so the goal of user and entity
behavioral analytics is to identify
potential insider threats or account
compromises or data exfiltration
attempts or just in general other
malicious activities that traditional
security controls might overlook.
And this brings us to something we're
more familiar with from the last
section. In this case, we have hostbased
intrusion detection systems or HIDs and
hostbased intrusion prevention systems
or HIPS. And these are security measures
that of course focus on monitoring and
protecting individual devices or the
hosts from malicious
activities, right? And so a HIDS is
going to operate by monitoring and
analyzing the internal activity on a
host like the system logs and files and
processes and configurations to detect
any policy
violations. And of course a HIPS on the
other hand can take it a step further
and automatically take actions like
blocking network traffic or terminating
malicious processes or modifying
firewall rules based on these predefined
rules. And there's going to be a lot of
overlap here into things like EDR and
XDR because typically these solutions
can also take these automated actions
and do things like quarantine devices or
kill malicious processes or prevent
specific file access. And lastly here we
have a hostbased firewall. And a
hostbased firewall is a type of firewall
that operates of course at the
individual host level to control
incoming and outgoing traffic based on
predetermined security rules. And so
unlike network firewalls that typically
protect an entire network by filtering
traffic at the perimeter, hostbased
firewalls are installed and configured
on individual devices to provide more
granular control over traffic flows and
protect the host system from any
unauthorized traffic or
access. So we can further break down the
main methodologies and components used
to detect different types of host
activities, focusing specifically on the
key aspects that are targeted by these
endpoint security tools. And we're going
to use this to sort of guide us through
this section as we explore how to
monitor and analyze these activities on
various operating systems. And so
firstly here we have process execution.
And this involves monitoring the running
processes, right? So which processes are
running on the endpoint any executable
files and applications. And so we can
analyze a list of running processes like
executable files and applications along
with their metadata, right? So things
like their process ids or parent process
or command line arguments that were
passed along with the
executable. And so we can use baselines
to quickly determine and detect
suspicious activity like a high number
of processes being spawned or an
unusually high CPU or memory drain from
specific processes. Additionally, we can
leverage reputation databases to
evaluate the trustworthiness and
reputation of processes based on factors
like digital signatures or file origins
or historical behavior or by analyzing
the parent child relationships of
processes. And so these refer to
examining the hierarchical connections
between various processes. So for
example, is the winword process spawning
command.exe or PowerShell.exe or other
strange interconnections or dependencies
of processes that aren't present in
normal system activities.
We can also look at file system changes,
right? So we can track changes made to
files and directories on the endpoint
and detect things like unauthorized file
access or the presence of known
malicious files. And so we have things
like file integrity monitoring that can
monitor file systems for changes like
creation or modification or deletion of
files and directories. And this might
involve maintaining a cryptographic hash
or a check sum of files and comparing
them against current values to detect
any alterations or just analyzing file
access behavior. Right? So if we have a
rapid creation or modification of
multiple files, well that might indicate
a ransomware attack. Or if there are
attempts to offiscate file properties
like clearing out logs or events or
altering metadata, well we can alert on
that as well. We also have network
connections and we're obviously very
familiar with this from the last
section, right? So we can monitor
network traffic and connections going to
and from the endpoint. And at the host
level, well, we could take a look at
what processes are making which network
connections. We can see the associative
files or executables. And this can all
help us in detecting things like command
and control communication by malware or
remote access
Trojan. And lastly here we have registry
modifications. And so the Windows
registry, for example, is a common
target for attackers who want to
establish persistence mechanisms or
create back doors or evade detection by
disabling antivirus or EDR software, for
example. And so we can monitor these
registries in real time and capture any
modifications or creations of keys and
values within the registry.
And so with all of these common activity
and detection methods, you can sort of
start to see how much of understanding
what is suspicious or abnormal on
endpoints relies on having a great
understanding of our baseline activities
and what is normal. And that's the
direction that I want to take this
section. So, we're going to start
looking at different ways that we can
analyze various operating system
components like processes and file
activity or logs or the Windows
registry, which is going to come in
handy, of course, when we need to jump
onto an endpoint in an incident response
scenario. And so, let's start to get
into all of this fun stuff. And so, I
will see you in the next video.
So, let's do something a bit fun here
and create a very simple piece of
malware to compromise our Windows VM
from a simulated attacker on our Abuntu
VM. And this is so we can have a live
attack to showcase how we can
investigate different endpoint
components like network traffic and
processes as they're occurring in real
time. And obviously, we're not going to
be creating malware and compromising
ourselves within the sock. This is just
so we can set up a very simple example
to demonstrate the concepts covered in
future lessons. And so to accomplish
this, we're going to need to install and
use the Metas-ploit framework. And
Metas-ploit is a widely used penetration
testing tool that provides a
comprehensive platform for developing
and testing and executing exploits
against a variety of systems. And
Metas-ploit includes a vast library of
pre-built exploits and payloads that we
can use. and it will specifically allow
us to achieve a reverse shell and set up
something similar to a command and
control operation over our Windows
system. And don't worry if some of this
seems out of scope or confusing. Right?
Your goal in sock 101 is not to learn
how to compromise machines, but this is
giving us a very simplified gist into
what the attacker side might look like
and with the added benefit of course of
setting up our lab for this section. And
if you're interested in the type of
actions we perform in this lesson, well,
definitely take the practical ethical
hacking course if you haven't already.
And so to install Metas-ploit, well,
first make sure you're on your Auntu
machine, right? And we're going to open
up the Linux terminal here. And we're
just going to follow the documentation
on the Rapid 7 website, which I'll have
linked down below. And within the
documentation here, if we scroll
down, we're going to see this section
for installing the Metas-ploit framework
on Linux. And specifically, we can copy
this command here. And of course, we
want to make sure what commands we're
copying and running on our system. But
in this case, you can see we're curling
the repository, specifically an install
file here, and then we're simply running
the install file. And if we really
wanted to, we could take a look at the
actual script here, the installation
script, and make sure we're not running
anything malicious. And so what I'm
going to do is copy this command, head
over to my
terminal, and I'm going to paste this
in. And from here, it's going to kick
off the installation.
And of course, we're going to need our
password
here. And this might take a second to
install as it needs to update a number
of packages and install some
dependencies. All right. And it looks
like we're good to go. And so now we can
simply just type in MSF console to start
the
tool. And you can see we're going to get
a prompt here to ask us if we want to
use and set up a new database. And so to
do this, we can just type in y or yes to
run the initial configuration script and
create the initial
database. And so again, this might take
another
second. Excellent. So once we see that
MSF6 prompt there, we're good to go.
And so now that we have the metas-ploit
framework installed, we can use it to
create an interpreter payload, which is
a very highly versatile payload and
handler that can provide us with an
interactive shell using in-memory DL
injection. And that's a lot of words and
we don't need to understand what it's
doing under the hood because we're going
to start digging into that after we get
our malware going. And so let's take a
look at our VM networking because first
we need to make sure that our Linux and
Windows VM are on the same network.
And this is dependent on the hypervisor
you're using, but assuming you've placed
them both within the same network. In my
case, I can go under settings here in
virtual box under network. And you can
see I've attached them to this NAT
network that I've titled
TCM. And so next, since we're going to
be creating a payload that executes on
our Windows machine, we need to know
where to tell it to connect back to,
right? So in other words, what is our
Ubuntu Linux's machine IP address? And
so I'm going to press control shift and
t to open up a new terminal tab here.
And I'm just going to run if config on
my ENP0S3 interface. I have the IP
address of
192.168.1.4. So I'm going to make sure I
write this down because I'm going to
need it in a second. And so now that we
know our IP address, we can create our
payload. And Metas-ploit bundles with
something called MSF Venom, which is a
payload generation tool and utility that
we're going to use to create our actual
payload using a very simple syntax. And
so again, I'm going to open up another
terminal tab
here. And in this case, I'm currently in
my home/TCM directory. And for
organization sake, I'm going to create a
new directory here just called
malware. And I'm going to CD into that
directory because this is where I'm
going to drop the payload that we
generate. And so to run MSF Venom, I'm
just going to type in MSF
Venom. And from here, I'm going to
provide the P option. And this is going
to specify the type of payload that we
want to use. And in this case, there's a
syntax that we want to follow for this.
Since we're going to be executing our
payload on a Windows system, well, I'm
going to type in Windows here. And after
Windows, I'm going to put a slash here.
And now we can specify the type of
handler that we want. In this case, it's
going to be that interpreter
handler. And lastly, I'm going to put
another slash here. Then I'm going to
provide the type of payload. In this
case, we want to create a reverse TCP
connection or that reverse shell from
the target machine back to our
attacker's machine. So, I can just type
in
reverse_TCP. And so, this means that
when the payload is executed on the
target system or our Windows system, it
will initiate a connection back to our
specified host, allowing us to gain
access and control over the target
machine. And so, we're not done yet.
There are a couple other options that we
want to include.
We need to specify the listening host.
In our case, it's going to be our Linux
machine's IP address or our attacker
machine. And I'll do that with the LHOST
option and set that to
192.168.1.4. And so remember, your IP
address might be different. That's why
we did that check first with if
config. Next, we have the Lport option,
and this specifies the listening port in
which we'll receive the connection from.
In this case, I'm just going to choose
the default of quad 4.
under F here. This is where we can
choose the file output of our payload or
the file type that we want the payload
to be. In this case, I want it to be an
executable since we're running it on a
Windows system. So, I'm going to type in
.exe. And then lastly, we have the O
option. And this provides our output
file. And in this case, I'm just going
to call our malware
notmalware.exe. And with all this ready,
we should be good to go. So, I'm just
going to hit enter here. And it might
take a second to
generate. There we go. We can see that
the file was saved as notmalware.exe.
And if I run an ls here, we can see our
file. And if I run a file command on
notmalware.exe, we can see that it's a
PE32
executable. And interestingly, when we
create this payload, it's going to
create itself as a known good or trusted
binary by default. And it actually
impersonates the Apache benchmark
utility or ab.exe. exe. And this is
going to come into play later when we
start looking into the process of the
executable itself. And we might wonder
why our malware is being classified as
Apache benchmark. But this is all done
so that we can create somewhat of a
Trojan horse. Whereas when an
investigator or different scanning
utilities look this over, they're going
to see what looks like to be a benign
Apache benchmark utility. And so now we
can set up our interpreter listener to
catch the eventual shell that comes back
to us. And so over in our first tab here
where we have metas-ploit open and if
you did happen to close it, you can just
run MSF console again, we can now set up
and execute our listener. And so to do
this, we're going to type in the use
command here. And we're going to select
the type of handler we want to use. In
this case, it's going to be exploit. And
I can just tab there to autocomplete.
I'm going to type in multi and then
another slash for
handler. And so I'm just going to run
that. And you can see that the handler
was configured. So next we want to set
the payload. And so again, we want to
match the same payload that we used when
we generated our
malware. And so to do this, I'm going to
write set
payload. And I'm going to set that to
again
Windows/terprepter/reverse_tcp. And
again, you can autocomplete that as well
with
tab. All right, we're almost there. We
need to set our LHOST again to either
again our IP address or we can use our
interface. Right? So I can type in
ENP03 and it will automatically convert
that to whatever my current IP address
is. And lastly, we want to set our
listening port with Lport to quad 4. We
actually don't need to do this because
this is the default port that my
interpreter will listen from, but
obviously it's good practice to manually
set
this. And so now that we're ready to go,
we can just type in literally exploit
and this is going to run our
listener. We're not going to connect to
our machine yet, right? We didn't even
get the malware over there, but it's
going to run our listener and payload
handler. And you can see that we've
started a reverse TCP handler on our IP
address on port
4444. And with that, we are ready to
catch our shell. And so now that we have
our payload created and we're listening
for the connection, we can transfer it
over to our Windows machine. And so on
Ubuntu, let's host this payload using
the Python HTTP server so that it can be
publicly accessed and downloaded from
our Windows client. Again, we're sort of
taking a peak behind the curtain here so
we can compromise ourselves easily. In
theory, we could think of an attacker
sending this over as a fishing email
that contains our payload as an
attachment or downloaded from a link.
And so to do this, make sure you're in
the same directory that we created our
malware in. And then I'm going to run
Python 3 with the M option here for
http.server. And I'm going to select the
port of 8000 to listen on and host our
server. And so now we're ready. We're
serving HTTP on port
8000. And so from here, I've started up
my Windows machine as well. Right? So I
have both machines running. I have my
Linux machine and my Windows machine or
our victim in this case. And so now on
Windows, we can open up Edge or you
know, Internet Explorer, whatever you
want to use. I'm going to paste in HTTP
the IP address of my Linux machine and
then with a colon here, specify port
8000. And if we open that, you can see
we get the directory listing. And this
is our Python HTTP server in action. And
so this is going to list all of the
files in the directory that we're
serving from. And of course, we can see
notmalware.exe. And if we click on this,
it's going to download to our local
system. And we can see in the top right
here that this is not a commonly
downloaded file. And so Microsoft is
trying to warn us here to be cautious
around downloading this file. But what
we can do is just click on the three
dots here for more actions. And then we
can go over to keep because we want to
keep this file. And again, we're going
to get another warning from Smart Screen
here. So, Microsoft really doesn't want
us to download this file. And so, you
can see all of the built-in protections
that are seeing our payload as
suspicious. And realistically, an
attacker would put more work into
obiscation and methods to get around
simple detection like this. And, you
know, obviously, we didn't create any
advanced malware or anything. And this
would definitely get picked up by most
antivirus solutions. And so, this is not
an AV evasion course by any means. And
so, I'm going to click on show more
here. and I'm going to click on keep
anyway. So, we're basically saying,
"Please let us keep this malware." All
right. So, now that we finally
downloaded the malware, let's open up a
command prompt as
administrator. And so, we're going to
simulate an administrator user falling
victim to this malware, giving our
attacker full compromise over the
system. Or we could assume that the
attacker was able to gain an initial
user shell and then from that foothold
escalate privileges as administrator.
And so, I'm going to click on the start
menu here and then type in cmd.
And then on the command prompt
application here, I'm going to
rightclick and then select run as
administrator and just say yes to the
UAC
here. And we now have a command prompt
running as
administrator. All right. So I'm going
to head over to the C
directory over to users and then the
user I configured for this machine is
called TCM. And then I'm going to go to
my users downloads directory. And if I
run a dur here, well, we can see
notmalware.exe. And so all I'm going to
do is just type in
notmalware.exe. And then I'm going to
hit enter to run that. And as soon as I
do, I'm going to hop back over to
Abuntu. All right, I'm going to go back
to our metas-ploit shell here. And you
can see that we did open up a
interpreter session. And specifically,
we can see that it was opened up on our
listening port over to the attackers
machine. This is our Windows IP address
on this ephemeral port here. And so we
successfully caught a reverse shell. And
so this is going to be the general
process for setting up the following
lessons. Right? So we're going to want
to keep this active reverse shell
connection so we can look into network
and process activities on our Windows
host. And if for any reason you need to,
you know, close out everything and
restart it, well, just follow these
steps once again. Make sure to set up,
you know, we've already transferred the
payload over, so you don't need to do
that again. You just need to set up
metas-ploit here. set the payload and
options and then just simply execute the
program on Windows. And so now that
we've compromised ourselves, I will see
you in the next
lesson. Again, a big thank you to Flare
Academy for sponsoring our 12 hours of
sock 101. Cyber threats are evolving
fast. And staying ahead is not just an
advantage, it's a necessity. And that's
where Flare Academy comes in. Flare
Academy is an educational hub designed
to democratize cyber security knowledge.
Backed by the Flair research team and
leading threat intelligence experts,
they provide accessible training,
collaborative discussions, and cutting
edge resources. With the support of
Flair's industry-leading research team,
members gain access to hands-on insights
and training while connecting with peers
and experts to tackle the toughest and
newest challenges together. This is
through practical sessions designed to
solve real world cyber security
challenges. The opportunity to engage
with industry leaders, researchers, and
fellow professionals to grow your
skills, community meetups to share
insights and experiences in both virtual
and in-person events, and exclusive
research and tools such as access to
cutting edge reports, tooling, and
intelligence from Flair's experts
tailored specifically for the community.
With Flare, you can learn and grow
through in-depth training sessions on
credential management, reconnaissance
techniques, OSENT, and much more.
Delivered by industry leaders like Jason
Hadex, and backed by Flair's research
team. You'll get exclusive access to
expertly crafted solutions, playbooks,
and session materials designed to
address real world cyber security
challenges. You'll be able to
participate in expert-led discussions
and Q&A channels and stay ahead of
emerging threats with exclusive reports,
feeds, and insights from Flair's
comprehensive cyber crime intelligence.
And verified members gain access to
premium resources and private insights
while contributing to a community that
thrives on shared knowledge. And so, if
you're ready to level up, join Flare
Academy today through the link in the
description. All righty, my friends.
Sadly, we are going to need to cap
things off for now, but I really hope
you enjoyed everything we covered up to
this point. You know, we really only did
scratch the surface of the full sock 101
curriculum. And I'm kind of leaving you
on a bit of a cliffhanger here because
the endpoint security section is really
where things start to pick up in the
course and really where we start to
correlate some of the different things
we're seeing on the network side. Uh,
and also how we can hunt malware and
different persistence techniques uh and
even perform a bit of sort of live
incident response on the endpoint level.
um and even working with an EDR as well.
And then of course, as we talked about
earlier, we start talking about the SIM
and we start working with Splunk uh and
how we can ingest logs and work with
logs and sort of cut them up as well uh
manually and also using tools like a
SIM. And of course, we get into threat
intelligence and how we can collect and
ingest and use uh sort of the the
intelligence we're ingesting uh in order
to make better uh decisions as an
analyst. And of course we have this
whole digital forensic section where we
really deep dive into different forensic
artifacts on the endpoint uh and also
how we can triage and work with uh many
industry standard forensic tools as well
and we really roll that up into incident
response as well. So just like we talked
about at the beginning of the video, we
really are only scratching the surface
here. So, um, if you did enjoy
everything we learned up to this point
and you want to sort of continue on
further, I really encourage you to check
out the TCM Academy uh, and get a
academy subscription where you can check
out both the sock 101 and a ton of other
courses that we offer on the academy
both in defensive and offensive security
as well and even programming. And so,
with all of that, I want to thank you
yourself for getting up to this point,
right? Uh, that was a ton of knowledge
dropped on you in a condensed 12-h hour
period like that. So, uh, that's not
easy, right? So kudos to you. Uh I hope
you took good notes. If anything is
unclear, you can always go back on the
chapter sections there and revisit
certain areas. And of course, again, if
you did enjoy uh the course and want to
continue and expand your knowledge, feel
free to check out the full course at the
TCM Security Academy. And so, please
feel free to leave a like on the video
and subscribe to the channel if you
haven't already because this is not the
first time we've dropped one of our
courses like this on the uh TCM YouTube
channel, right? So, I love that we get
to do this every now and then. Uh and so
with that, thank you again for watching
and I will catch you next time.